We'll take a look at the very wide range
of planning research areas and
techniques.
There's been quite a lot of work in
domain modeling, domain description, and
domain analysis, prior to using these
descriptions, these domain descriptions
in planners themselves.
Then of course the core work in AI
planning is being in the search methods,
and algorithms for creating plans,
searching for plans.
People have looked up plan analysis
because if you can constrain the types of
plan you're interested in through
analysis, that can limit the search
spaces involved.
It could be useful to pause here and to
read through this list of areas and
techniques.
How many have you already heard of?
Check out or ask about any acronym you
don't know.
Continue on when you're ready.
Then people concerned with realistic and
practical planning problems have often
had to deal with the hue of repairing
plans when things go wrong or when the
circumstances change.
A number of people have looked at planned
generalization,
the reuse of generalized plan fragments.
The sport of the user involved in
planning via a suitable user interface
is, advice interfaces and the ability to
generate plans in a mixed issued fashion
between the automated system and the
human are important.
In recent years, planners have been made
available as web services in order that
they can be used as a component of larger
scale systems.
And plans can be used in a range of other
areas, such as natural language
generation, dialogue management, the
sharing of plans between humans and so
on.
Pause again, to look at the research
areas and techniques listed.
So as you can see here, we're dealing
with the whole life-cycle plans, right
through from, creating domain models,
to making use of those plans in
productive situations.
The problem is that we need to make sense
of all of this.
We need to find a way of fitting in the
very many techniques that are available
now and that will become available
through further research and development.
What's needed is more collaborative
planning framework.
At the alta level, we've got to be able
to relate to the humans involved in the
planning process,
where they can present their objectives,
their issues,
they can make sense of the situation.
They can give multiple options and
advice.
They can argue about those options,
discuss them, outline plans, and so on.
Then we want detailed planners, search
engines, constraints, all that analyzers
and simulators, that can act within that
outdoor frame, and work in an
understandable way,
and use it to provide feasibility checks,
detailed constraints, and guidance.
Want to be able to share processes and
information about process products
between humans and systems,
and want to look at the current status,
the context we're in, the environment
we're in, you know, to be sensitive to
that.
We need a link between informal and
unstructured planning and more structured
planning and methods for optimization.
And that's what we've been trying to do
with our I X I plan work, just as an
example of how some of this integration
is going on in practical A I planning
systems.
First of all, we base it on an
underlying, intelligible, easily
communicated, easily extended, conceptual
model for objectives, processes,
procedures and plans.
Just based on four components, a set of
issues to be addressed, a set of nodes,
which are activities to be included in
the plan, a set of constraints which have
got to be respected and a set of
annotations on the entities that are
involved there.
We call that model INCA.
Then we want to communicate the dynamic
status and presence of the agents
involved.
The collaborative processes that process
products, and what they, what they're
able to do in terms of their
capabilities.
Want to be sensitive to the current
context so the presentation of options
for action are those which are suitable
for the context we're in.
And we want to do intelligent activity
planning, execution and monitoring
repair, and plan repair, and we do that
via the iPlan planner and what we call
the IX process panels, which are the user
interface element in the IX technology.
So IXs aim is a planning workflow and
task messaging catch all.
We designed it in order that it can deal
with the wide range of problems that can
be addressed in planning and activity
management.
It's meant to be able to take any
requirement to handle an issue,
perform an activity,
respect a constraint, or note an
annotation.
So that's the underlying computational
model of the I-X platform.
They can deal with these by a manual
activity,
so you can basically, just take items
off, for instance, on checklist.
That's a perfectly good way of
representing the fact that you've
performed an activity in some systems.
But also, by inbuilt internal
capabilities in the system,
by external capabilities you know about,
or by rerouting or delegating to other
panels and agents, which is where
communication and collaboration and the
models of those, those other agents comes
in.
And all we can plan next year to
compensate to these capabilities and we
can use the planner inside the system
itself, to plan that kind of work flow.
And then the system receives reports and
interprets them to understand the current
state it's in,
and to be able to start to handle that
situation and help the user control the
situation.
And the idea is it can cope with just
partial knowledge of the process and
organization involved,
and be able to fit in to an environment
where it isn't the only agent that's
working on plans and processes within an
organization.
I-x, as we've said before, has been
applied to emerge in serious bonds, and
we've used this kind of process panel or
user interface that's what the task.
But it's in a context where there is a
lot of verbal tools.
The main editors, links to mapping tools,
the planner itself can have a pop up
window, its like you look at the options
its generating and guide them and give
them advice and so on and you can link to
messaging and communication tools to the
systems.
So that concludes this series of
presentations on AI planning and context.
We've been looking at the context of
practical systems, and we've shown you
some practical planners in use.
We've looked at the context of task
assignment, and execution, the fact that
we're often working with multiple agents,
multiple systems and multiple services,
and we've looked at the context of
planned representation itself, where rich
plan representations can be used for many
kinds of communication and collaboration
in activity and, and planning situations.
And finally, we looked at Planning++, to
try to make sense of the wide range of
techniques being developed in this field,
and looked at a model for bringing some
of these techniques together in a
productive way.