>> Hi, I'm Brad Clement.
I'm going to talk about Artificial
Intelligence for Space Applications.
I worked for the NASA Jet Propulsion
Laboratory.
Jpl was a lead US center for robotic space
exploration and has space-based programs
in the earth sciences and astronomy.
Jpl Spacecraft have visited every planet
of the solar system.
This is an aerial view of JPL.
You can visit JPL's mission control room
where you can see missions uploading
commands to their spacecraft using the
Deep Space Network.
You can also go to the MarsYard and try to
scare the rover with loud noises.
>> So why would a space mission want
automated planning?
There's several reasons.
Spacecraft are complex and expensive.
Part of that expense is rocket fuel, the
launch.
The bigger the spacecraft, the more rocket
fuel.
So cost limits mass.
Well, mass limits power, because of the
size of solar rays and if you limit power,
you limit communication signal strength
which restricts bandwidth.
And bandwidth is critical resource for
spacecraft because oftentimes, it collect
data a lot more quickly than you can send
it back to earth.
So, these limitations and the complexity
of the spacecraft subsystems, will capture
many rules and constraints for operating
the spacecraft safely.
This complexity can be overwhelming for
science and operation staff, thus
operations are also expensive.
And spacecraft have a limited lifetime, so
inefficient use of the spacecraft can
reduce the value of the entire mission.
Also, mistakes can be disastrous.
Automation promises to reduce complexity
of operation, avoid human error, thus
reducing mission cost and risk.
That's not the only reason for planning.
For a space mission, everything needs to
be thought out in advance, because, once
the spacecraft is launched, you can't
replace the battery or add more memory.
In addition, communication signals can
take minutes to hours to reach the
spacecraft And communication is not always
available.
So, the spacecraft needs to be able to
receive a batch of commands and be able to
operate on its own.
You can't joystick the spacecraft.
This requires predicting what's going to
happen.
Well, if the environment is unpredictable,
then the spacecraft should be able to
operate on their own and be able to do
their own prediction, their own plan.
So, automate planning not only helps
scientists in operations planning, but
also enable spacecraft to operate on their
own in a predictable environment.
For these reasons, automated planning has
been used by science and operations
planning to figure out what to do and when
to do it.
And it has been used for autonomously
commanding a spacecraft.
Planning has been used to figure out how
to manipulate solar rays from an
International Space Station.
It's even been used for project management
for the construction of rockets.
So what's challenging about, about space
applications?
Scale is one of them.
You could have a schedule with tens of
thousands of activities, tens of hundreds
of statement resource variables.
And model [unknown] resources can be
complex too.
There's a conflex interaction between
solar rays and the battery in power
availability.
Temperature is difficult to model and how
would you model a fall system.
Well, you might be able to model how the
spacecraft works, but can you produce
schedules that the user really wants?
Sometimes the user can't tell you what
they want.
Also, can you gurantee every plan that
comes out of your playing system is going
to be saved properly and won't crash the
spacecraft?
On board the spacecraft, the CPU is about
a thousand times slower than your desktop.
I'll briefly describe the history of AI
planning in space applications, some of
the planners and their deployments
spanning 30 years.
In the early '70s, JPL began designing the
Mars Rover and recognize that the rover
would need planning capabilities.
That's about the time JPL began
researching planning.
In the early 1980s, the DEVISER planner
was used for activity planning for the
Voyager mission and its encounter with
Uranus.
But many of the planners from the 80s and
90s is written in the functional
programming language Lisp and inherited
traits from the Nonlin planner, such as
partial order planning, subgoaling, and
backward chaining.
This is done by starting out with the
goals and the plans, which is the one at
the bottom of the page, and then
establishing those goals with the effects
from other actions.
And then establishing the preconditions of
those actions through the effects of other
actions, thus building the plan from the
initial state to the goals.
The new thing the DEVISER brought was time
windows.
The reason about metric time, concurrency
in the form of simple temporal
constraints, where time points vary within
some ranging or constrained to be within
some range of each other.
Plan-it has been built as an improvement
on DEVISER.
As you can see, it's been used in a wide
variety of applications over the years.
One thing that it did differently is it
started to model resources explicitly in
the language, and, it also took a local
search approach called heuristic,
iterative repair.
The problem with building up a plan like a
partial order is that you can spend a long
time trying to figure out the solution and
then be left with just a partial plan.
The great thing about local search
approach is you always have some schedule
that you're working with.
It may have conflict and flaws on it, but
you're iteratively working on the same
schedule, that way you don't have, have
problems with growing memory and you have
a best effort solution or in any type of
solution.
A couple of years after planning was
scheduled for the Deep Space Network,
British National Space Centre launched a
technology-proven satellite project under
which the T-SCHED scheduler generated a 24
hour plan that was uploaded and executed
live on board UoSAT-II satellite.
You'll hear me mix the words planning and
scheduling.
Scheduling is implicitly a part of
planning.
Planning is about figuring out what to do,
scheduling is about figuring out when to
do it and what resources to use.
A Spike scheduler is in use by several
missions, most notably the great
observatories, like the Hubble Space
Telescope.
Spike takes a different approach than the
other planes we were talked about.
It represents a schedule and problems
constraint optimization, like a system of
equations that needs to solve for.
Then it has three main stages, a trial
assignment, repair where it tries to
resolve complex observations.
You're going to [unknown] stage, where it
removes the activities or it relaxes
constraints of something.
With the Hubble Space Telescope, Spike
schedules an entire year at the resolution
of a minute.
That's between 10,000 and 30,000
observations.
And its user-authorizing, because it has
constraints which span several months,
such as you can't take an observation of
the same target within 2 months of
another.
The Optimum-AIV planner was developed by
the European Space Agency for the Assembly
Integration and Verification of the
vehicle equipment bays for the Ariane 4
rockets.
Like Spike, it treats the plane
[inaudible] problem with resource in
temporal constraints.
However, it's [inaudible] is similar to
DEVISERS and planets.
The Remote Agent Experiment was the first
to demonstrate planning and executions on
board a spacecraft.
There are three main list components that
autonomously operate at the Deep Space 1
mission for 2 days.
Nasa Ames Research Center is responsible
for the planner[SOUND]cheduler and the
mode identification reconfiguration called
Livingstone.
Jpl will develop the EXEC, smart
executive.
In simulation it also demonstrated the
response to unexpected events while on
board.
This is a common integration of
components.
The planner[SOUND]cheduler is at the top
with the Liberty player, underneath is
monitoring and execution, at the bottom is
the actual actuators, and the hardware or
robot.
Sensor and state information typically
flow up the layers and commands flow down.
The Earth Observing-1 spacecraft has been
operated by autonomous planning since
2004.
Eo1 participates in main space networks
through the aqua spacecraft is downlinking
images as usual, and one of them is
detected to have changed since the last
time it was finished by software on the
ground.
This software signals EO1 to span a high
resolution image goal for its schedule the
time, it's planner reschedules its
activities, so then it can smooth the
spacecraft and get the image on its next
pass enabling a quicker response to this
forest fire.
That was CASPER on board EO1.
This is this continual version of ASPEN
JPL stochastic iterative repair planner.
It's the first planner we talked about
that's not written in Lisp, but instead,
C++.
Casper is also part of the Autonomous
Sciencecraft Experiment that's on board
EO1.
This also includes machine learning
algorithms that were used for detecting
different kinds of phenomena in the
images.
In this case, screening out images that
recorded clouds instead of the actual
target.
Here, it notices that there's a difference
in images, triggering it to take another
high resolution image of the target on
which they discovered volcanic activity.
That's going to save the MAMM, EO1, and
DARPA Orbital Express missions millions of
dollars.
It's currently being used to schedule
ground antennas for the Deep Space
Network.
Proba-1, the first in a series of several
autonomy missions demonstrated on board
scheduling resource management.
That saying, this Europa planner is
evolved from the planner[SOUND]cheduler
used in the Remote Agent Experiment now
written in C++.
Its constraint programming approach to
planning and scheduling and, as before, it
does not differentiate between action and
states.
Treat them both as variables with temporal
extent, and like most other planar, it's
language is object oriented, this is very
convenient for representing large problem
domains.
And it has its own CLIP-based interactive
development environments and is integrated
with SPIFe, the human centered planing
tool which that used for many NASA
missions.
This part of MAPGEN built to help the Mars
Exploration Rover mission pack more
activities into their plans increasing
their efficiency.
It's also been used to plan out the
movement and orientation of solar arrays
for the space station.
European Space Agency, MEXAR and RAXEM
planners were used for uplink and downlink
planning for the Mars Express mission
where they reduce planning effort and
increase science return.
So what does the future hold for AI
planning for space?
Well, how about making rovers autonomous?
Turns out that the rovers already use AI
style path planning.
As you'll see, rover navigation is very
sophisticated.
[music].
Class, today's lesson is autonomous way
point navigation in natural terrain.
This is your designated goal location.
First, watch this video to learn how it's
done.
There are ongoing efforts at JPL to make
rovers autonomous in different ways.
One effort, AEGIS, integrates planning,
machine learning, and science knowledge.
But rovers do not yet use autonomous
planning.
Other parts of AEGIS in use by MER so are
constantly discovering and investigate
high valued science targets during one
traverse.
There are wide variety of other
applications and challenges that require
research and planning like human robot
exploration teams.
Tele-operated robots, mission and vehicle
design, robotic instruction habitats.
Other than the rover, there are other
kinds of planetary exploration vehicles
that [inaudible] need to handle
uncertainty brought by weather or ocean
currents, like aerobots or hydrobots.
Planning is also apart of research in
related fields, such as testing,
verification, and validation.
For example, what are good scenarios to
test?
What are good test cases?
And how should they be ordered to more
quickly find bugs or other problems?
Over the past 30 years, AI planning has
shown its value in many ways.
But still, very few missions actually take
advantage of it.
There are unlimited number of applications
and opportunities where AI planning can
make a big impact.
There are many demonstrations of automated
planning, but few are operational.
In order for AI planning to gain
widespread acceptance, we need to make it
easier to hand off automated planning
systems to the domain experts and take the
algorithm experts out of the, the loop.
User interface design is key for solving
this problem.
Farther in the future, there are many
mission concepts that will need
capabilities that deployed planners do not
have today including reasoning about
uncertainty.
There are many areas of planning research
that can have a great impact on a wide
range of applications.
I hope you found this information helpful.
Thank you for your attention.