This is the first segment of the
artificial intelligence planning course.
In this segment I will give you an
introduction and overview to the problem
we are addressing in the field of A.I.
planning.
This will include some examples and
introduction to the basic techniques we
will be using to solve planning problems.
So the first question I have to answer
is, what is planning?" And more
specifically, what do we mean by planning
in the context of artificial
intelligence?" I will answer this
question by informally describing the
planning problem that is the problem we
are trying to solve in this field.
I will then argue why this problem is
important for artificial intelligence as
a whole.
And then continue to describe some
techniques that will be used to solve
this problem.
So let us start by looking at human
planning and acting.
Humans rarely plan before acting in
everyday situations.
Ask yourself, when was the last time I
sat down and made a plan before acting?
Chances are this will have been some time
ago.
This is because humans act without prior
explicit planning quite often.
There's a number of situations where this
is the case and here are some examples.
When the purpose of my action is
immediate, I don't need to make an
explicit plan. For example, to record
this lecture, I needed to switch on this
computer. I know how to do this, so I
just did it.
I didn't need to make an explicit plan.
The purpose of the action was immediate.
When performing well-trained behaviors, I
also don't need to do explicit planning.
For me, this would be driving a car.
I know how to drive a car.
I've done this many times, so I don't
need to make a plan before I switch gears
or before I turn the steering wheel.
It's a well-trained behavior,
I don't need to plan.
When the course of action can be freely
adapted, I also don't need to plan.
This would be when I go shopping in the
supermarket.
I don't need to plan in which order I go
through the different aisles,
because I can always adapt my my acting
to what I've missed in previous aisles
and just go there again.
So the, the course of action can be
freely adapted, means I don't need to
plan.
A number of situations make it possible
to plan, though,
and here are some examples where planning
is necessary,
that is explicit planning.
So, when I'm addressing a new situation,
something that I haven't done before or
haven't done often,
then I need to do explicit planning.
An example of this would be moving a
house.
Everybody who has done a big move with,
with furniture will know what this means.
You need to organize a van.
You need to organize people.
You need to have an explicit plan in
place before you can successfully move
from one place to another.
another situation is when the task you're
trying to achieve is very complex.
So, for example, when I was planning this
course, I was doing explissive planning.
This is quite a complex task, it involve
ten hours of lecturing and many other
things, so explicit planning was
necessary.
Another type of situation where acting
happens only after planning is when the
environment imposes a high risk or a high
cost.
So if I'm the manager of a nuclear power
station, I will do a lot of planning
before I act, because it's very important
what I do and the potential damage I can
do with wrong action is high.
So,
I will do explicit planning to counteract
that.
Also, when I'm collaborating with others,
explicit planning can be extremely
helpful.
So, think of people who are trying to
build a house.
That's the people who are trying to put
up the walls, trying to put in the
plumbing, and of, the electricians.
They all need to coordinate their
activity and that means they all need to
have an explicit plan for when they do
what and in which order.
So the main lesson here is that people
only plan when it's strictly necessary.
We don't do planning when we don't have
to.
We only plan when we feel there's a
benefit to it.
And this is because planning is a
complicated and time-consuming process.
There is a basic trade-off here.
If we plan, we normally come up with a
course of action that leads to better
results,
but there is a cost.
So, if there is no benefit to be had from
planning, we're often better off not
planning.
That is, often we seek only solutions or
plans that are good enough for what we
are trying to achieve, not optimal plans.
So people only plan when it's strictly
necessary.
Here is the definition for what we mean
by artificial intelligence planning.
Let me read this out for you first.
Planning is an explicit deliberation
process that chooses and organizes
actions by anticipating their outcomes
and that aims at achieving some
pre-stated objectives.
So I will try to take this apart for you
now.
What this says is, planning is an
explicit deliberation process.
What this means is, to plan, we need to
think.
It's a mental process where we think
about the actions that we are trying to
do.
It also needs to be explicit thinking,
which means, it's conscious.
It's not a subconscious process that's
going on,
we are aware that we are doing this
planning so we are thinking about
planning.
In this thought process, we choose and
organize actions.
So, choosing means, we have some options
available, things that we may be able to
do.
And we choose some of these actions, and
we discard others, as part of the
planning process.
We also organize these actions into a
structure.
That is,
we could choose which actions to do
before which other action,
which actions to do in parallel,
what the outcomes of each action will be,
etcetera.
So we organize them into some structure.
And, the way we do this is by
anticipating the outcomes of the
different actions that we have available
as options.
So we think about, what will the world be
like if we do this action?
And the result is either what we want or
don't want and that's what the next point
is.
The process aims at achieving some
pre-stated objectives.
So there are things that we want to have
true in the world,
these are our objectives,
and by anticipating the outcomes, we can
compare the world states as they will be
when we execute an action to the ones in
which the objectives we try to achieve
are satisfied.
So that is what we mean by planning.
Planning is an explicit deliberation
process that chooses and organizes
actions by anticipating their outcomes
and that aims at achieving some
pre-stated objectives.
Artificial intelligence planning now is
the computational study of this
deliberation process.
So what we're interested in is the
thinking about plans, the reasoning about
actions that takes place when we are
planning and we are trying to build a
computational model of this process.
Now that I've defined what we mean by
planning,
I want to explain to you why it is so
important to study planning in artificial
intelligence.
The goal of artificial intelligence is
really twofold,
there's a scientific goal and an
engineering goal.
The scientific goal of A.I.
is to understand intelligence,
and the key observation here is, that
planning is an important aspect of
intelligent behavior.
So, if we observe some intelligent
behavior, we assume that there is an
underlying plan and we assume that this
plan is the result of some planning.
So, to understand intelligence, we need
to understand planning, which is part of
intelligence.
In that sense, understanding planning
directly contributes to the scientific
goal of A.I..
The other goal of A.I.
is the engineering goal, which is to
build intelligent entities,
that is we want to build robots or other
entities that exhibit intelligent
behavior.
And if this is to be intelligent to us,
this needs to involve actions that are
carefully chosen and organized as we do
in planning.
So what we do in planning is we build
models of how this planning works and
these models are software models, so we
can build them into our intelligent
entities as components.
So planning directly also contributes to
the engineering goal of A.I.
And just as a side remark, the robot you
see here is the Shakey robot that was
built in the late 60s and that was one of
the first robots that used an actual
planner to come up with its actions.
There are really two different types of
planning, domain-specific and
domain-independent planning.
In domain-specific planning, we use
specific representations and techniques
that are adapted to each problem we are
trying to solve.
There are a number of important examples
for this type of planning,
domain-specific planning,
for example, path and motion planning.
If we are trying to navigate a robot
through a two-dimensional or
three-dimensional space, we need to come
up with a path through that space, that
gets the robot from one location to
another.
And to do so, a number of algorithms have
been developed to, to make sure that the
robot doesn't bump into other objects or
will fit through narrow passages.
All these algorithms are highly specific
and very efficient.
Another example is perception planning.
If we try to understand a given situation
a robot may have to wander around in a
scene and observe different aspects of
different angles to understand what is
going on.
And again, there are highly specific
algorithms that have been developed for
this type of problem.
Manipulation planning is another such
problem where we are trying to, for
example, assemble an object from
different parts and that needs to happen
in a specific order for it to work.
also, natural language generation uses
highly specific algorithms for planning,
namely the planning of utterances that
lead to communicating,
as given subject. The point is in all
these domains, we have specific
algorithms that we use to efficiently
solve a specific problem.
On the other hand, there's
domain-independent planning.
And there, we use generic representations
and techniques to solve the generic
planning problem.
The advantage of this is that it saves
effort,
so we don't need to reinvent the same
techniques for different problems all the
time.
We can always reuse the same planning
algorithms.
The disadvantage is that, this means
planning from first principles and is
often relatively slow,
but it also leads to a general
understanding of planning and as I've
just explained, that's the scientific
goal of artificial intelligence.
The important lesson here is that
domain-independent planning complements
domain-specific planning.
Domain-specific planning is good for
specific problems where highly efficient
solutions are required.
Domain-independent planning is good if we
need to plan from first principles for
the type of situation I've explained
earlier,
situations we have never seen before for
example.
So the two types of planning complement
each other.
But in this course, we will focus on
techniques for domain-independent
planning.
So here's a little quiz to test your
understanding so far.
The following five statements are either
true or false.
Please tick the box for the statements
that are true.
The first statement, people only plan
when they have to because the benefit of
an optimal plan does not justify the
effort of planning is true.
The second statement for humans planning
as a subconscious process, which is why
computational planning so hard is false.
The reason is that planning is not a
subconscious process.
We have defined planning as the explicit
deliberation process, so it needs to be
conscious.
Third statement, planning involves a
mental simulation of actions to foresee
future world states and compare them to
goals,
that statement is true.
fourth statement, in artificial
intelligence, planning is concerned with
the search for computationally optimal
plans,
that statement is false.
We're not only after optimal plans,
we also want to sometimes find out
whether a plan exists at all, whether
it's optimal or not.
Finally, domain-specific planning is used
when efficiency is vital,
whereas domain-independent planning is
good for planning from first principles.
That statement is true again.