Now, that you understand what it means
for a plan to be a solution to an HTN
planning problem, we can turn to the
algorithm that finds these solutions.
So we will now look at the planning
procedures that refine task networks
until we have solutions to our planning
problems.
And here is the pseudo code for the
Ground-TFD procedure.
TFD here stands for Total order Forward
Decomposition.
This procedure deals with total order
problems and domains only.
It does a forward decomposition meaning
it always starts from the initial state
and tries to build the plan out from
there.
And the D is simply for decomposition so
it uses methods to solve HTN planning
problems.
And the input to this records of function
is a planning problem.
So, we have an initial state, a total
order task network, a set of operators
and a set of methods.
The outline of the procedure then follows
exactly the definition we've just seen.
So, first we have the case where we deal
with an empty task network as input.
Then we have the case where the first
task in the given task network is
primitive.
And finally, we have the case where the
first task in the given task network is
non primitive.
The simplest case where k is = to zero.
That means we have no tasks in our
initial task network.
And that means.
The empty plan is a solution for this
task network as given in the definition.
Then, we're dealing with the case where
T1 is primitive.
That means there must be an operator that
has the same name as this task.
And that means, there must be actions
that are instances of this operator.
And that have the same name as the task
instantiated with some substitution
sigma.
And.
These actions may be applicable in our
state S.
So we're only looking at actions that are
applicable in our state S.
And that's what we do here.
We compute the set of actions that are
unifiable with our first task, t1, and
are applicable in S.
And that's the set actions here.
If this set is empty, then there is no
way to accomplish this primitive task and
that means we can return failure or we go
back to the nearest backtrack point.
Otherwise, we can choose one of these
actions from our set of actions and
refine our plan in that way.
Note that this choosing here is a
non-deterministic choice point, so that
means we may have to backtrack here and
try a different path, if we fail in the
current branch.
Then we apply the definition of a
solution here. That said, a plan is a
solution to a planning problem, if a
modified plan, is a solution to a
modified planning problem.
And we do this by recursively calling
ground TFD here, with the modified
planning problem.
Problem is modified as follows; we first
compute the successor of the initial
state given our chosen action and that's
our new initial state.
Then we take the remainder of our task
network consisting of the tasks t2
through tk, and instantiate those with
our new substitution σ.
Note that t1 is no longer in this task
network and the set of operators and
methods remains the same.
Of course, this procedure may return
failure.
And in that case, all we have to do is
pass the failure back up.
Because this branch in our search does
not give us a solution.
Otherwise, the returned plan is part of
our solution.
But our action that we've just chosen to
refine the plan, must be added to the
plan.
And in this case, it must be added at the
beginning.
Of the plan.
And then there's the third alternative
path in this algorithm where our initial
task T1 is not primitive and that's what
we have here.
And in this case what we have to do is
compute the set of methods that are
relevant for this given task under some
substitution sigma, and that are also
applicable in our initial state Given as
part of the planning problem.
And this is the set of methods that we
can use to refine our plan.
And again, if this set of methods is
empty, that means there is no way to
refine the first task in the network and
that means we can return failure.
There is no solution in this branch of
the search tree.
Otherwise, we choose one of the methods
which means we have a non-deterministic
choice point again.
We have to come back here if we fail in
the current branch and choose a different
method from our set.
So, we choose a method and substitution.
And we try to refine our plan with that
method.
And in a total order network, this is
quite simple.
We take the set of tasks minus the first
task.
We remove that from our sequence of
tasks.
Instantiate those with our substitution.
And pre-pend this with the subtasks of
our method.
That gives us a modified network that we
can now test to see whether this is a
solution to our planning problem and we
do this by again calling the function
grant TFD recursively given the same
initial state our new plan that we've
just created and the operators and
methods from the original.
Planning problem.
So what this procedure does is take this
task network, look at the first task in
the network.
If this is a non-primitive task, it will
go in that final branch here where it
replaces the first task with the
sub-tasks in a method that is applicable
and relevant here.
And then, eventually, this will get to
finer ground tasks.
We will get to the second part here.
Where the first subtask in 1 of these
methods was primitive.
And then we get to this part.
And we remove that task, and recursively
call this function.
And hopefully, finally, we end up in the
first branch, where we've removed all the
tasks from our network.
And have a plan that is a solution to our
plan.
And here is an example from the DWR
domain that shall illustrate this
algorithm.
We start with the same task we've seen
before we want to move the stack that is
in pile p1 to another stack q where q is
a variable so it is unspecified.
So the algorithm first takes the first
task in the sequence of tasks and tests
whether it is a primitive or non
primitive task.
In this case, it is a non primitive task.
Which means we have to compute the set of
all relevant and applicable methods, and
choose one of those.
And that's what I'm doing here, I'm
choosing the method recursive-move from
pile 1.
1 2 pile 2, where we're moving container
1 from container 2 as the first part of
this method.
Note that I'm making all the right
choices here that will not require me to
backtrack anywhere.
Now we can apply this method to decompose
the first task in our task network and
that gives us 2 new subtasks, namely,
moving the first, the topmost container,
from pile 1 to pile 2 and moving the
stack from pile 1 to pile 2.
So that's recursive.
Notice that it's ground here, in this
method.
p2 is instantiated, and it is
instantiated in our sub-task as well.
Then, the procedure, again, takes the
first sub-task in this new network, which
is the move-topmost task.
And because this is a non-primitive task,
we end up in the third part of the
algorithm again, which means we choose a
method.
And here I'm choosing the take-and-put
method with some appropriate arguments.
And I'm using that to refine this task,
giving me 2 new subtasks and they're grey
here, because they are now primitive
subtasks.
So again the procedure would go through
the recursive call.
Take the first subtask in this network,
which is now the take crane at location
and so on subtask.
And I'll have to find an action that
matches this task.
And of course there is an action that
immediately matches this task, so I can
add this to my plan.
Then I go to the next first sub task,
remember we have removed this task now.
So the next first sub task is this put
task here.
And again, there is an action that
directly matches this task.
So I can remove this from the task
network and Look at the next first task.
Which now, is this move stack task here.
And again, we end up in the branch, where
we have to choose a method that refines
this task, this non primitive task.
And now, we're choosing recursive move
here again with different containers.
And if we refine this task, we get as the
first sub task, move top-most, and then
move stack again.
And we go through the loop again, the
first sub task is now move top-most.
And we use a take and put method to
refine this task giving us 2 primitive
tasks.
So we go through the primitive tasks
again, trying to find actions for those
tasks.
And we find an action that matches this
task and we also find an action that
matches this task.
Task and that leaves us with this task
here as the new first task in our network
and again this is non primitive task so
we've got to find a method and use this
method to refine task into two sub tasks.
where move-topmost is not the first one
so we go again into the recursive call We
find a take and put method that matches
this task refines it to two primitive
tasks.
And again, there are actions for both of
those.
So we turn to the final task here, which
is moving a stack from P1 to P2.
But now, if I'd shown you the state,
you'd see that there are no containers in
here.
So we can apply the no move method, and
that gives us the empty plan as the
result.
And this is essentially how our
Ground-TFD Algorithm works.