In previous segments, we have looked at a
general technique used in Artificial
Intelligence to solve problems, namely
search.
We have seen how the efficiency of search
can be greatly increased through the use
of heuristics.
In this segment, we will look at one of
the early systems developed in AI for
planning,
that is the Strips planner.
One of the advances made by the Strips
planner, was the representation used by
it.
The Strips representation still under
lies much of the research done in AI
planning today, and the first three parts
of the segment, will be concerned with
the representation.
Once we understand the representation, we
can see how search algorithms as we've
seen them previously, can be used to
solve planning problems, and that is the
remainder of this segment.
The first thing we will look at now, is
how states were represented in the Strips
representation.
The way we have looked at search so far
is we have treated states as black boxes.
That is we have very limited access to
the internal structure of a state or an
action.
Of course, there are some things we can
do with states.
For example, we can see whether it is a
goal state or not,
and this is necessary to terminate the
search.
We can also find out what the applicable
actions are,
and this is related to the successor
states.
Remember, we have defined the successor
function to return an empty set if there
are no applicable actions.
So, these two are related to each other,
and give us information about what can be
achieved from this state.
More simple functions about states would
be an equality test and a hash function.
We need those two to turn tree search
into graph search.
And finally, we've seen how a heuristic
estimate gives us some information about
a state that we can use to guide the
search algorithm.
But we had no other access functions to
look into the states and actions, so they
are black boxes.
But our aim in planning is to reason
about these states and actions and that
is very difficult if we don't have access
to the internal structure.
Just think about what we have learned at
the end of the last segment, mainly that
it is possible to, to automatically
derive good heuristics but this is only
possible if we know something about the
states and actions in our search problem,
so we need to know the internal search
structure.
The strips representation gives us a
standardized ways of looking at the
internals of states, and actions.
Now this is not as pretty as it here
shown in the picture, but there will be a
formal language that we will define, that
describes what is going on in the state
and what actions do to the state.
And that is the fundamentals of the
strips representation we will look at
now.
The strips representation is based on
first order predicate logic.
This means we have objects in our domain
and these objects are somehow related to
each other.
Lets look at our dock worker robot
example.
In the dock worker robot domain we have
several types of objects that we are
looking at.
The first type we are looking at are the
robots.
We will introduce symbols like these,
robot one and robot two to refer to these
robots in our logic.
So we can use this symbol to denote the
robot with the number one and the robot
with the number two and so on.
And we can have an arbitrary number of
symbols denoting robots.
They are of the type robot, that means
they all represent a robot.
Robots are of course, the objects that
carry a container from one location to
another adjacent location.
The next type of objects we have are
cranes.
And again, we have symbols to denote the
different cranes that are in our domain.
Cranes can be used to stack or unstack
containers from a pile.
Or load or unload containers onto a
robot.
As opposed to robots, cranes have a fixed
location, so they cannot move.
And then we have of course containers.
Containers are denoted by these symbols
here, these can be arbitrary symbols of
course and they are the things we are
moving around in our domain.
Containers can be in some pile or they
can be loaded onto a robot or they can be
held by a crane.
Robots, cranes, and containers are
physical objects that means they're
tangible and we can see these objects in
the real world.
The next two types, do not have that
property.
The first one is locations, which denote
places that we have in our world, again
we introduce symbols, to represent these
different places.
These could be a storage area, a dock, a
ship, or some parking or passing area in
our domain of interest.
And then we have piles of containers
again we have symbols for these, pile
one, pile two here.
And a pile can be empty in which case
there's no mass to it, it's not a
tangible object or it contains some
containers in which case we can actually
see the pile and the containers that
belong to it.
Each pile is attached to a single
location so we cannot move the piles
around.
And at the bottom of each pile we have a
pallet.
This is denoted by the symbol pallet and
despite the fact that we have several
piles and therefore several pallets at
the bottom of these piles we only need
one symbol to denote all these pallets as
we don't need to distinguish the
different pallets.
So, in a state we have objects and these
objects are grouped into types as we've
seen here.
And each individual object is denoted by
a unique symbol in our domain.
Once we have identified the objects and
types that exist in a domain, we need to
specify them in a way that the planner
can take as input.
Which means we have to write a text file
that defines these objects and types.
In this file we need to adhere to a
specific syntax, such that the planet
will understand what we're trying to say
to it.
The syntax understood by most planners
these days is the PDDL syntax.
And PDDL stands for Planning Domain
Definition Language.
Here is an example of how we can specify
a domain in PDDL that defines the types
we have just seen in the previous slide.
The first thing we do is we tell the
system that we are trying to define
something.
And what we are trying to define is a
domain.
And this domain has a name.
This is an arbitrary name, and does not
really matter at this stage.
But the keywords define on domain are
always there.
Next, PDDL allows us to specify
requirements for a specific domain.
In this case we specify that our domain
requires strips and typing.
Strips is actually always assumed and
typing is a very simple extension, but
there are many other extensions that you
can use.
The typing extension is, of course,
required for the types, we will see next.
The types are introduced by the keyword,
types, I've seen here.
And then we simply name the different
types, the symbols that identify them.
Location, pile, robot, crane, container.
These are the types we've seen in the
previous slide.
Pddl also allows you to insert comments
into your input file.
And these are introduced by the semicolon
symbol.
Everything from the semicolon to the end
of the line is considered a comment, and
is therefore not part of the formal
language.
It will simply be ignored by the planning
system.
Of course, there is a lot more to
planning domains than just the types and
we will look at that next.