So the final topic in our first set of
slides is called L'Hopital's Rule.
And this is a rule for evaluating limits.
So, it's just one more little piece of
what we started on on the first session.
And so the problem that I want to look at,
is suppose I have a function that looks
like this.
So I have, sine x divided by x.
So one of my rules said that,
for a rational function I can just of this
as the
limit of the top divided by the limit of
the bottom.
But that's not going to work here for two
reasons.
A, the limit of the bottom is going to 0.
So, it's a continuous function, it's going
to be 0.
And the limit of the top is also a
continuous function, and sign of 0 is 0.
But if you plug this thing, it looks like
this.
So it looks like it's very well defined.
Except if I plug in the, the
number 0 I get an undefined quantity at
exactly 0.
But any positive number or any negative
number it's well-defined and it looks like
this.
So if you wanted to, sort of, fill in fill
in the gap.
So I'm missing this one little point right
here.
There's a very obvious choice of what
number
you would want to choose to put there.
And so this, this is sort of the problem
if I
jsut tried to evaluate it using the rules
that I already know.
But that's not allowed since the
denomiator's equal to 0.
And so l'Hopitals Rule, let's make some
sense of this.
So, let x be a real number or plus or
minus infinity.
And let F of X and G of X be
differentiable functions.
And there's a lot of conditions, so this
is a little bit
longer than I would like it to be to fit
on a slide.
But basically, what it's saying is if the
limit of F of X, so this
is the thing I'm going to have on the top
of my fraction is 0.
And the limit of g of x, the denominator
of my fraction, is 0.
And if the limit of F prime
divided by G prime exists.
And that just has to be true on some
neighborhood around 0.
So you can imagine a point x 0.
And then theres A over here and B over
here.
So you have some, some points around X and
0.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And
you need G prime, so the thing on the
bottom
has to be non-zero everywhere except at X
and 0.
Then, the limit of F of X over G of X, so
this is not the derivative anymore, this
is the two original functions.
So, this could be sign X divided by as X
goes to X 0 it exists
and is equal to the limit of the
derivative as x goes to x 0.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And
I, I think this will be more clear once I
show, I show an example.
And then we also have pretty much the
same thing if I have another, a rational
function.
But in this, this time instead of going to
0, so
0 over 0, now it's going to infinity
divided by infinity.
So this is another quantity that I can't
make any sense out of mathematically.
but pretty much the same condition so if f
prime over g prime exists and I have this
So the intervals now just mean after a
certain number it has to
hold, so such that g prime of x is not
equal to 0.
Then the limit exists, so f(x) over g(x),
even though both of these are going to
infinity.
The limit exists and it's equal to the
same thing, just the limit of the two
derivatives.
And just a note so you can use this slide
for reference in the future.
So, if X 0 is plus or minus infinity, then
these intervals that I've been writing,
you know, x has to
be in the interval a b, you would just
think
of as minus infinity up to b or a to
infinity.
So the way we're going to use this is if I
want to now
try and make sense out of the limit sin(x)
divided by x.
So I have the limit of the numerator and
the limit of the denominator both going to
0.
So if I just try to evaluate this,
[UNKNOWN]
sense they both of 0.
I'm allowed to use L'Hopital's Rule.
So and, I can say that this limit is equal
to the limit
of the derivative of the numerator divided
by the derivative of the denominator.
So we've already shown or already said
that the derivative of sine
is cosine.
So the limit here is going to be
equal to the limit as x goes to 0 of cos x
divided by 1.
So the derivative of x is just 1.
And now this is a continuous function, so
I can just plug in
the value 0 and I get cosine of 0 is equal
to 1.
And if we go back quickly and look at my
picture,
that's exactly the value that I would want
to choose for this
function to make it continuous.
Oops, okay.
So, as another example consider x squared
minus 1 x squared plus 1.
And I want to look at the limit of this as
x goes to infinity.
So clearly the numerator is going to go to
infinity and the denominator is going to
go to infinity.
So, if both of them go to infinity I'm
allowed to use L'Hospital's Rule.
And that
tells me that this limit Is equal to the
limit of the derivative of
the numerator, divided by the derivative
of the denumerator, as X goes to infinity.
And so when I take the derivative of the
top, the derivative
of the minus one, ones constant, so that's
just going to be 0.
And the power rule says the derivative of
X squared is 2X.
So I'm going to end up with the
limit as x goes to infinity of 2x divided
by 2x.
But still, I can't this isn't continuous,
at the point where I want to or I'm sorry.
Eh-heh.
I'm not going to 0.
I'm going to infinity now.
So, still if I look at the limits here,
the limit of
2x divided by the limit of 2x, as x goes
to infinity.
So I'm kind of struggling here to show you
that you
can use L'Hospital's Rule twice to get the
same thing.
You could just cancel the x's here and be
finished.
but the idea here is end up after one
application of
L'Hospital's Rule with another rational
function that's still 0 over 0.
Or infinity over infinity.
Then I can go ahead and use L'Hospital's
Rule again.
And so I, I end up with where I was
before.
Take the derivative one more time, so now
I end up with 2
over 2, and that's always going to be
equal to 1, regardless of x.
So the limit as x goes to infinity of
that, is going to be 1.