So now I'll talk about some extensions of
the chain rule for functions of several
variables.
So suppose f of x is a differentiable
function.
And so here I'm, I'm starting out again
just as functions
of one variable and then we'll try and
generalize from there.
And x is equal to g of t, where g of t is
also a differentiable function.
And
I can think of f as a function of t just
by, you know.
First I'll calculate x by evaluating g at
t, and then I'll evaluate f at that
number.
And so then by the, this is the, the
single
variable chain rule, I have derivative of
f with respect
to t is equal to derivative of f with
respect
to x times the derivative of x with
respect to t.
And so if I want to evaluate the log of
cosine of t.
With respect to t, so here, log is playing
the
role of f, and cosine is playing the role
of g.
So f is equal to log of x, and x is equal
to cosine of t.
So x is equal to g of t is equal to cosine
of t.
So to take the derivative of this I'm just
going to,
it's going to be a straightforward
application of the chain rule.
So the derivative of f with respect to x,
so that's the logarithm.
The derivative of the logarithm is just
one over x.
Oh and I guess this reminds me of
something, so.
Somebody asked me after class last time
what the difference between log and
natural log?
And, so for this class I actually
mean the same thing.
So when I write log just like this, I mean
log with a base e.
If I want it to be a log with a different
base I'll write sub base, so it will be.
Log and the subscript ten would be what
your
log button on, you know, old calculators
used to do.
I'm doing it this way just because later
in
the course we'll be using a program called
R.
And when you use the log function in R, it
calculates a natural logger rhythm even
though it's spelled log.
Generally, in mathematics when you get
sort of
higher, further along, l, o, g means
natural log.
And in engineering you have l n for
natural logarithm.
So, 1 over x is the derivative of log x,
when
the log function is using e as its base.
So here, when I take the derivative of f,
I get 1
over x, and then I have to multiply that
times dx dt.
And so here.
G of t or dx dt is just going to be
the derivative of cosign of t with respect
to t.
So that's minus sine of t.
So then I end up with minus 1 over cosine
of t so x
remember is cosine of t times the sine of
t and that's equal to.
So sine of t divided by cosine of t,
that's the tangent of t and so then it's
negative, so I get minus tangent of t.
So now let's see what happens when we have
a function of two variables.
So, f of xy,
it's differentiable again.
This time I'm going to define x to be a
function g of t.
And y to be a function h of t.
Where g and h are also both differentiable
functions.
But in this specific case now, f is a
function of two variables.
But g.
And h are both functions of t, so f of xy
is
actually only a function of one variable.
It's sort of like in the pricing formula I
had in the
first set of slides, I have this d one and
d two.
They are both functions of the same
variables.
I guess that'll be a better example when I
let,
g and h be functions of more than one
variable.
But essentially what you are sort of doing
is you're getting to
a function of t by way of a function of x
and y.
And so I can think of f of xy.
If I evaluate, so if I replace the x just
by g of t, which gives me my
x coordinate, and by h of t, y by h of t,
which gives me my y coordinate.
Then, this function here is really just a
function of t, and its derivative.
So here, I'm getting kind of clever with
the d' s and the partial symbols.
So, because f is only a function of one
variable
t, I can actually write a complete
derivative for f.
But the way I'm going to get that is I'm
going
to take the partial derivative of f with
respect to x.
So that's going to be a function of x and
y but
then by the chain rule I have to multiply
this by.
So this is going to be d u d t.
So g prime of t.
So whatever gave me this.
So here it's going to be advantageous to
use the,
the other notation, which will be in the
next line.
[COUGH]
And then I'm also going to take the
partial derivative.
With respect of f with respect to y,
that's
going to be a function of x and y again.
But then I have to evaluate that I'm sorry
multiply that by h prime of t.
So this is, this is the chain rule popping
out again, but I'm basically, what I'm
trying to do is capture how f is going to
react to a change in x.
And how f is going to react to a change in
y, and
then multiply that by how fast those are
changing with respect to t.
And when I add those together, that's
going to be
giving me my full derivative of F with
respect to t.
And this, is not something that you're
supposed to just look at
and understand, this is sort of the
definition of the chain rule.
When I define a function this way.
And so it's a little bit more clear when I
write
the, when I write out the chain rule using
this notation.
So I have df dt, so the full derivative of
f with respect to t, so I just take
the partial of f with respect to x and
multiply
that times the derivative of x with
respect to t.
And then I do the same thing with the
partial derivative of f with respect to y,
times the
partial, times the derivative of y with
respect to t.
And so the, the, here, f is a function of
two variables, so I have to think of doing
partial derivatives.
But here, x.
And y, these are just functions of the
single variable t, so I get full
derivatives there.
So we can do a quick example of this.
So suppose I let
f of xy equal x squared plus y plus xy
cubed,
and x is equal to e to the 2t, and y is
equal to t squared.
So first just to make sure that, you know,
I'm not selling snake oil I suppose, I'm
going to do this by direct computation.
So one way to make this into a function
of t alone is just to in the function
itself, replace x.
By e to the 2 t, and replace all the y's
by t squareds.
So if I do that, I get f of t is e to the
4t.
So that's just e to the 2t squared.
T squared, that's, came from my y.
And then y cubed this going to give me t
to the sixth
and the x is going to give me e to the 2t,
and
then I will take the derivative of this
with respect to t.
So, it's pretty easy.
I can do the first two just term by term
so.
Here I've cheated a little bit with the
chain rule
I skipped doing the substitution, but
that's 4e to the 4t.
T squared by the power rules just going to
be 2t.
And then here I have a function of t times
another function of
t so I have to use the product rule.
So that says derivative of the first
function so derivative of t to the
sixth and sixth t to the fifth times the
second function plus the first function
[COUGH]
times the derivative of the second
function.
And so that tells me that the derivative
of
f with respect to t is this expression
here.
Let's see, yeah, so, that's as simple as
it's going to get so it's not particularly
pretty.
But it's also ugly enough that if we get
the exactly the
same thing I'm not going to think that it
just happened by chance.
So, we'll try this again, this time using
the chain
rule So first I'm going to calculate all
the pieces I need.
So, I'll need the derivative of f with
respect to
x, the partial derivative of f with
respect to x.
So, that's pretty easy to see using
linearity and the power rule.
And the partial derivative of f with
respect to y.
And then I need the derivative of x with
respect to t, so that's 2e
to the 2t, and the derivative of y with
respect to t, so that's just 2t.
So remember x was equal to e to the 2t,
and y was equal to t squared.
And so now my expression for the
derivative.
With respect to t of f of xy was the
partial of f
with respect to x times the derivative of
x with respect to t.
Plus the derivative of f, sorry partial of
f with respect
to y times the derivative of y with
respect to t.
[COUGH]
So, I'll just go ahead and from the things
I've already calculated plug those in.
So, hopefully, it's clear where all of
that came
from, just each one of these shows up
here.
And, now, I need to get the answer in
terms of t so
I'll just substitute n, the expressions
for t for, for x and y.
Okay.
And then I just threw a little bit of
simplication,
and I think, so let's see, I put it in The
terms with, the polynomial bit descending.
So I have a t to the sixth term.
A t to the fifth term.
A t term, and a t to the zero term.
Just, that's how I'm going to put these in
order.
And so, was that.
Go back to the last thing.
So here I had t to the 6th term, 2e to the
2t,
t to the 5th term, t term, and t to the 0
term.
So,
so using the chain rule we got the same
result that we did using the direct
calculation.
Okay,
and so
now we'll let again, f of xy be a
differentiable function.
But now we're going to allow x to be a
function of
two other variables.
And y to be a function of two of them, the
same two other variables.
So we can express, we can write s, x as a
function
of s and t and y as a function of s and t.
And here, g and h, so these functions that
give me
x and t, x and y, also need to be
differentiable functions.
So, then if I re-write the function like
this, I can
think of my function f as a function of s
and t.
And I can write the derivatives.
So now because f of x is again, or f is
again a function of two variables.
I've just changed variables from x and y
to s and t.
I'm going to end up with two partials for
f, for f.
So have partial f, partial s.
And there I'm just going to get that
by both of these are equivalent, just
depending on
whether you want to think of the name of
the function that gives you x as x or
if you want to consider it g.
But essentially, I just have to add up.
The, the partials that give me my partial
with respect to S.
So I take the partial of f with respect
with s, times, the partial of, sorry,
partial of f with respect to x times the
partial of f with respect to s.
And I'm going to add that to partial to f
with respect to y times the partial
of y with respect to s.
And that sort of captures, all of the
dependents of my function f, on the
variable f.
And then I can do exactly the same thing
for the variable t.
[SOUND]
And so in general If f is a function of n
variables.
And for each i and 1 to n, x i.
So all I'm saying here is
each one of those variables, is in turn a
function of m other variables.
Then the partial derivative of f with
respect to tj so t
is one of my, sort of, second level
variables, is
given by this formula.
So it just says the partial of f with
respect to tj is equal to the sum Of the
partial of f with respect to
each argument of f times the partial of
the argument with respect to t j
so really what i am trying to do is just
capture all of the dependence of f on this
t
j and add those together and that's
going to give me
the partail of f with respect to t sub j.
And I worked through a very complicated
example of this as well.
I think.
So I'll just let you look at how I'm
setting it up.
So I have f is now a function of three
variables.
Given by this, again not very pretty
expression, and then each one of the
arguments of f, so x1, x2, x3 is in turn a
function of two variables.
So that means even though when I want to
write down F.
I see three things here.
There's really only kind of two degrees of
freedom, there's,
there's t1 and t2 that are affecting how f
changes.
And to calculate the partial, I'm just
going to take the partial of f, with
respect to the first argument, times the
partial of that wirh respect to t1.
Add that to the same thing for the second
argument..
And add that to the same thing for the
third argument.
I think I actually did all of this, but
I'm.
It's just algebra, so you have it all on
the slide if you would like to go through
it.
It comes from
the textbook too, so I think the reason I
chose to
do this was just I was reading the book
and thought,
that's way too complicated To go sort of
directly from here
to here, so, now you have an explanation,
if you need it.