Next up is polar coordinates.
So this is going to be last, last time
we talked about, change of variables for
double integrals.
And then I gave you one sort of contrived
change of variables, just
to show how you could change a very
funny-looking domain into a nice square.
another useful change of variables is
to change into something called polar
coordinates.
And so in the xy plane I think everybody's
familiar with describing a point as
an x value comma y value, but that's not
the only way you could do it.
And in polar coordinates, we're going to
describe points, so I'm
calling that xy plane this funny shaped or
funny drawn r squared.
And that just means, you know, I have a
real number
on the x axis and a real number on the y
axis.
So it's giving me coordinates in the xy
plane.
But instead of using x and y, I'm going to
describe them as a distance
r from the origin, and then an angle theta
from the positive
x-axis.
So angle theta is angle counterclockwise
from the, the positive
x-axis, and then the way you'll move
between x and y coordinates and
polar coordinates or, if I know what r and
theta are.
Then I can recover the x coordinate by
evaluating r cosine
theta, and I can recover the y coordinate
by evaluating r sin theta.
I think, I have a picture.
So if I
have a point x0 y0, in x
y coordinates I would call it x0 y0, in
polar coordinates I'm going to call it r0.
So it's the length of this dotted line
here, away from the origin.
And then it has, it makes an angle theta
0, with a positive x axis.
And then if you just drop the line
down here, you'll see that makes a right
triangle.
So if I, if I take
a line parallel to the y axis, that goes
through the point x naught y naught, I'll
end up with a right triangle.
And the height of that triangle
is going to be one of the legs of that
right triangle, and so the definition
of the sign of an angle is this leg
divided by.
The and by the hypotenuse, and I know
the hypotenuse is r zero, r naught.
So, that's how I can recover the x
coordinate, using r, whoops sorry,
y coordinate, using r assigned data.
And then the same thing is going to happen
for the x coordinate.
So, I have this right triangle.
The bottom leg is just the ratio of that
length
to the hypotenuse so that length divided
by r naught.
That's the cosine of theta, and so that's
how I'm going to recover my x coordinate.
So, for any point in the x-y plane,
there's one way of writing it as x comma
y and one equivalent way of writing it as
r
comma theta except for one point, which is
the origin.
And that's a little bit trickier in polar
coordinates, because if
I have r equals 0, I can have theta equal
anything.
So there's you know, there's an infinite
number
of ways to describe the origin in polar
coordinates.
But it turns out that in practice that's
just because it's only occurring at one
point, that doesn't cause too many
problems.
So the change of variables when I want to
move from,
from xy coordinates to polar coordinates,
I've defined it this way.
And so the partial derivatives of this
change of variables
are going to be, so I have to have dx, dr.
there'll be four of them.
So, dx, dr, and dx, d theta, and then dy,
dr, dy, d, theta.
So, dx dr, that's an easy one to take the
derivative of.
Dx d theta, so the derivative of cosine is
negative sine, so I just end up with
negative
r sine theta.
Dy dr is just going to be sine theta, and
then the derivative of sine is
cosine, don't need to change the sine for
that one so I end up with r cosine theta.
The Jacobian is then going to be so it's
dx, dr, dy, d theta, so cosine theta times
r cos theta.
So that gives me, that'll be r cos squared
theta.
And then I'm going to subtract the partial
of x with respect to theta.
So that was minus r sin theta times sin
theta,
and hopefully you sort of see where this
is going now.
So I can factor an r out of this whole
thing.
And I'm left with r times the
quantity cosine squared theta plus sine
squared theta
and this quantity is equal to 1.
So I end up with the Jacobian just being
r.
And then, because I've defined r as a
distance from the point
to the origin, I know it's going to be
greater than 0.
So when I stick, I, it simplifies things.
I don't have to worry about taking the
absolute value of the Jacobian.
So I can change an integral that's given
to me in terms
of x and y into an integral in terms of r
and theta.
So I just replace the x coordinate with r
cosine theta.
I replace the y with r sine theta.
I have to multiply by the absolute value
of the Jacobian, and then that, oops, that
changes it into an integral in terms of
r and theta rather than x and y.
And the only tricky part then is the
domain of integration.
If I consider the xy plane, you know, the
domain of integration is going to be the
same shape.
But I'm going to have to describe that
differently, because
it's going to be Very different, in terms,
when i have
to describe that in terms of R in theta
than it
is when I'm describing it in terms of X
and Y.
So, some easy domains.
So, in this case, I, I've written D zero
comma R,
and by this I just mean a disk of radius R
centered at the origin.
So this 0 is the center and R is the
radius of the disk.
And so this is going to be something
that's very easy to describe
in polar coordinates but there was more
difficult to describe in xy coordinate.
So this is the, this is the shape I was
getting at when I would do something like
integrate x from
minus 1 to 1.
And then I'd integrate y from the negative
square root of 1
minus x squared to the positive square
root of 1 minus x squared.
That would be describing the same region,
but
it's something that I can describe very
easy.
So it's just 0 to r.
And then 0 to 2 pi, in polar coordinates.
but it's a much more difficult description
when I'm working with x and y coordinates.
And then another useful trick for using
polar coordinates is if I'm talking
about the entire plane, so this would
be the equivalent of integrating.
Here I've written this, again kind of
funny r squared to
mean the entire xy plane.
If I wrote this as an iterated integral it
would minus infinity to
infinity for the dy and then minus
infinity to infinity for the dx.
And so this is the kind of integral I
would be doing if you're taking 461 when
you're, when you're computing expected
values so you would
often have to integrate over the entire
real line.
If it's a probability density function
of two variables, then you have to
integrate over the entire plane.
And so you can integrate over the entire
plane in polar coordinates
by integrating the radius, so the r
variable, from 0 to infinity.
And then integrating the theta variable,
from 0 to 2 pi.
Oh, and that I, I pointed out that
this would be useful for integrating
probability density functions.
So for example, suppose I have a disk of
radius 1.
So since its radius is 1, technically the
equation of the circle is x
squared plus y squared equals r squared,
but for 1 I can omit the squared.
And then if I make it less than or equal
to 1, then I'm
talking about any point that's on the
circle or closer to the origin than that.
So that gives me a disc,
and I want to compute the integral one
minus x squared minus y squared, over this
region.
So if I try to do this using xy
coordinates,
I think this is one of those examples I've
done
a couple times before where I'm going to
go a
little ways and just say This is way to
difficult.
I need to try something different.
Let's see what ends up happening.
So I'll try once using xy coordinates and
then
I'll try once again after switching to
polar coordinates.
So you can tell it's bad again when I need
so much
space on the slide that I can't even fit
the title here.
But you can see how I've, I've set it up.
So, for the outside variable, and it
doesn't matter which one I
use in this particular case cause I'm, I'm
working with a circle.
But I decided to do,
oops, I decided to do negative 1 to 1 in
the x direction.
And then the y direction, oops, will just
be
minus the square root of 1 minus x
squared.
So that's from the bottom of the circle to
the positive square root
of 1 minus x squared which is up to the
top of the circle.
And then I put my, my integrand in here.
Oh yeah.
>>
[CROSSTALK]
from minus one to one, where does the
minus one come from?
>> So a circle that's at the origin and
radius one, what is the left-most point
that I'm
going to, if I go one away from the
origin in the negative direction, where do
I end up?
Right.
And if I go 1 in the positive direction, I
end up at positive 1.
So, that's, that's the, the region there.
And then the top and the bottom are
going to be curved, so that's why the
limits have to change.
So when I'm very close to negative 1, I
just have a little bit over here.
And then it gets bigger, and then smaller
again.
Okay, so, I started out by finding the
anti-derivative of the integrand, with
respect to y.
That wasn't too difficult.
The notation here, I treated 1 minus x
squared as a constant.
So when I integrated that, when I too the
anti-derivative of this bit that I have
highlighted, I just ended up with 1 minus
x squared times y, and then minus y
squared.
That's the derivative of minus y cubed
over 3.
And now I have to plug in my limits, but
my limits aren't, aren't very pretty.
So, once I plug that in, it actually
doesn't end up
being quite as bad as I, I thought it
would be.
So I'm going to end up with 1 minus, the
square root of 1 minus
x squared cubed in this term, and then I
have this 1 minus x squared
times the square root of 1 minus x
squared.
And I can think of this as the square root
of one minus x squared squared, so when I
do this product here, I have the same
thing here.
So, it simplifies a bit, so I ended up
with six times this thing cubed.
So the square root of 1 minus x squared
cubed minus 2.
So I have 4 3rds square root
of 1 minus x squared cubed.
and this is where I, I sort of got sick,
also
realized it wasn't going to fit on the
rest of the slide.
So I stuck it into Wolfram Alpha just to
see what it
would give me as the, as the correct you
know, exact answer.
So, this, this is my little dots saying
lots of work.
And you end up with
this which, you can actually.
It's so, you know, once you've done
something like
this with Wolfram Alpha, you know, this,
if it's
being evaluated from minus 1 to 1, it's
the
anti-derivative of this being evaluated
from minus 1 to 1.
So you should be able to take the
derivative of this and recover this
function here.
But even taking the derivative of
something this complicated doesn't look
like
very much fun.
Finding this as an anti derivative of some
other function will, would have been
quite a lot of work, so I'm glad a
computer could do that for me.
So the point is this was not very easy to
do if I left it in x,y coordinates.
So now let's try it again in polar
coordinates.
And so just from the first line, not only
is there a title on this slide, but
there's also
a reasonable amount of space above the
first line.
[COUGH]
So all I've done I have my d theta as my
outside integral.
So that's going to go from 0 to 2 pi
because I'm trying to describe a disk.
So to get all the way around something
round I have to
go from 0 to 2 pi And then the disc has
radius
one so the limits on my inside integral,
these correspond to the
dr integral, that's going to take r from
zero up to one.
Then, my integrand was 1 minus x squared
but I've replaced
x with r cosine theta, so that just
becomes r squared cosine squared theta.
And just, just to be perfectly clear, this
notation, cosine
squared, it means cosine of theta times
cosine of theta.
And then, similarly, for y.
Y was r sine theta, so I'm going to
replace
that, and y squared will become r-squared
sine-squared theta.
And then my Jacobian to turn dy dx into dr
d theta gives me this r here.
So rd rd theta.
And
now we can do a little bit of
simplification.
So this term, and this term, both have a r
squared in them, so I'm going to factor
that out.
Well, I'll factor out a minus r squared so
that's going to then leave me with
cosine squared plus sine squared, which I
already said was equal to 1.
So this whole thing that I have, have
highlighted right now, that's just going
to drop.
So I'll, I'll
end up with 1 minus r squared times rd rd
theta.
So the 1 times r became and r.
The minus t squared times r because this r
cubed.
And so all of a sudden, this is an
integrand
that looks like it's going to be very easy
to integrate.
And because there's no dependence on theta
inside
these square brackets, it's also a
separable function.
So let's see if I was smart enough to do
that.
No, not quite, but you can just evaluate
this inside the square brackets.
So I end up with r squared over 2 minus r
to
the 4th over 4 and the limits are now 0
and 1.
So, whenever you have something where
every term has
an r in it, it's always really nice to
see this at zero because it means that
when
I have the second part of the Fundamental
Theorem
of Calculus.
Anti-derivative at the top limit, minus
anti-derivative of the bottom limit.
This bottom one will just be 0, so
you don't have to bother doing that
subtraction.
So, I'll end up with one half minus 1 4th.
So I end up integrating 1 4th, so that
the value inside the square brackets here
becomes 1 over 4 and I'm integrating now
1 over 4 d theta from 0 to 2 pi.
And that's just going to be, if you, if
you think about
what this is going to look like in the r
theta plane.
I have a function that's height 1 quarter.
sorry, not the r theta plane.
That's with the theta axis and the, with
the function evaluated over that.
It's just a rectangle with type one
quarter, and with 2 pi.
So the, the integral of this is just going
to be 2 pi times
1 quarter, which will give me pi over 2 as
the value of that integral.