So there're very, very few functions where
you're going to be able to just look
at it and see what the area is and use
that to evaluate the integral.
So clearly, we need something a bit better
than that.
So the fundamental theorem of calculus,
really gives us
the rule that's going to allow us to
evaluate that,
[INAUDIBLE]
most integrals.
So I'll start off by defining, something
called an anti-derivative.
So if f as a function is an integrable
function, then the
anti-derivative of f, so I use f from my
original function.
I'm in use the capital F, to mean the
anti-derivative
Of my function, is a function that
satisfies this property.
So capital f is the anti derivative of f
of x, if and only if, f prime.
So capital f prime of x is equal to f of
x.
So what I want to find is a function
capital f that has the property
That when I take its derivative, it gives
me the function I started out with.
And this, so when I, when I, write the
integral
symbol without limits on it, so notice it
doesn't have and
a, and a, b here.
I'm not talking about evaluating the
integral and trying to come up
with a number I'm just putting that symbol
in front of a function.
That's My symbol for take the
antiderivative.
Sometimes also called an indefinite
integral.
And one of the problems we're going to
run into is that antiderivative, is not
unique.
So I can
Add any constant, any arbitrary constant I
want to, to my
anti derivative and when I take the
derivative of that function.
The derivative of the constant is going to
be zero, and if f of
x capital f of x here is the anti
derivative of my little f function.
Than the derivative of this quantity, is
also
going to be a valid antiderivative for my
function.
So this means in particular if I ever say
what is the indefinite integral.
Or what is the anti derivative of, to be
correct you have to add a constant
after you've figured what the kind of the
core of the function is.
And the trick now of the fundamental
theorem of
calculus, is when a closed form of the
antiderivative
exists then we can use the following
theorem to evaluate a definite integral.
So I'm going to put some conditions on my
function f, f of x
has to be continuous on the interval where
I'd like to integrate it.
Then the integral of little f of x dx over
the integral of ab is
just equal To the anti=derivative of
little f(x), evaluated
at b minus the anti-derivative of little f
evaluated at a.
And the trick here is this is true for
every single anti-derivative?
So, if I look up, here you might
think what's going to happen to the c.
But essentially, if I added a c on here,
I'm going to get c times b minus
a, and it has to be the same
anti-derivative for both the upper and
lower endpoint.
So I end up with c times b minus a, minus
c times b minus a, and so it doesn't
matter what constant I choose, that That
amount is always going to
cancel itself out, so you might as well
choose the C
that is easiest, and for me the easiest
one is usually zero.
And so this is going to be our rule for
evaluating integrals, the
bulk of the work is going to be finding
the antiderivative, capital F
>> And then, I just need to evaluate it
at the upper
end point and at the lower end point and
take the difference.
>>
[INAUDIBLE]
>> The, the constant
makes it non-unique.
So you know, I could have, if I found a
function F of f
that has the property that when I take its
derivative,
I get f of x.
Then I could also
add I could say F of f plus 1, and when I
take the derivative of that, I get the
derivative of f of x plus the derivative
of 1,
which would just be the derivative of f of
x.
>> Which is my little F of X.
So, the little F of, differentiation has a
unique answer, but the anti-derivative has
a non-unique answer.
But, you can understand it by adding, just
it's only
every going to be off by a constant.
So, for example, suppose capital F of x is
equal to one-half of x squared.
So here I'm going to cheat a little bit.
I still haven't talked about how we're
going to find anti-derivatives.
So I'm just going to start out with the
anti-derivative,
and then get my little f of x by
differentiating.
Then by the power rule, I just take 2
times 1/2 x
to the 2 minus 1, so that's just going to
be x.
So the Fundamental Theorem of Calculus
says the area under
the curve f of x equals x from 0 to b.
So that's my integral of little f of x
from 0 to
b, is going to be capital F of b minus
capital F of 0.
And I know what capital F is, because
that's where I started.
So I get 1/2 b squared minus 1/2 0
squared.
So this second term is obviously just
going to disappear.
And so that tells me, that the area under
the curve little
f of x equals x is just from zero to b is
1/2 b squared.
And so I think if I draw a picture of
this, it's pretty obvious that's just the
area of a triangle.
And so we know the formula for the area of
a triangle.
So area of a triangle
should be one half base times height.
And we get exactly the same thing by
solving this question with integration.
So that, that's a very good thing to do
when you're.
Trying out you know, new mathematical
methods.
This probably seems like a very easy
operation.
But if it's not giving you the right
answer,
you know, it's you don't want to go a
lot further and find out it's not working,
and
that you could've seen that at the very
first step.
So you want to check it on the, on the
obvious examples.
So evaluating definite integrals basically
boils down to finding anti derivatives.
And unfortunately this isn't as
straightforward as differentiation so at
differentiation.
We, we, have a set of rules, and it was
pretty clear
how you could use those rules to compute
the derivative of a function.
Essentially for finding an anti-derivative
we're going to use the
same rules but just try, and use them
backwards.
So we're going to be looking for things
that we
recognize as the derivatives of functions
that we know.
And then once we've identified that, we
can then go ahead and replace that
with the, with the function that would
have that at its, as its derivative.
So the easiest one of these is just
going to be
the, the power rule so I've decided to
call the
indefinite integral of x to the n the
anti-power rule.
I Googled that I don't think anybody else
has used
that word yet so this might be unique to
this class.
the technique is definitely not unique.
and I think this was probably the first
type of antiderivative anybody figured out
how to compute.
So, if I want to find a antiderivative of
x to the
n, while I know that the power must have
been n plus 1.
And then if I was going to take the
derivative of x to the n plus 1,
I know that an n plus 1 would pop out in
the front by the power rule.
So I better divide by 1 over n plus 1 so I
can cancel that out.
And so I end up with this function here.
And if you take the
derivative of that, I just have n plus 1
times 1 over n plus 1.
So that gets rid of the coefficient.
And then I'd have x to the n plus 1 minus
1, or x to the n.
And then just to be complete, I add an
arbitrary constant to this
because when I take the derivative of
that, that's going to always be 0.
And after that essentially, what we need
to do is just come up with a dictionary
of functions that we know.
And what they're derivatives are, and then
we'll
be able to try and use that backwards.
So some common functions are if I have
a, a function that's equal to zero
everywhere,
it's derivative is equal to zero because
it's
a constant and the derivative of that is
zero,
If I have just a constant then I can use
my anti power
rule trick, I can just pretend that's c
times x to the 0.
Define that the antiderivative of a
constant is just c times x.
And then some important functions e to the
x.
Remember this was a special function where
it was equal to its own
derivative so here it's also going to do
that backwards it's going to
be a special function where it's, it's own
anti-derivative except in this column
we should have a c an arbitrary constant
could be added to that.
1/x.
So you might look at this and think,
that's just
x to the -1, that probably came from the
power rule.
Except if you try that, you'll realize
that
this won't work backwards for that one
particular case.
And it turns out that the antiderivative
of
1/x is actually equal to the logarithm of
x.
And then here we had before.
I, I think this was the one that I asked
my phone for.
the derivative of sine is cosine.
So the anti-derivative of cosine is sine
and then again for
all of these we could always add an
arbitrary constant to that.
The capital f.
Colon.
And then also the anti-derivative of
sin(x) then -cos(x).
And so these are things where you can
either look in one of those big fat
calculus textbooks to find tables of
integrals and
they get a lot more complicated than this.
You can use computer algebra software, or
you can just try
using something like Wolfram|Alpha to try
to find the answer to these.
And so just some quick examples that, some
simple examples
again, of using some of the properties I
went through
in the last set of slides, and then And
then
some of these anti-derivative rules that
I've just shown now.
Let's consider evaluating the definite
integral over the interval from two
to five of three x squared plus two x plus
one.
So the first property I'm going to use is
linearity property so I can split
this up into three separate integrals and
then I can use the, my anti-power rule.
3 times.
And so because of the way I've written
this
down, these are all just derivatives of
powers of x.
So 3x squared is the derivative of x
cubed.
2x the derivative of x.
And dx is the derivative of X.
And then I need to evaluate these each
term.
Evaluated at the upper endpoint and
subtracted at the lower endpoint.
So here my function is x cubed.
So I'm going to evaluate it at the upper
endpoint.
I get 5 cubed.
And then subtract that function evaluated
at the lower endpoint.
I get 2 cubed.
Then I repeat for the x squared term and I
repeat for the x to the first power term.
And then I skipped some of the messy
calculations and that ended being 141.
If I want to evaluate
the integral of 2 Sin x over the interval
of 0 to pi
I can treat that as a constant times a
function I know how to integrate.
So I can move the 2 outside of the
integral sign.
And then in my little dictionary on the
last
slide, I had an antiderivative for sine of
x.
So that's just going to be equal to two
times minus cosign of x evaluated
between zero and pie so that's just
going to be two times minus cosign
x of pie minus, oh let me just show you,
minus cosign of zero
Oops, and I've done something silly
here.
So cosign
of pi is equal to 1 not
equal to 0.
So if you imagine what a cosine looks
like, For you it's going to start at 1.
It's going to drop, hit 0 at pi
over 2, and it's going to hit negative 1
at pi.
So this actually should have been a
negative 1 here.
So I would have had negative 1 minus 1.
So I would have had minus 2.
Times minus 2 and that would have been
equal to 4.
Yeah, so little typo there.
So this is going to be an easy one.
So the integral of the exponential
function from minus 1 to 1.
>> So, the exponential functions, it's
own antiderivative.
So, I'm going to get E to the first power
minus E
to the minus 1, which is just E minus 1
over E.
And that's equal to about 2.35.
And then the final example.
I'm just going to try and integrate, so
this is shorthand, when I type dx over x.
The function f of x is equal to 1/x, and
then because it's
an integral, I have this dx at the end,
but I multiply those together.
And I just write this as D X divided by X.
And so, in my little table of anti
derivatives, we saw
that the anti derivative of one over X was
equal to log X.
So the value of this integral is just
going to be log x evaluated at 4 minus
log x evaluated at 1.
So log of 4 minus log of 1 which
is just equal to log of 4 because of 1 is
0 and
that's equal to about 1.39.