Welcome to week four of the AI planning
course.
We've already seen a lot of material.
In week 1 we've seen the basic planning
problem and the context in which planning
takes place.
In week two we've learned about the A-star
search algorithm that is the foundation
for state space forward search, the
algorithm we have seen to solve planning
problems.
In Week 3, we've had two main topics, plan
space search, and HTM planning.
In plan space search, we have described a
completely new and different search space,
which we can also search.
And this was the space of partial plans.
Then we've seen how plan refinement
operations can be used to define steps in
this new plan space that we are searching.
And finally we've seen an algorithm that
is basically the UCPOP planner which is
the partial order planner that performs a
plan space search.
Then, we've gone over to HTN planning.
Htn planning is a completely different way
of looking at planning problems.
So really solves a problem that is
different from the one we've solved with
strips like systems.
In this problem, we're not trying to
achieve goals, but we're trying to
accomplish tasks.
So we're using methods to decompose tasks
into finer grained tasks until we reach
the level of actions that we can use to
form a plan.
So that's what we've learned in week
three.
And now I want to encourage you again to
use the social platform that we provide.
And this time I briefly want to talk about
a virtual world meeting space that we
provide in Second Life.
And I hope you will have a look at this
and send your avatar there and talk to
other people in this space and I'll
quickly go there now.
Just to see whats going on there.
And see who's their that's Austin's
avatar.
Hello Austin, hello.
The graph plan planner addresses the same
planning problem as the strips planner.
Or UC pop.
That is the planning problem consists of a
set of operators constituting a domain, an
initial state, and a set of goals that
need to be achieved.
One major difference to the planning
algorithms we've seen so far, is that
graph plan works on a propositional
representation.
That means the atoms that make up a world
state are no longer structured.
They don't consist of objects that are
related to each other, but of individual
symbols.
Where each symbol represents a fact about
the world that can be true or false.
The same goes for actions.
They are now individual symbols not
parameterized actions.
But as it turns out, this isn't such a
major difference as every strips planning
problem, as we have seen it so far, can be
translated into an equivalent
propositional problem.
So, for simplicity we will now think of
the planning problem as given in its
propositional form.
And here is now an overview of how the
graph plan algorithm works.
The details of this will follow in the
remainder of this segment.
Essentially what the algorithm does is
create a data structure called the
Planning Graph.
An example of which you see here.
The algorithm then, consists of two major
steps.
The first step expands this planning graph
with two new layers.
An action layer and a proposition layer.
The second step of the algorithm searches
this graph for a plan.
And here is how the first step works.
The algorithm starts with a single layer
of nodes in it's planning graph and that
is the proposition layer P0.
In this layer we have all those
propositions that were true in the initial
state as nodes.
So in this layer we have six nodes holding
one proposition each that were true in the
initial state.
That's the initial planning graph.
The graph expansion step then adds exactly
one action layer and one proposition layer
to this graph.
The first action layer contains all those
action symbols, those 4 here.
That would be applicable in a state
consisting of all those symbols contained
in the preceding proposition there.
So these actions are applicable in a state
that would consist of all these symbols.
And then in the proposition layer P1 that
we are adding in this expansion set we
have all the effects that were asserted by
the actions in the preceeding action layer
plus all the propositions that were true
already.
So this is the proposition layer P1,
consisting of all the positive effects of
these actions, and all those elements that
were already in P0.
The edges you see here simply represent
the preconditions and effects of the
actions.
When we look at the detail of the
algorithm, we will see that there are
actually a few more action nodes in the
action layer representing noops, no
operations, which were intruduced to carry
propositions forward frmo one proposition
layrr to the next.
And there are also some additional edges
not shown in this graph, and these are
edges that are internal to proposition and
action layers and represent mutual
exclusivity of these symbols being true.
One important feature of this expansion
step that comes first, is that it runs in
polynomial time.
So it is fast.
The expansion step is then followed by the
second step in this algorithm which is the
backwards search.
So what we do in the backwards search is
search for our plan from the last
proposition layer.
Are in the plan.
So we are searching from this layer here
and we're going backwards towards the
initial state, until we reach the initial
state and search for sets of actions that
may constitute our plan.
And this was a standard search following
the type of search we have seen before,
that can be done with something like the
A-star app.
[inaudible] Algorithm.
Unfortunately, this means that the
backwards surge may have exponential time
complexity.
If the backwards surge finds a plan, then
we're done, because we've solved the
problem.
If it doesn't find the plan, then the
algorithm returns to the expansion step.
So it generates a new action layer, which
is shown here.
And a new proposition layer shown here.
And this is again followed by a backward
search, starting from the last proposition
layer, and going backwards towards the
initial state.
All the way to the initial state.
Selecting actions from both action layers.
And that's essentially all there is to
graph plan.
When Graphplan came out in the mid-1990s,
it was significantly faster than all the
previous planners.
And there are a number of contributing
factors why this is the case.
And I shall point them out to you while we
go through the technical details of the
planning an algorithm.
In the second part of this week we'll be
looking at advanced heuristics that can be
used for state space forward search.
A technique that we've seen in week two.
And in this context we'll take a closer
look at the FF Planner, which was
developed by Joerg Hoffman.
And one of the distinguishing features of
the FF Planner is that it uses the relaxed
problem heuristic, which is on the one
hand efficient to compute and on the
other, accurate.
And that will end this week.
And now let's step into the technical
material for week two.
At the end of this, you should be able to
implement an almost state of the art
planning system.