So you have already seen that methods
share some properties with operators.
And two of the properties they also share
are applicability and relevance, although
they are defined different here.
Applicability is actually very similar.
So we say a method instance is applicable
in a state s if all the positive
conditions of the method are satisfied in
the state so they must be elements in the
state and none of the negative
pre-conditions must be in that state.
So the intersection of the state and the
negative pre-conditions must be empty.
This is exactly the same way we've tested
whether the pre-conditions of an action
are satisfied in a state.
But the definition of relevance is quite
different from what we've seen previously
so we want to define when a method
instance m is relevant for task t.
Since we don't have effects in methods
and we don't have goals in planning
problems, the definition of relevance
must be quite different from what we've
seen previously.
And we define relevance here with respect
to tasks that we want to accomplish.
And a method is relevant for a task if
there is a substitution sigma such that
the task that we're trying to accomplish
is the same as the task described in the
method.
Remember, the task of a method describes
what we can accomplish with that method.
And if we have a task, t, in a task
network, that we can make the same, with
the substitution sigma, as the task of
the method, then we can use this method
to accomplish the task.
And the method is relevant for the task.
And if we have a task network that
contains a task, t.
And we have a method that is relevant for
this task under some substitution sigma.
Then we can apply this method by
decomposing the task.
So we define the decomposition of a task
t, by a relevant method m under
substitution sigma.
And we define it as follows.
We define a decomposition function,
delta, that takes exactly those three
arguments, the task, the method and the
substitution.
And it simply returns the instantiated
network that is associated with the
method.
So, every variable in this network is
replaced according to the substitution
or, if the task was totally ordered, then
we can return the sequence of sub-tasks
instantiated with the substitution,
sigma.
That is what we call the decomposition
and delta is the decomposition function
for a task given a method and a
substitution.
And here is another quick example to
illustrate applicability and relevance in
the dark worker robot domain.
The world state that we have is the same
state we've seen earlier.
We have 1 crane, and 3 piles.
And there are 3 containers on the first
pile.
Now, suppose our task t is to move the
stack p1 to q.
So we don't have a task that says in
[UNKNOWN] that way, we just have a task
to move it at all.
And we want to move it from p1 to some
other unspecified stack because q is a
variable here.
The state s is as shown here so this is
our initial world state.
In which we have this task to accomplish.
Then we can look at the following method
instance, mi.
Which is recursive move, P1, P2, C1, C2.
So remember, this is the pile from which
we're moving, this is the pile to which
you're moving.
This is the container we're trying to
move.
And this is the container from which
we're taking it.
To check for applicability, we need to
examine the pre-conditions of this method
and if you remember, there were two
positive pre-conditions associated with
this method namely instantiated that the
container, c1 must be the top of the
origin pile.
And we can see in the state here, c1 is
the top of the origin pile so that
pre-condition is satisfied.
And the other pre-condition was that the
container, c1, that we're moving Is on
top of c2.
And again, you can see, c2 is the second
container here, so the second
precondition is also satisfied.
There were no negative preconditions, so
we don't need to worry about those, which
means, our method, m i, is applicable in
the state shown here.
And to test for relevance, we've got to
see whether we can make the task
accomplished by this method the same as
the task that we are trying to
accomplish.
And indeed, this is the case.
Because the task symbol is already the
same.
It is move stack,
that is also accomplished by recursive
move.
And the 2 parameters.
of the methods tasks are p1 and p2.
And p1 is also the first parameter of the
task we're trying to accomplish.
The second one is q,
so we can make these the same if we apply
the substitution where we replace q by
p2.
In which case the task would be
move-stack (p1,p2) and the same for the
task we're trying to accomplish and the
task that is accomplished by the method.
So, the method is indeed relevant for
this task under the substitution.
This means you should now be familiar
with three new concepts that were
introduced for task network planning.
Namely, tasks, task networks, and
methods.