The next component of a partial plan to
consider are the variable bindings.
We've already seen that, every time we
add a new instance of an operator to our
plan,
we introduce a new copy of the variables
of that operator into our plan.
But, of course, our solution plan must
contain actions which are fully ground
instances of operators.
The variable bindings simply help us to
keep track of the possible values for all
these variables that we're introducing
into our plan with the new actions.
But, they can do more than that.
They can also contain co-designation
constraints which says, a variable of one
operator must have the same value as the
variable of another operator but we don't
know what that value is yet.
So, we can have constraints on the
equality or inequality of variables in
our plan.
Again, when we add variable bindings as a
planned refinement operation to our
partial plan, we want to stick to the
least commitment principle.
So, we only want to add variable binding
constraints when we have a good reason
for doing so.
And the most important reason for adding
variable constraints is, of course, that
we need to turn all the operators
instances the partial actions in our
plan, into fully ground actions.
But, this is not the only reason.
In fact, we've already seen that when we
introduce a causal link to use an effect
to support a precondition, then the
effect may have variables, but the
preconditions may have specific values in
there.
So, we need to unify these to make sure
that the effect and the precondition
match, and that is the second reason for
introducing variable binding constraints.
And here is our example again.
I've dropped the second action simply to
save some space.
So, you remember we introduced this
causal link here from the effect to the
goal condition to record that we've
introduced this action to support this
goal condition.
Now, with this action, of course, we've
also introduced a new set of variables,
r1, l1, and m1, moving the robot r1 from
location l1 to location m1.
And initially, our variable bindings were
all empty so this is the table of
variable bindings we maintain, and it
contains the three variables we've just
introduced, r1, l1, and m1, and there's
no constraints on these variables.
Note that I've shown the variables in the
operator as red because there's no
indication what values these might have.
But, of course, they need to have
specific values to support the goal
conditions we want to support.
And adding variable binding constraints
ensures that this unification will
succeed.
So here is how this works.
We add variable bindings, we say that r1
must become the value robot at m1 must
become the location, loc2.
Also, the two variables, r1 and m1, in
the operator are now black because we
have values for these variables.
L1, on the other hand, remains undefined.
Now, one thing that can happen is that
the other effect of this operator
interferes with the goal.
So, we have the effect not at r1, l1
which can ofcourse also unify with the
goal we are looking at.
This would be a problem because one of
the effect is positive and the other is
negative.
So, what we can do is introduce a new
variable binding constraint that says the
value of l1 cannot be location 2.
In that case, the unification can never
happen and we're done.
The threat is gone.
We have also introduced another causal
link from the initial state to our new
move operator to support one of its
preconditions.
Again, we need variable binding
constraints to make sure the unification
succeeds.
In this case, we would add a variable
binding constraint that says the value of
l1 must be loc1, and that is consistent
with it not being loc2.
While this looks quite simple note that
the maintenance of consistency between
the variable binding constraints is
actually a complex problem.
The final plan refinement operation we
have is to add ordering constraints to
our plan.
Ordering constraints, the final component
of a partial plan, are simply binary
relations that specify the temporal order
between actions in our plan.
And there are quite a few reasons we may
consider for ardering, ordering
constraints to our plan, some of which
we've already seen.
So, the first reason for an ordering
constraints is quite trivial.
Namely, that all actions must come after
the initial state, and similarly all
action must come before the goal.
We never add actions before the initial
state and we never add actions after the
goal.
And this can be enforced with ordering
constraints.
Then, we've already seen that a causal
link, implies an ordering constraint.
The final reason is a little more
complex, and that is to avoid possible
interference between the actions in our
plan.
Remember, that I told you, that an action
can interfere with a causal link if it
has a negative effect that interferes
with a positive condition on a causal
link.
Adding ordering constraints is one way to
get rid of this possible interference.
Returning to our example, the first thing
that you may note is that the second
action has reappeared.
This is simply because I am not showing
you the variable binding constraints
anymore but they are, of course, still
there.
You can see this in the color of the
variables of the different operators.
The red variables are the ones that still
need a value, whereas the black ones are
fully ground by the variable bindings.
What this diagram still shows are the
dotted arrows represnting causal links,
and I've already told you earlier that
each causal link implies an ordering
constraint.
So, I will add those here. For the three
causal links, we need three corresponding
ordering constraints.
Then, I wanted to add constraints for all
actions that have to come after the
initial state and for all actions coming
before the goals state.
So, this will be four new constraints.
But, in fact, I only have to add one
because three of those were already
implied by the causal links, and there is
no need to represent the same constraint
twice.
Finally, you may notice that the values
of these variables, the value of r1 and
r2, must actually be the same value,
because this has to unify with robot and
this has to unify with robot.
So, that means we're loading and moving
the robot in parellel here which will not
work.
And, this can be resolved by adding yet
another ordering constraint to this plan,
namely doing the loading before we move
the robot.
And that's it.
Adding ordering constraints was our final
plan refinement operation.