So now we get to start with the actual
content of the course.
I'll start with the idea called present
value.
So, we're going to start out with, just
talking about interest.
So you can think about this you know,
pretty much everyone has some sort of bank
account.
So if you think of a savings account, you
put
money in your savings account and then
periodically the bank.
Or whoever is holding your savings account
gives you a little bit as
a reward for letting the, letting the bank
hold on to your money.
And so for simple interest,
this is the easiest possible way that a
bank can pay you interest.
money is going to accumulate proportional
to the total time of the
investment.
So here r is my interest rate.
So you could think about this as the
yearly
interest rate, so maybe, you know, 4% per
year.
n is the number
of periods, and A zero is going to be my
initial amount that I put in the bank.
And so the way this is going to work is,
it's a single
interest payment that just happens at the
end of whatever agreement I have.
So if I, if I said I'm going to put this
money into a bank
account for one year, then I would get 1
plus r times A 0, out at
the very end.
If I put it in for two years I would get 1
plus 2 r times A0
at the end of two years, so its a linear
function here in the number of years.
And then compound interest, simple
interest,
I don't think this really happens.
Too much anywhere, any more.
But you know, back when it was difficult
to do mathematics before
computers, things like that, this, this
was probably a lot more common.
Compound interest is interest paid
regularly.
So let's see if I can understand what my
slide is here.
So basically,
what's happening here, v is going to be my
value in the future, A0 is going to
be my initial deposit, 1 plus r times A0,
that's going to be the values.
Oops, that's going to be the value after
one
time period, and notice it's in these red
brackets here.
And so when, when I go to
the second time period, I get 1 plus r
times what's in the red brackets.
So that means I'm going to get some
interest on the interest this time.
And so you can sort of see that, oops,
sort of see that as 1 plus r times A1.
So you can pick up A0 is the amount in my
account is my initial deposit.
A1 is the amount after one time period, so
say one year.
Then after two time periods, I'm going to
have 1 plus r.
Times what I had at the end of the first
period.
And the way that's going to end up looking
mathematically,
is just 1 plus r to the nth power times my
initial investment.
And then, you can make this formula a
little bit more general.
So it might, in the second bullet here
compound
interest, I'm just receiving one interest
payment per year.
But quite often the compound interest is
going to be stated in a year license.
So if somebody says you know, the interest
on this
account is 2.5%, they mean you're paying
2.5% per year.in the.
But they might be paying you interest
monthly.
So in every statement, you get a little
interest payment that's going into your
savings account.
And so the way we're going to handle that
is you're just
going to have r, which is the yearly
interest rate, divided by m.
So this is going to be the number of
times.
That it gets paid.
So the, you know, the key ones are
probably going to be quarterly,
monthly or daily.
So in that case you know, if it's
quarterly n would
be 4, if montly, n would be 12 and so on.
And then it's basically the same formula
that you
have here, except that I'm just changing r
to be.
in some sort of different units.
And then k instead of being now measured
in years, it's just measured in periods.
So if m is dividing the year into 12
periods then k
equals 1 is going to be the value after
the first month.
k equals 2 is the value after the second
month and so on.
And then just so that the slide will be
useful as a reference when
you're trying to think about this later,
here's all of the terms that I have.
So, to make it fit on one line I had to
say r equals rate.
That's the interest rate.
And, yeah, so I think everything else
should be clear there.
So, present and future value.
So, suppose the interest rate is 4%.
Then in one years time, if I make an
initial deposit, if
I go to the bank and put $100 in a
saving's account.
After I get my interest payment in one
year.
My savings account is going to have $104
in it.
So one year from now, I have $104.
So, kind of in our present value,
future value terminology, I would say that
the future value of my $100 now is $104.
And present value I'm going to get just be
turning that around.
So if I know that my $100 now is worth
$104.
A year in the future, but I also know that
the present value
of $104 a year in the future, is worth a
$100 now.
And so without too much trouble you should
be able to work out this formula.
So the future value is just equal to, 1
plus r times
the present value, where r is the interest
rate for the time period.
And ten we can get an expression for
the present value just by doing some
simple algebra.
So we get present value is equal to 1
divided by 1 plus r times the future
values.
And we're going to call this factor 1
divided by 1 plus r
a discount.
So what I want to do is, discount
a future value to come up with some idea
of what that's worth now.
And I'm going to call that my present
value, and so will call
d1 a discount factor so, because I haven't
put the over
m here this is all on kind of a yearly
basis.
But just like on the last slide, we can
mess around with this and
get a discount for a finer grain of
interest payments.
And then with this discount factor, d sub
k, we can say the
present value of a payment a sub k,
received after k periods.
Is just A sub k discounted by the
appropriate discount factor d sub k.
And now we're going to look at a financial
product, or a contract, called an annuity.
And this is just a contract where I buy it
now, and what I'm buying is some future
stream of payments.
And my question is, suppose I want to buy
an annuity that pays $100 at the end of
the year for each of the next ten years,
and the current interest rate is 4%.
So how much would I expect to pay?
So you could kind of get an idea of how
much this thing should be.
Just that you know the interest rate is
never very big.
I mean today 4% is extraordinary.
My savings account right
now pays 1/10th of 1% so it's uh.You know
if we go much
further we might not be even have to learn
this accounting any more
so if I did a discount if I said $100 in a
year
is worth $100 now I'm going to be paid ten
times $1000 per year.
The money now would still be better, but
but I would be willing to pay something
close to, but not, not, never more than
$1000 for ten
yearly payments of $100.
But if we want to be mathematically
correct about this, what we really want to
do is discount each
of the ten future payments, and then sum
up all of those.
And that's going to give me the present
value for this stream of payments, so
receiving
$100 a year for the next ten years.
So, we just start plugging numbers into
the formulas on the, on the last slide.
And we get the present value of the kth
payment is just going to be.
So d sub k, if m is equal to 1, then 1
divided by this, oops, 1 divided by that.
That's my discount factor.
And then the a sub k is always going to be
100, because I'm always getting $100.
So this is the present value
of the payment received in period k.
Then the value of the whole annuity is
just going to be the sum of those.
And so I get a, a formula that looks like
this.
And that probably doesn't look too
intimidating.
I mean you could stick that into a
spreadsheet
pretty easily and figure out figure out
what that's worth.
But, you know when people were working up
these
formulas in the first place, there were no
spreadsheets.
And some said at maths class, we're going
to do it the way the old people did.
So, we'll start off with, this is just
what I had on the last line of this slide.
So, the value of the annuity is.
The sum of these ten payments,
appropriately
discounted for, for being in the future.
And so, you know, the one way I could do
it, just actually write down everything.
It's going to take a while, but you will
get the right answer,
but what we want is a short-cut, and so
the, the trick we use to get that.
As I'm, I'm going to multiply v by
whatever's in the denominator here, but
not, not with the power.
So, just 1 plus 0.04 times v.
And what that's going to do is if I, if I
multiplied both sides of this thing up
here by 1.04.
Its just going to knock out one of these
things
in the denominator here, and leave me with
this
thing on the left side.
So for the, when k is equal to 1 I'm
going to have 1.04
on the bottom here, times 1.04 and that's
where this 100 comes from.
Then I'm going to have the remaining nine
of these things and
the only place, there is a K is down at
the bottom here.
So I'm just going to change this as the
sum from 1
to 9 of 100 divided by 1 plus 0.04 to the
k.
So I hope
that's clear how that one worked, but if
its
not just write it down with instead of 10
here.
Write it out without the summation
notation with 4, maybe 3 or 4 terms.
And just do it, and you'll see what's
happening.
And then what I'm going to do is, I'm
going to write the original thing we had
underneath it.
So I had the sum from 1 to 10 of 100
divided by, my discount factor.
But instead of write, writing that out as
just
the summation, I'm going to write that out
as sum from
1 to 9, and then just add on what I would
have put in there for the tenth term.
And now I subtract these things, so this,
this guy over here is a
little red subtraction sign, I think
Manage to put a line in my slide, too.
So it's supposed to look like kind of a
elementary school maths problem.
If I now subtract
the bottom line from the top line, I'll
have 1
plus 0.04 v minus v, so that's going to be
0.04 v.
100 minus, well, there's nothing behind,
nothing below that.
So there's going to be 100 here.
This term here, oops, is the same as this
term here.
So those are going to cancel each other
out when I do the subtraction.
And then I'm going to have minus this
thing on the right hand
side over here.
So now I've managed to get an expression
involving v, and not involving the sum any
more.
And so, it doesn't matter if I want from 1
to 10 or 1 to 1,000, basically
the information I need to get to recover v
is kind of somehow contained in just the.
You know, the, the very first and very
last of those terms, if you're clever.
And so that is just a little algebra
exercise
to figure out what this annuity should be
worth.
So I ended up coming up with $811.9.
So now we're going look at this as the
number of
periods gets longer and so there's
something called a perpetual annuity.
or a perpetuity and this is going to pay
$100 per time period.
So say $100 a year.
But the payments never stop.
It just.
Just keeps going so, forever.
And I actually thought this was something
that
they invented just, you know, for
economics 101
text books to kind of work through this
example.
But apparently they actually exist,
there's
something in the U.K. Called a console.
Which, you buy and it pays you forever.
And so we'll sort of just try to do the
same thing that we did last time.
So, the only difference is now instead of
going from one to ten.
You know, I'm going from one to infinity.
And so when I pop off this first term, so
when I multiply by the.
The 1 plus 0.04.
I still have an infinite number of terms
trailing off in the end.
But this hundred does
pop out in front.
And I'm going to do exactly the same
thing.
Subtract the v.
But now.
And this is kind of clever, but
essentially
what's happening is, you know, as I go
further and further into the future, you
know,
the money that I receive 1000 years from
now.
you know, really this whole exercise seems
kind of silly to
me, because I'm going to be dead in
probably 60 or 70 years.
There's no point in me thinking about
money I'm going to receive in 1000 years.
But it's
getting, you know, this discount factor on
the bottom's getting really, really small.
I'm sorry, the discount factor's getting
really small,
the thing in the denominator here is
getting big.
And so that means these future, future
payments just their present value's
effectively zero.
So again we do the subtraction, but this
time
I just find out that 0.04, so that's the
interest
rate, times the value of my annuity, is
then
just equal to the payment that I'm
receiving every year.
And so, again, I can just solve that
simple algebra exercise.
And get, 2,500, okay.
So a quick summary of, my present value
slide.
So this is the formula for the discount
factor.
So m is the number of periods, r is the
yearly interest
rate and then k is the index for period
that you are
receiving the payment.
The value of an annuity that pays a an
amount annually at an
annual interest rate r for n total
payments is given by this formula.
So this is just the same one we had on
the previous slide, but with the a over r
factored out.
And then value v of perpetual annuity,
that pays an
amount a annually at an interest rate r,
is just
a over r.
And you can kind of see that from this,
this expression here,
you know, the 1 divided by 1 plus r to the
n.
As n gets bigger and bigger this
denominator is going to get bigger and
bigger and so the, the second term is
getting closer and closer to 0.
So, you know, hopefully this v is kind of
getting close to, to this v in the bottom
one.
As you let the number of periods increase.