>> I think you will all understand the
structure of the planning graph now.
You know what types of node exist in the
planning graph, proposition nodes and
action nodes, and you know what types of
edges exist between these different types
of nodes and the different layers.
And in the example graphs we've looked at,
you should have seen that we can grow this
planning graph in my illustrations left to
right, starting from the proposition layer
P0, which contains those propositions that
are true in the initial state.
The process of growing the planning graph
is what I call Forward Planning Graph
Expansion and that's what we will be
looking at next.
One of the issues with the planning graph
is that it is really an infinite graph,
because I've never told you where we need
to stop generating action and proposition
layers.
So, in theory, this sequence could just go
on and on.
This proposition here tells us when we can
stop expanding the planning graph and do
something else instead.
Suppose we are given a propositional
planning problem consisting of the usual
components and we start generating our
planning graph consisting of nodes and
edges, nodes being the usual proposition
of action layers, then the following must
be true.
If our goal that is part of the given
planning problem, the goal g, is reachable
from our initial state, then there must be
a proposition layer, that's called the
proposition layer, Pg, for which the
following holds.
The first is that all of the goal
conditions must be a subset of this
proposition layer, Pg.
So, if Pg was a state, then our goal would
be satisfied in that state.
And the second thing that must be true, is
that there does not exist a pair of goal
conditions that are part of our goal.
There does not exist such a pair, g1, g2,
that is mutually exclusive in this
proposition layer.
So, not only are all the goal propositions
in this layer, but they can also be
achieved together, at least, as far as we
know.
One caveat here is that this only works in
one direction.
So, this direction, that means we still
only have a necessary condition for when a
planning graph my contain a solution.
But we can exploit that and we will look
at how to do that next.
And here is the basic idea that underlies
the Graphplan algorithm.
We start by expanding the planning graph
just as we've seen it so far.
So, we start off with the initial
proposition layer and we know what this
contains and then, we expand to the graph
in each step by one action layer and one
proposition layer at a time.
So, this is our first loop that we go
through to expand the planning graph.
But we don't want to go through this loop
forever.
So, here is the condition when we have to
stop.
Namely, from the first graph which
contains a layer, Pg, for which the
proposition we've just seen, gives us a
criterion that the goal maybe satisfied
and the plan maybe contained in the graph.
So, we have to check whether all the goal
propositions are true in the last
proposition layer that we've just
generated and whether any of the pairs of
goal conditions are mutex in that
proposition there.
If and when we find such a layer that
contains all the goal conditions none of
which are mutexs, then we can stop or at
least interrupt our planning graph
expansion and do something else.
And that something else is a backward
surge in our planning graph.
So, we start from our last proposition
layer and search backwards towards the
layer P0 to try to extract a plan.
And how exactly that is done, is something
I will explain to you later.
All you need to know now is that this
search can't fail.
So, that means, we haven't found a
solution plan in our planning graph.
And in that case, what we do is we go back
to our first step and we continue to
expand the planning graph, again, we add
another action and proposition layer.
This will, of course, contain our goal
propositions and there can't be mutex any
more.
And then, it can search backwards again in
our graph that contains those additional
two layers now, and so on, until we find a
solution plan.
And for those of you interested in the
implementation details, here is the data
structure that can be used to hold the
planning graph.
Specifically, we're talking about the
structure that can hold the kth planning
graph we're generating, which consists of
the proposition layers, P0 through Pk, and
the action layers, A1 through Ak.
And the first graph we generate is, of
course, G0, which contains just the
proposition layer, P0, at no other layers.
For quick access, the proposition layers
and the action layers can be stored into
arrays and the symbols within these layers
should be stored in sets, sets of
proposition symbols and sets of action
symbols.
They should be represented as sets,
because we don't want the same symbol
appearing twice in the same layer.
In fact, since we know that proposition
and action layers are monotonically
growing, we can store each symbol in only
exactly one layer.
And we know that the symbol must also be
contained in all the following layers of
the same type.
And then, we have the edges of the
planning graph.
In fact, we have five different types of
edges, all the ones we've seen before.
So, there are preconditioned edges, going
from proposition layer Pj minus 1 to
action layer Aj, to the following action
layer.
We have positive and negative effect
links, which connect the action layer, Aj,
to the following proposition layer, Pj.
And then, we have mutex relations that are
the proposition mutex links that are
within each proposition layer, and we have
action mutex links that are within each
action layer.
The only thing that is remarkable here is
that our mutex proposition links start
from index 1.
That is because in our proposition layer,
P0, we don't have any mutex relations, of
course.
That is an initial state.
It's consistent.
And therefore, nothing in it can be
mutually exclusive.
So, that's the data structure.
And here is the pseudo code that describes
how we can expand a given planning graph
with a new action and proposition layer
and all the links we need.
So, we assume that we're given the
planning graph Gk minus 1, and we want to
generate the planning graph Gk.
Then, we start by generating all the
actions we need in our new action layer,
which is Ak.
And in this action layer, we find all
those actions that have their
preconditions in the preceding proposition
layer and that don't have a pair of
preconditions, P1 and P2, that are
mutually exclusive in the preceding
proposition layer.
And when we've got our new actions, we can
compute the mutex relations between our
new actions.
And we can do that by going through all
the pairs of actions that are in our new
action layer.
They must be different actions.
And use the mutex function that we've
described earlier to compute whether they
are mutex in our new action layer.
Then, we can compute the next proposition
layer, Pk, and that simply consists of all
the positive effects of all the actions in
our preceding action layer.
Note that we don't have to explicitly
carry forward the propositions from layer
Pk minus 1, because we have the no-op
operations doing that for us.
Next, we compute mutual exclusivity
between the propositions in our new layer.
And again, we have to go through all the
pairs that are different and use the mutex
function for propositions that we've
defined earlier.
And now, all that's missing are the
precondition and effect links.
And what we do is simply go through all
the actions in our new action layer and
add the corresponding links between the
correct nodes.
And these are all listed here.
Preconditions, positive effects, and links
for negative effects.
And that's it.
And here is a proposition that states what
I've already mentioned a couple of times,
namely, that the complexity of expanding
the planning graph is polynomial and
therefore, it can be done reasonably fast.
And what the proposition states is that
the size planning graph up to level k and
the time required to expand it to that
level are polynomial in the size of the
planning problem.
The size of this propositional planning
problem can be described by the number of
propositions and the number of actions we
have in this problem.
So, we assume we have n proposition
symbols and m action symbols.
Then, we know each proposition layer is a
set of symbols so each proposition symbol
can be contained at most once, which means
the size of each proposition layer can
never be more than n.
Similarly, for the action layers, they
contain at most all the action symbols
plus all the no-op actions, and no-op
actions, of course, we have n for n
proposition symbols.
So, the size of an action layer can never
be more than n plus m.
And when you go back to the slides, where
I explained the different algorithms for
expanding the planning graph, I've always
explained to you that they run in
polynomial time.
And that means, each layer can be
generated in polynomial time.
And, of course, we only have a linear
number of layers in our graph, Gk, or a
fixed number k.
So, the whole algorithm for expanding the
planning graphs, runs in polynomial time.
Now, another important property of
planning graphs, is that they will
eventually reach a fixed-point level.
And here is what a fixed-point level is.
A fixed-point level in a planning graph is
the kth level in that graph such that for
all i that are greater than K, so for all
the following levels, they must be
identical.
So, for all the following layers, we have
that the propositions in the following
layer, has the same propositions as layer
K.
The mutex relations are the same for all
the following layers.
The action symbols are the same, and the
mutex between the actions are also all the
same.
And this holds for all the layers
following the fixed-point layer, not just
for one.
And the important thing is, of course,
that every planning graph must have a
fixed-point level K, that is the smallest
k, for which the proposition symbols in
one layer are the same as the ones in the
next, and the mutex relations that hold in
that layer are also the same as the next.
Note that these two proposition layers
must be the same if the two sizes are the
same.
Because proposition layers are
monotonically increasing, if they have the
same size, they must also contain the same
symbols.
And the same goes for the mutex relations
which must be the same if they have the
same size in subsequent layer.
Now, if the to proposition layers Pk and
Pk plus 1 are the same and the mutex
relations are also the same, that means,
the actions that are applicable in Pk are
exactly the same actions that are
applicable in Pk plus 1.
So, that means the same actions exist in
action layer Ak and Ak plus 1.
And if they didn't add any proposition
symbols from Pk to Pk plus 1, then there's
no reason why they should add any more
from Pk plus 1 to Pk plus 2, and so on.
And the same argument can be made for the
mutex relation in this action layer
because this only depends on the preceding
proposition layer, and on the independence
between actions, which never changes, of
course.
So, once we have reached a level, where
the number of proposition symbols is no
longer growing and the number of mutex
relations that are holding is no longer
shrinking, that means, we have reached a
fixed-point level.
And, every planning graph, must have such
a fixed-point level.