You should now understand what we mean by
planning in AI. Next, we will formalise
this understanding of planning by means
of a conceptual model for planning. This
conceptual model will be a
state-transition system.
Before I introduce the conceptual model
that underlies planning,
I want to talk to you about conceptual
models in general and why they are a good
idea.
So, what is a conceptual model?
A conceptual model is a theoretical
device for describing the elements of a
problem.
What this means is it helps us to
formalize the problem we are trying to
solve.
This is good for a number of things.
For example, we can explain the basic
concepts with this model so it helps us
to define what the objects are that we
are manipulating during problem solving.
It also helps us to clarify some
assumptions.
What constraints are imposed by this
model is clarified by writing down such a
model.
We can also use it to analyze
requirements, so we can look at the
representations we need to develop to
represent the objects that we're
manipulating during problem solving.
Also, we can prove semantic properties
with a theoretical device like this. The
most important properties for algortithms
we're interested in our soundness and
completeness and they require a semantic
foundation which is given by a conceptual
model.
What a conceptional model isn't good for,
is developing efficient algorithms and
other computational concerns.
So, we cannot immediately derive planners
from the conceptual model.
But the conceptual model we are using and
planning is called a state-transition
system.
Formally, a state-transition system is
defined as a 4-tuple consisting of four
components, S, A, E, and gamma.
I will now explain these components in
turn.
The first component, S, is a finite or
recursively innumerable set of states.
So, these are all the possible states the
world can be in.
The set can be finite or recursively
innumerable, which means infinite.
But in most of the examples we'll be
looking at, we have only finite sets of
states so don't worry about the second
part for now.
The second component is a set of actions.
Actions are the things an agent can do to
change the state of the world.
The third component is a set of events.
Events can happen in the world and are
not under the control of an agent, but
events, too, can change the state of the
world.
The fourth and most complex component of
a state-transition system is the
state-transition function, gamma.
Gamma takes two things.
It takes a state, a state of the world as
input, and it takes an action or event.
So, this second component is the union of
all the actions and events and one of
those is the second argument to the
state-transition function.
The result of applying the
state-transition functions then, is
another set of states.
So, this notation here, 2 to the s, just
denotes the power set of all possible
states.
Which means an element of the set is,
itself, a set.
A set of world states.
So, the state-transition function takes a
state, an action or event and gives us
all the possible states that may be the
result of applying this action, or this
event happening.
We can now use this definition to define
some other concepts formally.
For example, applicability, we can say
that an action A is applicable in a state
S, if gamma of S and A is not empty so if
there is at least one state that is the
result of applying this action in the
given state.
And when we apply an action A in a state
S, this will take our state-transition
system to a new state S prime.
And S prime must be an element of gamma
of S and A.
Another way to look at a state-transition
system is to view it as a graph.
Suppose we are given a state-transition
system S, A, E, and gamma,
then we can define a directed labeled
graph G, that consists of nodes NG and
edges EG.
The nodes of this graph are simply the
world states that are possible in this
state-transition system.
NG is equal to S.
And the edges in this graph correspond
directly to state transitions defined by
the state-transition function.
So, we have an arc from a node, s, to
another node, s prime.
So, this is and edge in this graph and
that is labeled with label u, which is
either an action or an event, if and only
if.
The state s prime is the result of
applying u in s.
u can be action or event so we have a
transition from here to here with label
u.
So, a state-transition graph consists of
nodes that correspond to world states and
edges that correspond to state
transitions.
Let me illustrate a state-transition
system with a very old problem that has
been used many times in AI,
the missionaries and cannibals problem.
In this problem we have a river.
And on one side of the river we have
three missionaries and three cannibals
initially.
The missionaries are black triangles and
the cannibals are red circles here.
There is also a boat available and in
this boat, can be up to two people.
And they can use this boat to cross the
river.
Now, the problem is, if the cannibals
ever outnumber the missionaries on either
of the banks of the river, then the
missionaries will get eaten by the
cannibals.
And we don't want that.
So, you can see in the initial state,
there's an equal number of missionaries
and cannibals on one side and no
missionaries or cannibals on the other
side, so there's no problem.
The planning problem now is to come up
with a sequence of actions that carries
all the missionaries and cannibals safely
across the river, to the other side.
This system can be described by a
state-transition system.
And if you're not familiar with this type
of system, I would advise you to now try
to define this as a state-transition
system.
Specifically, you are trying to see what
are the world states that are possible
here, what are the actions and what are
the events that can happen in this
problem.
The state-transition function is best
defined as a graph.
And, if you've sit down for about half an
hour, I'm pretty sure you can come up,
come up with a graph that describes the
whole state-transition graph for this
problem.
So, if you want to do this little
exercise, you need to pause the video
now.
So, here is my version of the
state-transition graph for the
missionaries and cannibals problem.
To define this as a state-transition
system, we have to define the four
components.
The first component is the set of states
S.
And that can be defined as the different
world states we see here.
And these are all the squares,
rectangle that are drawn here.
there are sixteen different world states
and they are denoted by these rectangles.
So, this is the initial state, as we've
seen in the previous slide, where all the
missionaries and cannibals are on the
left-hand side of the river.
And over here on the right, we have the
gold state.
And in this gold state, all the
missionaries and cannibals are on the
right-hand side of the river.
And the second component of a
state-transition systems are the actions
that are possible.
In this case, there are five different
actions.
And I've denoted them here with the
labels that occur on the different state
transitions.
So, there's two types of actions,
namely, actions with one person in the
boat, and actions with two people in the
boat.
The actions with one person in the boat
are the ones where we have one missionary
or one cannibal in the boat,
or we can have two people in the boat.
This can be two missionaries, two
cannibals or one missionary and one
cannibal.
It's denoted here by 1m1c.
So, these are the five possible actions
that we have to to do something in this
system.
I don't need to denote where the boat is.
Because the boat can only cross from one
side of the river to the other.
The set of events is empty for the
state-transition system.
And finally, the state-transition
function is defined by all the arcs that
make up the, the lines between the
different state here.
Note in this specific problem, all the
arcs are bidirectional.
Which means, with the same action, we can
go to one state and then back to the
original state.
So, this is one arc here, and this is
one, this is one.
And all these arcs together make define
the state-transition function.
And that concludes the definition of the
state-transition system.
A state-transition system is useful
because it describes all the possible
ways in which our system may evolve as a
result of applying actions or events
happening.
But what we want to do is solve planning
problems and the solution to a planning
problem is a plan.
And by a plan, we mean a structure that
gives appropriate actions that we can
apply in the initial state of our problem
such that it gets us to a different state
in which our objective that we're trying
to achieve, as part of the planning
problem, will be achieved.
A simple example of such a structure
would be to have a sequential list of
actions that we need to perform in order.
A more complex structure could be a
function that maps states to actions so
that when we are in a given state, we can
use that function to decide what action
to apply.
A plan implicitly describes a path
through, through our state-transition
graph.
So, when we execute a plan, we expect to
end up in a state in which our objective
is satisfied.
There are different types of objectives
that can be defined for planning, and I
will give you some examples now.
The simplest way to define an objective
is simply to have a gold state.
This can be an individual gold state that
is named,
we've seen this in the missionaries and
cannibals problem,
or it can be a set of gold states that
means one of those states is one that we
want to reach.
An objective can also include some
constrains on itermediate state through
which we're passing on the way to the
goal, for example, we can have states
that we don't want to go through that we
need to avoid as part of the objective.
A more complex objective could also come
with a utility function for each state
and tells us that we have to maximize the
utility on our way to the goal.
As you can see, an objective can be quite
complex.
A completely different view of an
objective would be to not try achieve
something but to perform a given task.
So, a good example of this is when you
are going on a holiday.
You're not really trying to change the
state of the world.
You want to end up back in the same state
where you started.
But you want to do something in the time
where you go on holiday.
And that's a task that needs to be
performed.
Probably, the most common reason for
solving planning problems is that we want
to execute the resulting plans.
And here is the model for how planned
execution might actually work.
So, we have a planner that is given a
description of the state-transition
system that tells the planner how the
world may evolve.
We're also giving this planner the
initial state.
That is, the state in which the world is
in and some objectives that tell the
planner where we want to be.
The planner then solves this planning
problem and generates a plan which is
passed to the controller for execution.
The controller takes this plan and
executes the actions in this plan.
So, it has to extract the next action to
be executed and passes this to the
system.
The execution of the action then changes
the state of the actual system that we're
trying to manipulate.
For example, the real world.
And hopefully, our system is consistent
with the description of the system that
was given to the planner to generate the
plan that we're now executing.
But the system is not only changed by the
actions we are taking that are controlled
by the controller, it is also changing
because of events that are happening.
For the controller to take appropriate
actions, it usually needs to know what
state the system is actually in and to do
so it has observations which are going
from the system to the controller.
We model observations through the
observation function eta which maps a
state to set up observations that can be
made in the state.
Quite often, the world is not fully
observable, and in this case, the set of
observation does not allow us to
immediately infer which state we are in.
So, a given set of observation makes it
possible that we are in a number of
states, and this is what is called the
belief state of the controller.
Now, the model we've just seen is not
very realistic, because the real world on
which we are executing our plans is often
different from the description of the
state-transition system that we are
giving to our planner.
So, those two are not identical.
The reason is that this description we're
giving to the planner is an abstraction.
It leaves out many details about the real
world which make planning possible.
And then, when we execute the plan,
things may go wrong because the two
models are not the same.
A more realistic model is called dynamic
planning, in which planning and execution
are actually interleaved.
What is different in this model is that
the controller has to do something called
plan supervision and that means, it has
to detect when observations differ from
expected results.
So, it expects the world to be in a
certain state as a result of an action,
but it can observe that it isn't.
What it can do, in this case, is plan
revision.
That is, we take the existing plan and
try to change it in some way to take into
account the new state.
This can be done by the controller for
very simple cases or it has to be done by
the planner for more complex cases.
In this case, the controller has to pass
an execution status back to the planner,
so that the planner can generate a new
plan that is passed to the controller.
And that takes into account the change
that has happened.
In the worst case, the planner will have
to re-plan that is, it will have to
create a completely new plan from scratch
for the given problem.
Dynamic planning then, closes the loop
between the planner and execution by
passing back the execution status to the
planner for replanning or plan repair.