Before we move on to the planning
algorithms, I want to tell you a little
bit more about heuristics and
specifically, what makes a good heuristic
and how do we find these.
We have defined a heuristic in a
technical sense, as a function that
estimates the distance to the nearest
goal node.
But a heuristic obviously has colloquial
meaning as well and that's what's defined
here.
So it's, it's heuristics are criteria,
methods, or principles for deciding which
among several alternative courses of
action promises to be the most effective.
So the alternatives that we're looking at
are of course the successor nodes that we
want to evaluate.
We want to see which one of those is the
most promising.
And what we need to do is we need to
decide which one to follow first.
Of course we keep in mind the others and
follow those later.
We use heuristics in everyday life.
For example, here you see a heuristic for
deciding whether a pineapple is ripe.
If you ever go into a shop and want to
buy a ripe pineapple, this may work for
you, or it may not.
So, if you can rip out the inner leaves
easily and the fruit smells like a
pineapple should smell, then you're
looking at a ripe pineapple and this is
one you can buy, assuming the price is
right.
If there are no pineapples where you are,
tough luck.
The reason why I've circled the word,
deciding, here, is because this gives us
a different idea of what heuristic can
be.
All we need from a heuristic is just a
decision.
Which alternative looks best.
So it doesn't really need to be related
to the distance, to the goal, at all.
All we need is a function that decides
which one is the best node.
If we have that function, that would
constitute a perfect heuristic because it
would tell us which successor to follow.
And which path we should explore first.
If that deciding.
Is correct.
Then we have a perfect heuristic.
Another example of a heuristic you've
applied probably not too long ago, is in
choosing this course.
You looked at the introductory material
to this course.
And used this as information to decide
which of the courses that were available
you want to take.
So you used heuristic information about
the course to make this choice.
Okay, assuming you understand what a
heuristic is, now the question is when is
a heuristic a good heuristic?
And if we have a given search problem and
a given heuristic we can evaluate that
heuristic by looking at the number of
states that are generated for a specific
problem with that heuristic.
And if we have two heuristics, we could
compare them by using the number of
states they generate to see which is
better.
The better heuristic would generate fewer
states.
But that is only heuristic for deciding
which heuristic is better.
because what we are really after is, we
want solutions as fast as possible, so we
have time constraints to respect.
And computing a good heuristic also takes
time.
Unfortunately, this means we are dealing
with a trade-off here.
And this is the trade-off.
Some heuristics are simple.
So they provide a simple way of
discriminating between the successes we
generate.
And since we opt-, want to optimize the
time we take to research.
Simplicity here means easy to compute.
We want to have a fast way to compute the
heuristic value for a given state.
But heuristics that are simple to compute
are often not accurate.
And accurate is the other property in our
trade-off here.
A heuristic, unless it is perfect, does
not provide a guarantee that it tells us
which the best successor is to explore
next.
So, there's no guarantee that it
identifies the best course of action.
But if it's a good heuristic, it will do
this more often than a heuristic that is
not as good.
So, a good heuristic does this
sufficiently often.
It's accurate.
It tells us which is the best course of
action, or in the technical sense, it
tells us how far the goal state really
is.
So now we know what a good heuristic is
the important question than is how can we
find good heuristics for a given problem?
And this is somewhat similar to the
problem of problem formulation it's a
matter level problem.
We have to find good heuristic to do good
search.
Just as a good problem formulation will
ease search.
That means this is a very important
question.
And the answer is, there are methods for
doing this and we will look at some
general methods next.
But then there is a different question
that is just as important.
If we have a method, can we automate this
method?
And the answer again is yes, but that's a
very complex process and we will get to
that later in this course.
In fact, automatically finding good
euristics has probably been one of the
most hot topics in the AI planning
research over the last ten, fifteen
years.
So here's a general method for finding
good heuristic.
The idea is based on a simplified problem
or a relaxed problem.
Usually a problem is defined in terms of
states, and actions that are applicable
in states, and achieves certain things
in, successor states.
So what we have is restrictions on these
actions when they are applicable, when we
can use them, and which states they are
useful.
What we can do is relax those
restrictions.
So we can look at the restrictions
defined in the original problem, and drop
some of them or make them less hard.
And that gives us a new problem, which is
the relax problem.
And then the following should be fairly
obvious to see.
Namely that the cost of an optimal
solution for a relaxed problem is an
admissible heuristic for the original
problem.
In fact it's admissible and consistent,
but since we haven't defined consistent
yet, I won't go into that.
So you just, you should see why it is
admissible.
It's very simple to see because the
optimal solution for our original problem
is of course also a solution for our
relaxed problem.
We've only relaxed the restrictions on
the actions.
So, an optimal solution for the relaxed
problem can have, at most, as many steps
as the optimal solution for our original
problem, because that is a solution for
the relaxed problem.
In general, what we have is that in our
relaxed problem, we allow shortcuts to be
taken with these relaxed actions that are
not possible in our original problem, so
if we take out these shortcuts, we end up
with longer solutions.
And since this method is quite abstract I
want to illustrate this with an example
and we will use the 8 puzzle that we've
seen before and the actions that are
defined for this 8 puzzle.
So here is the original condition that we
had for the applicability of actions.
Namely a tile can move from square a to
square b if a is horizontally or
vertically adjacent to b and b is blank.
So the condition we have here is a
conjunction of two sub-conditions and
that should tell us how we can build a
relaxed condition quite easily.
Namely by dropping one of the two parts
or both of them.
And this is how this works.
If we drop the second part.
Then B is blank.
We end up with this heuristic here.
And that tells us that a tile can move
from square A to B if.
A is adjacent to B.
I've dropped the horizontally or
vertically.
And what we get there, of course then, is
the Manhatten block distance heuristic.
Because we now allow a tile to be moved,
no matter where it is moving to, which
gives us exactly the block distance for
this tile.
And if we add all those up, that's the
Manhatten block distance we've seen.
The second one is, if we drop the first
part of this definition, so that the
adjacency distance is dropped, then we
end up with a heuristic.
That's a tile can move from A to B, if B
is blank.
And finally we can have a heuristic if we
drop both conditions that says a tile can
move from a to b and there are no
conditions.
And of course this then gives us the
misplaced tiles heuristic.
We simply count those tiles that can move
to where they need to be in one step
because there's no conditions on how they
can move.
So what you see here is we've derived two
of the heuristics that we've already used
for the 8 puzzle using the method we've
just introduced by using relaxed
conditions of the actions that are
applicable in our problem.
So this concludes this section of the
course on AI search technology and the A*
algorithm.
You should understand now that a
heuristic function encodes
problem-specific knowledge in a
problem-independent way by mapping a
state to a real number.
This information about search states can
be used to make the search more
efficient.
In general, this is done by using an
evaluation function that tells us how
good a search node is.
Greedy best first search simply uses the
heuristic function as the evaluation
function but the better solution is
provided by the A* algorithm.
The evaluation function used by A* is
simply the sum of the heuristic function
for a node plus the cost of getting to
that node in the first place.
We've also seen that A* is optimal.
It will always find an optimal solution.
And it is optimally efficient.
It does not expand more nodes than
absolutely necessary.
But I've also shown you that A* is not
the answer to all questions, specifically
when it comes to graph surge.
Finally, since good heuristics are so
important for A*, I've also talked a
little bit about what good heuristics are
and how to find them.
So now a big tick because you understand
all of that.