So moving on, part 3 is going to
be Taylor's formula for functions of
several variables.
So last time f was just a function of a
single variable, x.
And now I'm going to let x be a vector.
So you can think of x as x1, x2 up to xn.
And f is still going to be a, a real
valued
function, so whatever it comes out is I'm
assuming is scalar.
[COUGH].
And a, a linear approximation of f around
a point a.
So a has to be, has to live in the same
space as x now.
So if x has n components, then a has to
have n components as well.
So if it was a point in the plane you'd
need a x con, an x coordinate and a y
coordinate.
And for x, then you'd need a x coordinate
and a y coordinate for the point a as
well.
And then linear approximation around the
point a, it looks a lot like the
Taylor polynomial for the function of a
single variable, so I have.
One point, f of a, where I know what the
function
value is and then I'm just going to add a
linear approximation.
So, for each of the directions, I just
multiply the distance in that direction,
so that's xi minus a, times the partial
derivative.
So the slope in that direction, which is
the
partial derivative of f with respect to
that direction.
And then evaluate it at the point a.
And again, we end up with the result that,
if the second order
partial derivatives are continuous.
Then we have a second
order approximation.
So, if I make this linear approximation,
linear, so, order 1 Taylor polynomial for
a function of two or more
variables.
Then f of x, so this is the thing
that I'm trying to approximate.
Is equal to my approximation.
Plus, a term that behaves and now I have
to
be a little bit more careful about how I
write quadratics.
So, what I'm looking at here is x is a
vector and a is a vector.
This symbol, the two parallel, vertical
parallel lines on each side, that just
meant the length of the vector, so the
Euclidean length of the vector.
And because that length is squared, this
is big O of x squared, essentially.
As x is going to a.
So I still have the same quadratic
sort of error property for this linear
approximation
that I had when I had a linear
approximation for a function of a single
variable.
And it also turns out.
That because this big O is kind of taking
care of any it's taking care of these
constants of proportionality.
You can also think about this as just the
sum of the individual components, squared.
And also for the, for the quadratic
approximation, so
now that this is getting a bit more
complicated.
So I have f of a is my constant, so that's
the one point where I know what the true
function value is.
I have the linear approximation that's the
same as in my linear approximation up
here.
And now I have to do all of the mixed
partial derivatives to get my quadratic
term.
So, if I have a function of n variables, I
have to sum i equals 1 to n and
j equals 1 to n, and then all of the
mixed partials times the distance in each
of those directions.
And then we see, have because of just the
definition of the
Taylor Polynomial, I have to have this one
over two factorial here.
And so, hopefully you're starting to
recognize that when I see big ugly
sums like this I can benefit from using
vectors and matrices for my notation.
So hopefully that's what's on the next
slide.
Oh, good guess.
So lets let d of f of x, so this is the
gradient of my function f
and it's going to be a function that I can
evaluate at a point x.
And it's just
defined to be the first partial
derivative, the second
partial derivative and so on in a row
vector.
And so it ends up being for a function,
a scalar function, a scaler value function
of n variables.
I end up with a row vector with n elements
in it as the gradient.
And then if I define, if i define x minus
a, so remember for vector
addition, we can do we can do the addition
element wise.
So x minus a is just going to mean this
vector.
So I can actually just do that addition,
and
this, this is a vector of, a column
vector.
So it's got 1 column and n rows.
And then I end
up with anyone remember what this is
called?
Hessian, good, okay.
the Hessian of x, which is.
So I take the gradient and I kind of
imaginarily put that
across the top row.
And then I just take the
derivatives with respect to the x in in
each column, or sorry,
in each row.
And that gives me now a matrix of partial
derivatives.
So the
[COUGH]
next partial derivatives of the function f
of x, and now that
big ugly formula I had at the bottom of
the last slide.
I can now write that as, so I have to
evaluate my function at, at the point
where I know, still.
And then since the gradient is a row
vector.
I'll write a row times a column, so
basically
it's just be, become the dot product of
this
with this, but I can write that out using
matrix notation because I've made the
gradient a row vector.
and that's a order of big O of x squared
approximation.
Then I can also write the quadratic Taylor
approximation, so
the first two terms are just what I had
above.
And then it turns out that that big, ugly
sum can be expressed in matrix vector
notation.
As x minus a transpose, so that's this
vector here that's transposed.
So I want it to be 1 row times n columns.
Then I'm going to multiply it by an n by n
matrix.
And then finally, I'm going to multiply it
by a column vector.
So that's an n by 1 matrix.
So this whole thing is going to end up
being a one by one quantity, so it's a
scalar quantity, and what's left over is
going to behave like x cubed.
So as x is getting closer and closer to a.
My, quality of my approximation is, is
getting better at a cubic rate.
And so just as an example lets consider a
function of two variables.
So I want to make a linear approximation
of a function
f, with two variables, so x and y, around
a point
a,b and so all I end up having to do, I
have.
Whoops, I think I wrote this backwards.
oh no.
Sorry.
It's one thing at a time.
So, here x is actually
the number x.
It's no longer the vector like it was on
the last slide.
And.
B and y are also just numbers.
So all I'm doing to get a linear Taylor
polynomial, I'm taking
the function at the point where I know the
true function value a,b.
That I'm making a linear approximation by
the change
in the x direction, so how far away x is
from a.
So that's x minus a.
Times the partial derivative of f with
respect to x, evaluated at a, b.
So that's the slope in the f, x direction.
So that's just a linear approximation in
the x direction.
And then I do exactly the same thing here,
but in the y direction.
So this is how far away is y, how far away
y is from b.
Times the slope
in the y direction.
And then what I'm going to end up with
when I look at the convergence properties
here.
It's a quadratic, it has quadratic
convergence properties.
So, as x is getting closer to a and y is
getting closer to b, the
error term is big O of x minus a squared
and big O of y minus b squared.
And in matrix notation I can just write
this out.
So remember the gradient here is a row
vector
times a column vector, so those are
conforming dimensions.
So this, I just have to do matrix
multiplication
but it's the same thing as a dot product.
And then I still have my error term, but
at least
I kind of understand it's not a bound but
I understand.
It's property, as I'm getting closer and
closer to the point a,b.
And if I want to add a quadratic term
to my approximation, so this is getting
pretty yucky here.
so the first row here
is just the linear
approximation I had from
the previous slide.
That I need to
split up the, so there's going to be four
possibilities,
but the, the cross term which I have on
the third bit here.
Let me see.
Oh dear, I forgot one of my derivatives in
the fraction.
so I have x minus a squared, divided by 2
factorial.
So I need to have this 2 factorial in the
denominator,
because this is the, that's the definition
of the Taylor polynomial.
And then I need to multiply that by the
second
derivative of f with respect to x,
evaluated at the point a, b.
For the cross term, I have x minus a times
y minus b.
So this partial with respect to y.
We're supposed to be in the denominator
here, but I think
I, I missed a, a bracket when I was
typesetting this.
So this is supposed to be the mixed
partial derivative evaluated at
a,b again, and there's no two factorial in
the denominator here because
this one shows up twice.
So I actually have an x minus a times y
minus b plus a y minus b times
x minus a, but I, because that's a
symmetric
term, I have two of those divided by 2.
So that knocks out the 2 factorial that
you would expect to find in the
denominator here.
And then finally, I have the y term, so y
minus b squared divided by 2 factorial.
Times the partial derivative of f, the
second partial derivative of
f with respect to y evaluated at the point
a, b.
And then what's left, oops, okay, what's
left over should be order x cubed terms.
So, as I've added one more term to my
approximation,
then the error is now behaving as a, a
cubic.
And I can write this in matrix vector
notation, so it simplifies quite a bit.
I have f of a,b so that's just my function
again.
The oops, the linear term.
Then the quadratic term and then again
these things should have been to the third
power for the cubic error term.