This section of the course, we'll look at
practical applications of AI planning and
the use of plans when executed.
It'll also describe some common themes
found in many practical AI planners.
Plans only become useful when they're
executed.
Even the earliest AI planners were linked
with plan execution capabilities, as
shown by the use of the STRIPS planners
alongside the PLANEX, plan execute over
40 years ago in the Shakey robot.
Sacerdoti's NOAH planner was used to
follow along an apprentice engineer
repaired a hydraulic pump and the system
maintained a model of the state of the
pump to build, suggest fixes when the
apprentice ran into problems.
Nonlin maintained the goal structure or
rationale behind plan elements and could
use this as the basis for plan execution
monitoring to spot significant
divergences during the required outcome
[INAUDIBLE] and their later uses to
satisfy constraints in the plan.
In some cases, alternative contributors
to satisfy those required constraints can
be found in the existing plan without
changing it.
In other cases, problems could be spotted
well in advance and suitable changes made
before the problem became critical.
SRI International work on SIPE and PRS,
the Procedural Reasoning System, use rich
representation of plans and processes,
support execution, and recovery from
errors.
Work at the University of Essex, in the
U.K.
Created a reactor planner, which
maintained a representation of the flaws
in the plan whether those arose at plan
time or during execution.
It could apply fixes to these flaws in a
uniform manner, to provide an integrated
planning, execution, and monitoring
framework.
Work in Chicago on RAP explored a
reactive agent architecture for
representing plans that were suited for
real-time plan execution monitoring in
robots, for example.
Our own O-Plan system include algorithms
for plan repair and replanning in both
high tempo and less time constraint
situations when execution monitoring
indicated problems.
Was not at all surprising is that many of
the AI planners which were created to
address practical applications also
include technique support, execution, and
monitoring of the outcome of plan
execution.
We'll now look in some depth, at a good
example of our AI planning and plan
execution techniques we used in practice.
We'll see the importance of integrating
planning into other key systems for
real-time task assignment, system
diagnosis, condition monitoring, and
execution time plan repair.
Deep Space 1 launched from Cape Canaveral
in 1998 and tested twelve advanced high
risk technologies from space including
ion thrusters and advanced on-board
automation.
In a successful extended mission, it
operated through to 2001 and encountered
Comet Borrelly.
Deep Space 1 included a remote agent
experiment, RAX, to demonstrate both
ground-based and on-board AI remote plan
execution.
The spacecraft control application domain
posed some tough requirements.
High reliability was essential and issues
could arrise from single point system
failures are for more complex multiple
cause problems.
Deep space 1 operated under tight
resource constraints for fuel and power,
and frequently there would be multiple
goals, you could not all be satisfied at
the same time.
Of course, given the nature of a very
high speed fly-by of a target comet,
deadlines were fixed and very tight.
There's no second chance return if
essential observations and scientific
goals are not achieved due to some
precondition, not being satisfied, or
some systems not being fully prepared at
the critical time.
Spacecraft did have sensors to report its
status and the status of its instruments,
but these only provide limited
observability of the many conditions
under which the spacecraft can operate.
And of course.
many things can be happening at the same
time on a spacecraft.
And some operations can take a long time
to complete when started.
There's no possibility of fully ordering
and completing one activity before
another must begin.
So Deep Space 1 posed a very interesting
and realistic example of a remote device
that we might wish to control via more
automated AI planning methods.
The Deep Space 1 remote agent approach
was to used constraint based planning and
scheduling.
It had to deal with robust multi-threaded
execution of the activities and it had to
integrate with model-based fault
diagnosis and reconfiguration.
Real time control and monitoring of the
spacecraft was the key issue.
Deep Space 1 could operate at various
levels of autonomy.
It could execute single commands or
sequences of activities which are to be
executed at some particular times.
It could seek to achieve some given goal.
It could maintain a model of the state of
the spacecraft and detect errors from
incoming sensor information.
It could deal with a scripted plan and
decompose that into greater levels of
detail and it could deal with on-board
back-to-back plan generation, execution
and plan recovery in its most autonomous
mode.
This table provides a summary of the
levels of autonomy on-board Deep Space 1
and shows what elements can be done on
the ground, on the on on-board planner
and scheduler, and on the on-board
execution system.
So this goes right through to the most
autonomous modes where plans can be
prepared on the ground, they can be
completed on-board the spacecraft, then
take into account the situation the
spacecraft is in and could be
autonomously executed.
So Deep Space 1 systems cover everything
from the ground control through what's
happening on the spacecraft itself.
It involves planning, execution, and
monitoring of the outcome of plans.
Deep Space 1 remote agent experiment
functionality includes the planner
schedule and mission manager,
which deals with the on-board generation
of plans dealing with replanning when
failures occur and so on.
The Executor provides the low-level
commanding interface that links back to
the planet to initiate on-board planning
when it's needed,
and is linked to the mode identification
recovery or diagnosis system on the
spacecraft to make sure that we can
confirm command execution meets its
objectives.
Deep space 1 planning could deal with a
diversity of goals.
Final state goals, such as turn off the
camera once you're done using it,
schedule goals such as communicate to
earth at pre-specified times.
Periodic goals such as ensuring you take
a picture for navigation purposes every
two days.
Information-seeking goals such as asking
the on-board navigation system to return
its profile for the thrusters.
continues accumulation goals such as
making sure that over a given period, you
make sure you accumulate enough thrust
but it don't, these actions don't have to
be on at specific times.
And then default goals such as when
you've got nothing else to do, point the
high-gain antenna back to the earth to
maintain good communications with the
earth.
And it can deal with a diversity of
constraints,
state action constraints such as to take
a picture, the camera must be on.
Dealing with finite resources such as
power constraints.
Dealing with true parallelism,
where for instance, the attitude control
system must work in parallel with the ion
propulsion system controller.
Functional dependencies,
example is the duration of a turn depends
on its source and its destination.
Continuously varying parameters such as
counting the amount of accumulated
thrust, under the constraints that come
from other kinds of specialized modules
such as the on-board navigation system.
A Deep Space 1 plan is in the form of
timelines of the different instruments
and when they're turned on and off, and
various constraint, time constraints and
all kinds of constraints, apply between
the elements of this plan.
This tool shows the stages of the exact
system on-board the spacecraft.
A Java applet was provided to allow
observers to watch the remote agent
experiments in real-time while it was
operating.
The actual flight experiment for Deep
Space 1 remote agent experiment took
place 17th and the 21st of May, 1999.
RAX was activated and controlled the Deep
Space 1 Spacecraft autonomously,
but some issues and alarms did arise.
There was a divergence of the predicted
value of the state of the ion propulsion
system and the actual observed values.
This was determined to be due to the
infrequency of real-time monitor updates
on the spacecraft.
They EXEC deadlocked in use,
the problem was diagnosed and a fix was
designed quickly,
but it was not uploaded to Deep Space 1
for fears of the safety of the flight
systems.
This condition hadn't appeared in
thousands of ground tests,
which indicates the need for formal
verification methods for this type of
safety and mission critical software.
Following later experiments, RAX was
deemed to have achieve its aims and
objectives.
RAX controlled the spacecraft
autonomously for two days.
On the first day, typical operations took
place.
The ion propulsion system was turned on
and off at various times.
The attitude control system was operated
when appropriate,
some images were taken,
some on-board planning was performed.
The second day included the injection of
some simulated failures of the
radiometric tracking and thruster systems
in order to show how the planet could
cope with these events.
The final report to the Deep Space 1
remote agent experiment concluded that
the validation objectives had been
achieved.
The system was able to do what both
ground-based and on-board autonomously
generated plans and execute those plans
in the face of failures and re-plan where
required.
And it did this through capabilities,
which included robust goal-based
commanding, and integration with the
on-board model-based fault recovery
system.
So to summarize, Deep Space 1 remote
agent experiment featured an AI planner
outer level with re-planning capability,
detailed constraint handling for time and
resources,
integration with system diagnostics and
analysis,
integration of plan exclusion and
monitoring,
rich domain description languages,
and involved comprehensive user
interfaces.