Our first approach
[SOUND]
to building a player for small single
player games, is called compulsive
deliberation.
It's a big name for a relatively simple
concept.
In compulsive deliberation on each step
the
player examines the then current game tree
to determine his best move for that step
and at then makes the move.
Repeats his process on the next step and
so forth until the end of the game.
Now in pure compulsive deliberation, each
step
of the computation's independent of every
other step.
No data compute, -puted during one step is
accessible subsequent steps.
The player treats each step as if it were
a brand-new game.
Now this is obviously wasteful, but it
doesn't really hurt
so long as there's enough time to do the
repeated calculations.
We start with this method because it's
simple
to understand and at the same time it
serves as a template for the more
sophisticated and much less wasteful
methods to come.
Using basic subroutine provided in the GGP
starter
pack, building a compulsive deliberation
player is not difficult.
The implementation looks like this.
As shown, it's almost identical to
our implementation of legal and random
players.
The only difference lies in the play
handler.
In selecting an action a legal player uses
find legal
x, to compute a legal move for a given
state.
In compulsive deliberation,
the play handler instead uses a subroutine
called bestmove that does a more
sophisticated computation.
Before looking at bestmove, let's look
at slightly simpler subroutine called
maxscore.
Maxscore takes up state as argument, and
returns the best score that
the player can obtain by any sequence of
actions in the specified state.
Let's see how it works.
As its first step, the procedure checks
whether the given state is terminal.
If so, then the pos, best possible score
is a reward for the specified state.
Computes this by calling the find reward
subroutine on
the goal, role, the state, and the rule
set.
If the state's not terminal, then it tries
each of the actions legal in that state.
Computes the maximum score for the state
that results from
executing that action, and returns the
best score it finds.
First step in doing this is to compute a
list of all legal actions.
It initializes the variable score to zero,
then loops over the possible actions.
Since it generally can be multiple players
findnexts takes
as arguments a list of actions of all
players.
In this case we have a single player game,
so the player creates a list of just one
element.
The player then uses find next to compute
the
next state resulting from this move in the
current state.
Then finds the max score for that
successor state.
If
the result is 100, then it simply returns
that value,
as there's no way to get more than 100
points.
Otherwise, if the result is greater than
current
score, it updates the score and goes on.
And finally, if it has not encountered a
100 value, and, in the process, it
returns the current score, which, by
construction, is
the maximum score for, for all possible
actions.
Okay, now that we have max score, let's
return to best move.
The definition uses max score, and is
actually quite similar to max score.
There're just a few differences.
First of all, best move is not itself
recursive, though it calls max score,
which is recursive.
Best move does not need to check whether
the state is terminal, because it
would not be called if the gate were, game
were in a terminal state.
That's already been checked.
It initializes a variable called action to
the first legal action.
It then behaves pretty much like max
score, trying each possible action, to see
if
it can find one with a higher score than
any previous action it has seen.
If it ever encounters a max score
of 100, it simply returns the
corresponding action.
Otherwise, it proceeds until it has tried
all actions, at which point
it returns the action with the highest max
score that it has seen.