topic four is going to be Newton's Method
for n Dimensional Nonlinear Problems.
[COUGH]
So now I'm going to consider functions,
so, I've decided to
call them capital F.
And these are functions of n variables
that have n outcomes.
So you sort of think of it as a vector of
n functions.
And each one of those n functions take the
same n variables as inputs.
And I still want to solve the problem f of
x equals 0.
But now, because f of x is a function that
has n outputs
this 0 on the right hand side is a vector
of n 0's.
So it's the 0 vector.
And let's remember that the gradient of f
is this n by n matrix.
So in the,
[SOUND]
in the first
row.
I just have the gradient
for the first function, the first
component of this function f, so
I called that f1.
Second row is the gradient
for the second component f2 and
so on.
So I can make a Taylor
polynomial.
Around the point xk.
And it looks exactly the same way as it
did for the one-dimensional one,
except here I have a vector of values.
Here, I have
an n by n matrix.
And here,
I have a n by 1 matrix, so a column
vector of, of the function
inputs.
And so I'm going to play around with this.
This Taylor polynomial, exactly the same
way as I
did when it was just a function of 1
variable.
So I want
to imagine that I am approximating a point
f of xk plus
1, and that that's where this function is
going to
be equal to 0.
So that gives me this relationship here.
So, I'm trying to find this point, k plus
1, so that my function is zero.
But instead of doing that I'm just using
the linear approximation and finding out
where that's
equal to 0.
And then, I just want to solve this again
for x plus 1, and so it
ends up being a little bit more
complicated
this time, because this is a matrix now.
I can't just divide by the matrix but
if it's non-singular, I can multiply by
its inverse.
So that's going to put the inverse of the
matrix in front of
this term, so if I move this to the other
side of the equal
sign, it becomes negative.
And then I multiply by the inverse.
And that gets me just this guy.
And then I'm going to move the xk also to
this side of the equal sign.
So I've isolated my point xk plus
1.
And this is basically the same, same
formula as I had.
For the, the one variable case.
Except now, when I had one variable, I can
just
interpret multiplying by the inverse as
dividing by the derivative.
And then I need a, a stopping condition.
So what I'm going to look at here is this.
Is my updating step.
So this is how, how much I'm changing my
guess.
If this actually did converge to the true
value, so if I put in x
star here, x star here, and x star here, I
should already be at 0.
So it shouldn't move at all.
So at x star, this quantity should be 0.
So my stopping condition is going to be,
again the problem is
this is a vector, so I can't just say,
less than something.
What I can say is how long that vector is.
So that's going to give me some idea of
how far
away I am from the thing that I'm trying
to calculate.
And when that, when that improvement
gets below a certain level, that I'm
going to call tau.
So I need to pick some tolerance tau
greater than 0,
but generally you think of this as a very
small number.
When the size of my update gets below
that level, that's going to be my stopping
condition.
It might not be the, the best idea for a
stopping condition, but
I need some condition to stop and so this,
this will be okay.
[COUGH]
And it's more complicated now, but you
still have the
quadratic convergence that you had for the
univariate
case.
Once I'm close enough to the value x star.
So the algorithm for using this to, to
solve
An undimensional optimization problem, an
n-dimensional non-linear problem.
I still need a starting point, x 0, and
then I'm
going to try to improve that starting
point, using these Newton iterations.
So, if the gradient is non-singular, then
I can
compute the, compute the next step.
So from, you know,
from x 0, I can find x 1, just by updating
according to this rule.
But I see this inverse of a matrix here.
And I don't like that.
So to avoid computing the inverse of this
matrix, what I'll do is take this
and this is a n by n matrix times an n by
1 matrix times the column vector.
So I'm just going to look at this product
and
say well that's just going to be another
column vector used.
So n times n, times n times 1.
I take the outer dimensions, that's what
the product's going,
the dimensions of the product is going to
be.
And so that gives me u is also n by
one, so it's a column vector of n with n
entries.
And then I'm going to multiply both sides
by the gradient.
So what I end up with is this gradient
matrix times my unknown.
And then here I have the gradient times
its inverse, so that's the identity,
so that's just going to be equal to the
function evaluated at f of xk.
And this is exactly the problem that we
looked at in
in the linear algebra section, this is a
times x, equals b.
So this is something that we know how to
solve.
So the algorithm that I'll end up using to
compute the n dimensional Newton's
method, so I have a, a tolerance, tau
greater than 0, and a starting point, x 0.
And so, for the kth step, I have to
compute this vector f of xk.
This is just a vector of numbers now.
And I have to compute the gradient.
So I have a formula for the gradient and I
plug in xk, and so
that's going to give me a matrix, so it's
just a matrix of numbers now.
So, then I can solve this linear system,
and find the value u.
And that value u is the the size of
update that I want to use in my Newton
iterations.
So, I'll update.
So my current guess is xk.
I update that by subtracting this vector
u, that I got by solving
this linear system in step two, and that's
going to give me xk plus 1.
And then if the size of this u is less
than
tau, then I'm going return xk plus 1 as
the answer.
Otherwise,
I'm going to go back to step one and just
pretend
now that this xk, once I'm on the next
step.
That's going to just run me through this
same set of steps again.
So I'll do a, a very simple example.
So if I take 1 minus, so this x minus 1 to
the 4th power and y minus 1 to
the 4th power.
So these are both going to be positive, so
when I subtract them they're both going to
be negative, so it should be pretty clear.
That this is going to have a maximum, when
this is equal to
0 and this is equal to 0 and that maximum
is going to be
equal to 1.
Because if I put in anything nonzero for
these, it's going
to be subtracted from 1, so it's going to
make it smaller.
So this should have a critical point at
the point 1, 1.
Or it has a maximum at the point 1, 1, so
it should have a critical
point at the point 1, 1.
So I can compute the gradient of
this so this is the, the gradient.
Of the function that I'm trying to find
the critical point of.
So this is a function, it's a function
of two variables but it's a scalar-valued
function.
When I evaluate this, I just get a single
number.
[COUGH]
But when I want to find a critical point,
what I want
to find is a point where the gradient is
equal to 0.
So now the gradient is my function of two
variables,
and this is what I want to use Newton's
method on.
So I want to, I want to use Newton's
method to find the point
where the gradient, so basically where the
derivative is equal to 0.
You have to be a little bit careful here,
because, in general,
when you think of a function that has
several
outputs, you think of that as a column
vector.
The gradient here is a row vector, so I've
just taken the transpose
here and the transpose here so that
everything lines up the way it should.
The gradient of f of x, then, is just this
function.
So it's has a very simple gradient.
And now I'm going to use r to run through
several iterations
of Newton's method to try and find the
solution for this.
So, the first, the thesis that I'm
going to need to be able to do this.
I need a function that I'm going to call
capital F.
And this is going to evaluate the, the
function that I am
trying to find that I am trying to make
equal to 0.
So this is a pretty simple function, its
just going to be, its
a, so it has two inputs and two outputs.
The first output is just 4 times
x minus 1 cubed, so its a it's basically
just returning the
gradient of the function that I'm trying
to find the, the maximum of.
DF is going to return the gradient of f.
So
those are just this and this, but written
out in r form.
So what I've done here is, looked at the
diagonal elements.
This is the top left element.
This is the bottom right element.
And I've put them in a vector.
And then a short-cut for making a diagonal
matrix is just to use this function diag.
If I give it a vector as its argument, it
makes a diagonal matrix that has.
These elements down the main diagonal, and
then I don't have a particularly
good way of choosing a starting point.
Because it was pretty clear from the
definition of the function, that the point
I'm
looking for was 1, 1, but it won't be very
exciting if I choose that.
So another commonly chosen starting point
is 0.
So I'm going to start at the 0 vector.
So I'll say x is equal to 0.
Or, assign the, the 0 vector to the
variable x.
And then I'll do 25 Newton iterations.
So, because I've defined these functions
as functions of x
and y, I need to provide each one of them
with two arguments so
as just the first element of' x and the
second element of x.
I can use the solve function to solve the,
the
linear system that I was talking about on
the previous slide.
And so all I have to do is give the matrix
a and the vector b and solve is
going to solve the linear system for me.
And then my updating
step is just to say, xk minus u becomes xk
plus 1.
And so when I, when I run this code in r,
it's going to take xk, it's going to
subtract the vector u and
then it's going to write the answer to
that.
Into the same piece of memory that I
originally was using to hold x.
And then I'm going to put that in
something called a for loop.
Which is just going to run this line 25
times in a row.
And so we can look at x after this has
gone 25 times.
So x started out as 0, 0.
Then after 25 newton iterations.
I end up with 0.9999 and 0.9999.
So, it's gotten
very close to the point that I was looking
for, 1, with these 25 iterations.