Assuming we have generated a plan, the
next question is, what do we do with this
plan?
What happens after we have planned?
Now you may think execution as the obvious
answer, but there may be other things.
For example, we may have generated
multiple plans as options that we want to
consider in which case the next step would
be to evaluate these plans according to
some different criteria, and then select
the plan possibly for execution.
But we may also have scenarios where we
hope that we will never have to execute
those plans, for example when we come up
with emergency response plans.
In this case the planning is really just
for preparedness.
But the most common thing we do after
planning is probably plan execution.
And my colleague, Austin Tate, talked
about planning and plan execution, in the
context of real applications earlier this
week.
So all I need to give you now, is probably
a brief reminder.
Here's a slide that I've used before and
that describes our model of plan
execution.
This model starts with what we've seen a
lot in this course, namely with a planning
problem.
This is described by an initial state, and
by some objectives which can be either
gold, or tasks depending on whether we do
STRIPS like our HTN planning, and then we
have a description of our state transition
system which could be methods or strips
operators as we've seen before.
And then the planner is the planning
algorithm we've looked at most of this
course.
And the output of that planner is, of
course, a plan.
This plan is then passed to the
controller, which is responsible for the
execution of the plan.
The controller takes the actions from our
plan, and somehow makes sure they get
executed, which affects our real world
system, that somehow changes its state.
Of course, the system also changes its
state due to events that may Occur.
And to deal with those events and to
ensure that the actions have the desirous
effects on the state of the real world.
The controller has some observations that
it can use to monitor the state.
Ideally then, everything goes according to
plan.
And the controller has nothing more to do.
More realistically things will go wrong or
the unexpected will happen.
And that means the plan needs to be
changed, and for the plan to change we
need the planner again.
But what we have to do is give the planner
some additional input and that is the
execution status of the plan so far.
Then the planner hopefully can generate a
new plan.
The controller can start executing that
new plan and so on.
So what we really have here is a loop that
starts with the initial planning problem
then goes through the controller and the
execution and returns to the planner and
may go through this process several times
before we end up with the desired
objectives achieved in the real world.
And to answer my question then what comes
after we plan?
Well the answer's simply more planning.
Namely when things go wrong we need to do
either plan revision which means we take
our existing plan and change parts of it
to deal with deviations between the
description of our system and the actual
system that we are manipulating.
Or we can throw away the old plan and
start replanning from scratch.
One of the issue with the model I just
showed you in the previous slide is, that
there was just a single planner and a
single controller.
More realistically, however, is a scenario
where we have multiple agents.
That is, multiple agents which are
executing the plan.
Multiple agents which are controlling the
execution.
And even multiple agents that are
generating the plan.
And this of course, leads to a number of
additional problem during plan execution.
And one of the problems is that, if we
have multiple agents execute the actions
and the plan, then these actions need to
be coordinated between the different
agents.
As a simple example, remember that our
plans contained ordering constrains
between different actions.
Now, if we assign two actions that are
ordered with respect to each other to two
different agents.
Then during plan execution, these two
agents need to make sure that first, one
action is executed.
And then the other action is executed by
the other agent.
That means the second agent needs to know
when the first agent has finished its
activity.
So ordering constraints leads to a
coordination problem immediately.
A similar problem arises when actions use
shared resources that have limited
capacity.
Again, we need to coordinate the actions
if they are assigned to different agents,
such that they will never exhaust the
capacity that is available.
And, of course, we may have joint actions.
You remember the example earlier from two
agents lifting a table with objects on it.
The lifting of the table needs to be
started and finished together or the
objects will fall off the table.
And, again, this requires coordination
between the two agents.
And the most common way to solve
coordination problems is, of course,
communication between the different agents
involved.
And the way this is done is that we start
with a plan as we've seen it so far.
And then we assign the actions in that
plan two different agents.
And then, what we have to is, amend the
plan with communication actions that are
required for the coordination of the
different activities in the plan.
So we add more actions to the plan,
communication actions to make sure the
execution may go well.
Another reason why we may need
communication in a plan is that we may
have observation actions.
So one agent that is part of our plan has
to look at the state of the world and
recognize something in that state.
And then it may need to communicate the
result to other agents that may depend on
it.
But however well we prepare our plan it
can always still go wrong and that means
we have execution failure somewhere in our
plan.
And the question then is how can we
recover from this failure if we have
multiple agents executing the plan.
And the easiest way to recover from
failure would of course be local plan
repair.
So if we can modify the plan locally so
that only the agent that experienced the
failure can some how fix its part of the
plan without effecting other parts of the
plan assigned to other agents.
Then we wouldn't have to talk to other
agents before we continue the execution.
But often a plan cannot be fixed locally
and requires some global change to the
plan.
That is a change that effects other agents
that have to execute actions in the plan.
And then the problem is to propagate those
changes through the plan and to other
agents.
And one important concept here is
decommitment.
So when we start the execution we have the
agents commit to the actions.
That they need to execute in the plan.
And when things go wrong, they may need to
de-commit from these actions, and we need
to handle this somehow.
So, as you can see, there are many
problems that may arise during multi-agent
plan execution, and all these need to be
addressed if we successfully want to
execute our plans with multiple agents.