The problem with Greedy Best-First search
is that it often finds sub optimal
solutions, often very badly sub optimal
solutions.
But the idea of using a juristic
function, to determine the search
strategy is a good one.
We will see this next when we define the
A* algorithm which always gives us
optimal solutions.
A* is probably, the best known algorithm
in all of artificial intelligence and as
far as I know it is described in every
single AI textbook.
A star is simply refinement of the best
first search algorithm we have seen
earlier.
The only difference to Greedy Best-First
search is that it uses a different
evaluation function.
So remember f, the evaluation function,
tells us in which order we explore nodes
on the fringe.
The heuristic h tells us the distance to
the nearest goal node.
So far it is nothing new, what is new is
this component g that we add to the
uristic to get our evaluation function
and this function g simply gives us the
cost to reach the note end so that's the
cost we already had to get from our
initial state to this note end and to
this we add a uristic which is the
estimate to the nearest goal note from
this note end.
So if we have an initial state I and we
somehow to get our note N.
Then the distance between those two.
Is g of n.
Whereas from here, we somehow get to a
goal node, and this is our nearest goal
node g.
Then this distance is estimated by the
heuristic function H, of N.
One way to look at this is that greedy
best first search behaves a little bit
like depth first search.
It tries to go deep into the search base,
as quickly as it can to a goal node.
It always tries to eat at much as
possible out of the distance to the goal.
By adding g to h, and using that as our
evaluation function.
We sort of add a breadth first component
to this depth first search.
In fact, the evaluation function we're
using gives us the estimated cost of the
cheapest solution through the node N.
Why is that?
Well, very simple.
The cheapest solution though N surely
must consist of the path that goes from
the initial state to N.
And the cost of that is given by G of N.
And it consists of the cost of getting
from N to the goal Node.
And we can estimate that, using the
function H, the uristic function.
So when we use this evaluation function
to select the next node from the French
we are selecting that node N.
Which looks to be on the cheapest path to
A goal node.
And we can show that A* search is optimal
if our heuristic function is admissible.
And that means that it always
underestimates the distance to the goal.
But I will get back to properties of A*
later.
So let's look at the same touring Romania
example we've had before.
Our initial state is that we are in Irat,
and we want to get to Bucharest.
Note that the number in brackets in each
node is the F value, not the H value.
So this includes the G component.
The amount of path we've already covered.
For the initial node, G is zero, because
we haven't gone anywhere yet.
So the initial, for the initial node,
the, H value is equal to the F value.
So again, the first thing we do is select
the node from the fringe.
And since there is only one node, we
select that node.
And then we expand that node and add the
successors to the fringe.
Whereas, a rod disappears from the
fringe.
So if you go back you will see that the
numbers and the different nodes are
different from what we have seen
previously.
Which is what I've just explained.
They contain the G component as well as
the H component.
So again the algorithm proceeds by
selecting the node from the fringe that
has the lowest F value which is 393 in
this example.
We continue by testing whether this is a
goal state, which it is not so we have to
expand it and generate its successors.
There are four successors again as
before.
Arot is one of the successors so we're
doing tree search.
But now, one big differences is that the
number that we see with Arot is very
different.
It's a much higher number because it
includes the path that we've already gone
through.
So this is not the same as for the
initial state, because we've already gone
through the loop through that other city,
before we returned to Arot.
So we continue with our loop, and we have
to select another note from the fringe.
Which will be the note with the lowest F
value, in this case 413.
This is not a goal note, so we have to
expand it.
And there are three more successors we
add to the fringe.
Now something interesting has happened.
Previously this was our lowest value so
we estimated that a path through this
node could cost as little as 413.
We have expanded this node and seen that
its best successor has a value of 417.
This is because the heuristic
underestimates.
The distance to the goal, now we are
closer to the goal the heuristic has
become more accurate and we know the
power is in fact a little more expensive.
What that also means is that there is a
note higher up in the tree this one here
that now has the lowest f value on the
fringe so this is the one we will select
next.
We will perform the goal test as before.
And since this is not a goal node, we
have to expand this node.
Generating two more successors.
Including as you will see, one that is
the goal node.
But, having generated to go on node does
not mean that we are finished.
We will finish when we select to go on
node, and try to perform to goal test on
this node.
So let's select the next node from the
fringe.
And the node with the lowest F value is
now over here, with a value of 417.
That's the successor we previously
ignored.
And since this is not a goal note we will
proceed by expanding this note.
Generating three more successors and once
again of, of those is the goal.
So our goal note appears twice on the
fringe now but these have two different
paths to the goal note.
Notice that the one further up is the one
that Greedy Best-First search found
earlier.
Now lets proceed with A star.
A star goes through the loop again and
selects the note with the lowest f value,
which in this case is the bookarest note
at depth four.
It performs the goal test and finds
indeed Bucharest is the goal node and
hence we have found a path to the goal
node and it is the optimal path.
We can go again back through the tree,
tracing the way we came, to get the
optimal path to this goal node.
So a star gave us an optimal path to the
goal node, better than what Greedy
Best-First search found.
However you can also see that this tree
contains quite a few more nodes than the
tree that was generated by Greedy
Best-First search.
And that means A star search is generally
a little bit slower than Greedy
Best-First search and unfortunately this
is often the case.
The touring Romania example is not very
interesting, because it is a relatively
small search space.
So here's something that has a slightly
bigger search space.
The 8 puzzle.
Again, to remind you, the 8 puzzle's
character is by an initial state, there
is one state that is given here, and one
goal state, exactly, that is given here.
The actions for this puzzle were that we
can move the tiles around the grid, and a
good way to think about this is that we
are moving the empty tile rather than the
tiles themselves, which means there are,
at most, four possible actions we can
move the empty tile.
In the four different directions, which
reduces the branching factor of the tree
we are generating.
Also, it might be a good idea to test for
reverse action, because undoing what
we've just done immediately never leads
to anything good in this search space.
Finally, we need to define the cost of
the different actions, and we use a unit
cost here.
Moving a tile is, same cost for every
tile.
What is missing to apply best first
search or Greedy Best-First search or a
star search here is a heuristic function,
and we will look at that next.
In fact I will give you two symbol
heuristics for the eight puzzle.
The first one simply counts the number of
misplaced tiles.
So we go through all the eight tiles in
the puzzle, and check whether it is
already at the right position.
If it is not, then we add one to our
heuristic.
Because we know if it is not at the right
position, we have to move the style at
some point.
And since every action moves just one
tile, that's a good heuristic to start
with.
So let's look at this in this example.
This is our heuristic H1 number of
misplaced tiles, well this is wrong, this
is wrong, they're all wrong.
So we see that in this example the value
of our heuristic is eight that means all
eight tiles are in the wrong position.
The second heuristic H2, uses the
manhattan block distance as an estimate
to how far we need to go.
So again, we go through all the eight
tiles in the puzzle, and compute the
manhattan block distance, and add those
distances together.
What I mean by Manhattan block distance
is simply that all the moves we are
allowed, are to go somewhere along the
grid.
So there are only four possible ways in
which one can move a tile.
So lets start with the first time, that's
the number seven.
And the way, where we want the number
seven to be is here so the Manhattan
block distance is one, two, three.
And this is the first value we'll choose.
Then we have the two here.
And where should the two be?
The two should be here.
So the distance is one and so on.
If we continue like this for all eight
tiles, we will see that the Manhattan
block distance heuristic for this state
is eighteen.
It is easy enough to see that both of
these heuristics never overestimate the
distance to the nearest goal.
It should also be easy to see that the
second heuristic, H2, always gives us a
much more accurate estimate of how far
the goal node is away, but it is not a
perfect heuristic.
The actual distance to the goal node from
the state shown here is 26.
So if you feel like a little programming
now why don't you go ahead and implement
the eight puzzle using the a star
algorithm and solve a few puzzles.
Use different heuristics.
Play around with it.
See what happens.