OK, so lesson six is going to be, called
Put-Call Parity and The Greeks.
This will be a pretty quick lesson.
I just want to introduce a couple of
concepts
that I'll use than in the next four
lessons.
So I'll start off.
By naming V to be the value
of a portfolio of derivative securities
all based on one underlying asset.
So this could be, you know, more than one
option based on the same underyling asset.
Really, for, for what we're going to be
doing this week, it's going to
be just a single thing, either one call
option or one put option.
And then the rates of change of the value
V with respect to
the pricing parameter, so that would be
the asset price S, the volatility sigma.
These are going to be things that are
useful for hedging.
And these rates or chains are called the
Greeks of the portfolio and they're.
They're basically just the different
derivatives you
can take of the Black-Scholes pricing
formula.
So we're going to consider a portfolio
containing a single European call option.
And basically, this week's going to work,
if you've looked at the homework already.
I'm going to go through the examples of
how
to compute the Greeks using a call option.
It'll be very similar, but just, a little
different, to do it for a put option.
And so the homework is going to be a put
option.
But you should be able to refer to the
calculations for the call option, and up
to just to a few things being reordered
and some different signs, it will be very
similiar.
And there's also, well I'll get to this in
a second,
first I'm just going to remind you about
the Black-Scholes formula.
So the inputs to the Black-Scholes formula
Where the asset price, s.
And so this is going to quite often in,
in these slides also have a t associated
with it.
And that just means the, the price at a
certain time t.
If there's no t, we kind of mean the, the
price right now.
And sigma is going to be the volatility.
K is the strike price.
So this is the, the exercise price of the
option.
Little r is a continuously compounded
risk-free interest rate.
Capital T is the maturity date.
Q is a, asset dividend rate, and this is
a, continuously compounded rate at well.
And then little t is going to be time, so
you can think of that as current, the
current time.
And really, the way capital T and little t
are going to
show up in the pricing formula is, capital
T minus little t.
And so that means some date in the future
minus today.
And so, that quantity, capital T minus
little
t, you can think of that as the time
left until the maturity of the, of the
contract.
So the Black Shoals formula for a European
call option
So I'm using the same notation that is
used in
the text book and so, this is for some
reason
treated as a function, just of two
variables, S and T.
But it's really, has several more has all
of the variables that I had
on the previous slide in it, so you have
the, dividend rate, you have.
Maturity, current time, strike price and
risk free interest rate.
And then we also have this function
capital Fi, and that's just defined
as the integral from minus infinity Up to
z of
e to the minus x squared over 2dx and then
normalized
by this factor of 1 over the square root
of 2 pi.
We have a function d plus, which is also a
function of all of the arguments of the
pricing formula.
And essentially it's not necessary to, to
write d-plus
as a separate function and put it in here.
I could actually just write the whole
thing out, but
again it just gets kind of unwieldy to do
that.
And now that we have tools, like the
product rule and the chain rule,
it's actually more convenient.
To treat functions of functions separately
like this.
So we had a, a d plus in the first term of
the pricing formula.
We have a d minus in the second term of
And these two functions are very similar.
And where, where they differ is just that
d plus.
Has a plus sigma, oops, okay, I can't, I
can't highlight that,
but has a plus sigma squared over two in
this part here.
And d minus is actually equal to d plus
minus sigma times the square root of T
minus
t And all that that changes is that this
plus sign here becomes a minus sign in d
minus.
So the, the plus and minus subscript on
the d here just
refers to whether this should be a plus
operation, or a minus operation.
Then there's a relationship between the
price of a
Put option and the price of a Call option.
So If I let C of T be the price of a
European Call option, and P of T be
the price of a European Put option on the
same
asset, with the same maturity date and the
same strike price.
Then the following relation holds, and
this is called Put-Call parity
And it just says that the price of the Put
option plus s
times S times E to the minus QT minus T.
So, it's basically this is just what the
asset's going to be worth.
If it's paying some dividends, it's
going to be a little bit more.
Then, minus the value of the call option
has
to be equal to the discounted value.
Of the strike price.
And so what we're really trying to do here
is relate the Put price and the Call
price.
And so in the homework I've asked you to
do two things.
So I'm going to show you how to calculate
the derivatives of the Call price.
And then I'm
going to ask you to calculate the
derivatives of the put price.
And so what I want you to actually, in
the homework, compute those by taking
derivatives of the formula.
But you can check that you got the right
answer by taking derivatives of this put
call parity relationship.
And then just plugging in, so if I took
the derivative of this, for instance, with
respect to s.
This term would just be dcds.
That's going
to be something that I show you how to
calculate today.
And so you'll end up with an expression
for the derivative
of the put price with respect to S, these
two other
terms and something that we already know,
and so that'll give
you an easy way to verify that you've got
the correct answer.
And the Greeks are, and they just
the different derivatives of the, the
pricing formula.
But they all have names that are Greek
letters.
So that's why they're called the Greeks,
it has
nothing actually to do with the country of
Greece
So the rate of change of c, so it's rate
of change in general of the value of
the portfolio but since for today's
lecture I'm considering
my portfolio just to be a single call
option.
I'm just going to say c is the value of my
portfolio.
So the rate of change with C with respect
to S, is called Delta
and that's just going to be the partial
derivative of C with respect to S.
Second one is called Gamma which is the
rate of change of Delta with respect to S.
And since, so partial derivative of delta
again, with respect to s.
And since delta was the partial derivative
of c with respect to s, gamma
can also be the second partial derivative
of c with respect to s squared.
Then we have theta, which is the rate of
change of c with respect to t.
And so that'll just be the partial
derivative of c with respect to t.
Row, which is the rate of change of c with
respect to the risk free interest rate r.
So it's the partial derivative of c with
respect
to r And then, vega, which I'm not sure
this
is actually a real Greek letter, but it
sounds kind of Greek.
So I guess they threw it in with the, with
the group.
Which is the rate of change of C with
respect to sigma.
So partial of C with respect to sigma.