So now onto some more complicated rules
for taking derivatives.
So the first one is going to be the
product rule.
So suppose f of x and g of x are
differentiable functions.
So this is going to be kind of like my
linearity rule from from the last section.
So I'm not going to be given f of x and g
of x, I'm going to be given a function but
as I look at it, I'm going to see that
that function is actually composed of two
simpler functions multiplied together.
And if I can take the derivative of each
of those simpler funtions,
then the product rule is going to allow me
to
take the derivative of the product of
those two functions.
So, suppose I'm given a function p of x,
and I can see a way to write it down as a
function of f of x times the function g of
x, and I want to take the derivative of p
of x.
So p of x is differentiable and the
derivative of p of x, or p prime of x.
Ops, so my definition
of p of x is just the product of f of x
and g of x and the product rule says that
the derivative of this is going to be the
derivative of the first function,
so f prime of x.
Times g of x, times g of x
plus the first function, so f of x, times
the
derivative of the second function, g prime
of x.
And so I think the, the best way to
deal with this is just to go through some
examples.
Ops.
So, in several of my slides I start out
the slide with a recall just to remind
you what the product rule is, so this
is just the definition of the product rule
here.
And suppose my function, p of x, is x
times e to the x.
So, right away, I'm going to recognize
this this is
the product of a function f of x equals x.
And another function, g of x equals e to
the x.
And I know how to take the derivative of
both of those functions.
So.
I'm going to kind of skip in this course
all of the rules for taking derivatives of
functions.
These are easy things to look up now, I
actually brought my phone
here, because I found out that Siri, which
is the voice assistant on an Iphone.
One of the things that it asks for sources
of data
is Wolfram Alpha, which is this website
I've been recommending to you.
So I'm going to try an onscreen
demonstration of this, see what happens.
what's the derivative of the exponential
function?
>> Checking on that.
Here's what I found.
>> Okay.
So I don't know if the camera is going to
be able to pick that up.
But it shows up this little, I don't know
what that's suppose to be.
Actually that's a dot matrix printer paper
but it
actually has the derivative of the
exponential function on it.
although they used a capital X and I used
a small x but otherwise
it's exactly what I wanted.
So the point is and I'm going to remember
to switch off the ring
[INAUDIBLE]
otherwise I will get embarrassed.
you can use a lot of tools.
Google would probably find the correct
answer for this
If you have a computer algebra program
like Mathematica or
Maple, you're going to be able to ask it
questions like that.
You can look this up in any number of
calculus text books.
So kind of going through all of these
rules I'm going to skip
that but when you come to a function you
don't know how
to take the derivative of there're lots of
tools available online or
in the library that will help you figure
out how to do that.
So what we just found
out from Wolfram Alpha via Siri was that
the derivative
of this function e to the x is just
itself.
So it's a it's a special function that has
the property that it's own derivative.
So this one, will be the easy one to take
the derivative of.
And, this is isn't going to be too hard
either.
You can think of x as just x to the one.
And use the power rule.
So you get one times x to the one minus
one, or one.
So I'm going to break this up as f of x
equals x.
G of x equals e to the x.
And then just, evaluate this.
So what I end up is derivative of x is one
times e to the x.
Plus derivative of e to the x, which is
itself, times x.
And then, I'm just going to Do a little
bit
of grouping like this, because I think it
looks nicer.
But either this or this line.
These would both be acceptable answers
for, for the derivative.
So, for my second example, I defined p of
t.
So here, there's no real difference
between using x and t.
It's just the variable.
I can call it anything I want to.
a lot of times, t shows up as kind of a
variable name for time.
X shows up for position, You know?
S shows up for an asset price.
it doesn't matter you do everything
exactly the same,
regardless of how you choose to label the
parts of your function.
And so p of t is defined to be the square
root of t times the quantity 1 minus t.
And so I'm going to look at this, and I'm
going to say,
well that, if I want that to be a product,
the, the
simplest thing Is going to be the square
root of t,
as f of x, and one minus t as g of x.
And then to make taking the square root
possible, I
can rewrite that as t to the one half
power.
And so this is just another way to express
roots.
So if I wanted the cube root of t, that
would be
t to the 1 3rd power and so on and it's a
lot easier I think to take the derivative
when it's written like
this, it's just very clear that you can
use the power rule.
So now that I've defined my f of t and g
of t I'm
just going to take the derivatives and
then plug the, plug the pieces into the.
Product rule.
So the derivative of t to the one half
that's by the power rule
just going to be one half times t to the
one half minus 1.
So one half times t to the negative one
half then times g of t.
So times the quantity 1 minus t.
Plus t to the one half, so that my f of t.
And then the derivative of 1 minus t, we
have to
sort of, in our head, use the linear ity
principal and the power rule at the same
time.
So this says that I can take the
derivative of g of t,
it's going to be the derivative of 1,
which is a constant so it's zero.
And the derivative of minus t, which is
just going to be negative 1.
So that's where this minus 1 comes from.
It's a derivative of minus t.
And then I can
do a little bit of simplification.
replace the t to the one half with a
square root of t, if you want to.
And maybe mess around with it a little bit
to make it a bit more pretty.
But again, you know, once you are
this far, you've successfully taken the
derivative,
and the rest of this is just to make it a
little bit more presentable.
The next rule I want to talk about is
called the chain rule.
This is probably the most important rule,
and where you will make the most mistakes.
So again, we're going to talk about two
differentiable
functions, f of x and g of x.
And so last time we we thought about
multiplying them together.
This time we're going to think about
evaluating, how did I do this,
so f of x.
Taking the result of that and feeding
it into g of x.
And so that's called a composite function.
The text book uses this notation, all it
means is so g composed with f of x is,
sorry,
g evaluated.
At f of x, I find it a lot more sensible
just to always write it down like this.
Any time I've
tried to write it down like this, I end up
confusing myself, so I prefer this
notation.
So if f of x and g of x are differentiable
functions, then the composite function g
of f of x is also differentiable
and the derivative of this composite
function is the derivative of the
outside function.
So the derivative of g of x evaluated at f
of x times f prime of x.
And, so like I said, I really don't like
this notation of the composite fuction.
I, I tend to confuse myself.
So, another way you can write this is
using
something called Leibniz Notation, who is
just another mathematician
and so what you do is you think of you
think of it in sort of two steps.
So first I'm going to evaluate f of x and
that's going to give me a number u.
And then I'm going to evaluate g at that
number
u to get my final answer, g of f of x.
And the chain rule then says that the
derivative of
g, so the derivative of the outside
function, with respect
to x which is the argument of the inside
function,
is the derivative of just g with respect
to it's argument,
times the derivative of u.
So the argument for the outside function
with respect to x.
And I think this will become clear once I
start doing some examples.
So like I said this is called Leibniz
notation.
So first I'll try to do a few using using
this funny Composite function notation.
So if I say g of f of x is equal to the
square root of x squared plus 1 then I
sort of have to look at that and say that
this has to somehow be two functions.
So the two functions I see.
Are x squared plus 1, and then the square
root.
And again, just to make this a little bit
simpler, I'm
going to write the square root as this
quantity to the one
half power, and that's going to hopefully
stop me from making quite
so many I suppose typographical errors
while I'm writing this out.
And so the chain rule then says that the
derivative of g composed with
f is going to be the derivative of g so
that's just going to be one half.
Times the quantity x squared plus 1 to the
one half minus 1.
So negative one half.
Then times f prime of x.
So, here the f of x is x squared plus 1.
And so, by the power rule I can see
that x squared, it's derivative is just
going to be 2x.
Then one is a constant, so it's derivative
is zero.
So I end up multiplying this thing by x,
and then
I can re-write my one half power as a
square root again.
This two over here is going to cancel out
my one half, and so
I get a little bit nicer looking format
once I simplify a bit.
And you can do the same thing this is one
examples from the text book.
it's exactly the same problem as this one
up here just with some different numbers
so, I
have something on the inside and then the
outside function is that raised to the
hundredth power.
So when I take the derivative of that.
First I'm just going to say, 100 times
the,
the quantity to the 100 minus 1, so 99.
And then the chain rule says, to get the
derivative right,
I also need to multiply this by the
derivative of the inside.
So that gives me 3x squared over here and
if I simplify the sense of being the
derivative.
If instead we, we think about this using
the Leibniz notation the way I
want to set up problems is using something
called substitution.
So suppose I want to compute the
derivative of the sine of x squared.
Well if I just look at that as one
function, I don't know how to take the
derivative
of that, but you can see right away that
you do know how to take the derivative of
sine.
If you
don't you can ask Siri or Google search
Wolfram Alpha
[COUGH].
So, what I'm going to do is to find a new
variable u, that's equal to x squared.
And now if I replace x squared with u, I
would know how to take the derivative of
this function.
And so that means my function g of u is
just going to be sin of u.
So it's.
Sin of x squared, if I replace x squared
with u, I just get sin of u.
And then I'm also going to need this du dx
over here,
so I'm going to get that just by taking
the derivative of this.
So, the derivative of u, is just going to
be 2x, so du dx is going to equal 2x
So if I take the derivative, and this is
where you have to be a bit careful
of not getting variable names confused,
I'm taking the
derivative with respect to x of the sin of
u, and so that, what the chain rule is
telling me is if I want to do this, I can
just take the derivative of sin of u with
respect to u, so that's this first term
in the, in the chain rule.
And then, I need to multiply that times
the derivative of my substitution.
So here I've substituted u equals x
squared, so I have to take
the derivative of that, and multiply it in
To whatever I get here.
And so now I can just go ahead and start
evaluating derivatives, so you can
look up the derivative for the sine
function, you'll find that it's cosine of
u.
And the derivative of u, with respect to
x, that's easy
to get from here, just by using the power
rule, is 2x.
But now I still have a u in my answer
here, but I can just
undo my substitution now by going back and
saying, well, u is equal to x squared.
So
I end up getting the correct answer here,
2x times cosine of x squared.
And so another example Suppose I try to
take the exponential of sin of theta.
And I want to take the derivative of this
with respect to theta.
So here I see two functions.
The inside function is going to be the
sine function.
And the outside function is going to be
the exponential function.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to
let u be the value of the inside function.
So I'm going to make the substitution u
equals sign of theta.
And then I'll fill in the rest of the
pieces like I did in the first example
so g of u is then just going to be e to
the u.
So I get that just by looking at my
original function and making
the substitution u equals sin of theta or
sin of theta equals u.
And then I also need the derivative of my
transformation, or of
my substitution so du d theta is just
going to be cosine of theta.
So if I take the derivative of ops, the
derivative of this here,
ops with respect to theta.
I'm just going to get cosine of theta.
And then I just start plugging things into
the chain rule.
So I get the derivative with respect to x.
Ops, that should be a theta there.
So derivative of E to the sin theta with
respect to theta.
Is the derivative of e to the u with
respect
to u times the derivative of u with
respect to theta.
Derivative of e to the u, well we've
already seen
this, this was the special function that's
its own derivative.
So that just stays.
Where did my mouse go.
That, that's not good.
Okay, there it goes.
That just stays e to the u.
Du d theta becomes cosine theta and now I
have to, I have
this u here which I don't want anymore,
because the answer should be in
terms of theta, so I just have to
substitute backwards and I get
the, the final answer, cosine of theta
times e to the sine of theta.
And then just one last rule.
So if you have an inverse function, so an
inverse function of a function
f of x Is a function f inverse that just
gives me back
the argument, so it sort of undoes
whatever my function just did.
So if I take f inverse of f of x, I just
get x back.
And you have to be a little bit
careful here because F has to be sort of a
function where this is going to work.
So if I did something that was periodic,
like if
I looked at a sine function or a cosine
function.
That's very easy to take the x variable
and get a y variable.
But if I just tell you the y variable,
there's going to be a whole bunch of x
variables.
That will give you that
same y variable.
So you have to define it on a region where
it's one to one both directions.
So that I can actually do this and get
exactly the same x back that I put in.
And so f inverse is then just going to be
a function so f.
Takes a point in a b and gives me back a
point
in c d and f inverse is just going to take
that point
in c d and give me back my original point
in a
b and I have to choose these intervals so
that, that is unique.
So that I can go forward and go back and
get the same answer.
For all of the points in the interval a,
b.
So then there's a rule for computing the
deritivative of the inverse function.
And so as long as this thing in the
denominator, is not equal to zero.
Then the derivative of the inverse
function is just
1 divided by f prime evaluated at the
inverse function.
And so just as a quick example, consider
log of e to
the x, so these are functions that are,
kind of, undo one another.
So log of e to the x is always equal to x.
So I'm going to say, my function f is e to
the x.
F prime of x, so e to the x is this
special function
that's it's own derivative, so f prime is
just e to the x.
And then, f inverse is going to be the log
function.
And so, if I look at the derivative of log
of x.
It tells me that I should just take 1
divided by f prime.
So that's e to the x.
Evaluated at f inverse, so f inverse is
log x.
So it's e to the log x and so just like we
had log of e to the x was x, here I have
e to the log of x is also x.
And so that tells me that the derivative
of the logarithm is 1 over x.
And again, you could ask Wolfram Alpha
what's the derivative of the logarithmic
function.
And it's going to tell you it's 1 over x.
Okay so just a quick summary.
We had the, the product rule.
So that said the product of two functions,
f of x and g of x, was just, sorry the
derivative of a product.
Is the derivative of the first function
times the second function,
plus the first function times the
derivative of the second functin.
We had the chain rule.
So I like this notation a bit better.
So it says that the derivative
of a function of a function.
Is the derivative of the outside
function times the derivative of the
inside function.