Space missions and related areas have
been a fruitful source of applications
for AI planning over a long period of
time.
One of the earliest AI planners applied
to spacecraft missions was Steve Veers De
Visa planner created at NASA's Jet
Propulsion Lab in the early 1980's.
Optimum-AIV is a deployed planner used
for Ariane rocket assembly, integration
and test based on the old plan design.
Applications have also included ground
segment planning and control.
Telecommand of meteorological satellites.
Experiments in technology proving that in
the control of autonomous space craft
that a wide range of planners built at
the European Space Agency and in NASA and
we'll cover some of those in this
feature.
And the remote agent experiment within
deep space one.
Divisor created at NASA's jet propulsion
laboratory by Steve Vair was the first
NASA AI planner.
As based on the nominally design, but
added time window handling.
It could produce Voyager mission plans.
As part of our own work with the British
National Space Centre on the TSat
Technology Proving Satellite design The T
sched-, scheduler was able to generate
plans on the ground that were suitable
for controlling the spacecraft.
A 24-hour plan was created, uploaded and
executed live onboard the UoSat-2
spacecraft.
In early work at the European Space
Agency, an AI planner for ERS one
operation planning was created, and later
modified to become the optimum AIV
planner for assembly integration and test
of the paid load bay of Arian rockets.
There are quite a range of projects in
the European Space Agency that you AI
planning methods, and a few of them are
listed here.
You can find more details on the European
Space Agency's space craft operation
websites.
Esa's project for on-board autonomy,
Prober, has had a series of spacecraft
which have demonstrated potential and
feasibility small satellites with Van
Syke scientific and Earth observation
missions and some have been controlled by
automated ground systems.
Nasa also had a wide range of spacecraft
with AI planning embedded in them over
the years.
And some examples listed here, which is
Aspen and Casper.
More details of these projects are
available at the NASA JPL, and NASARange
websites.
The NASA Mars exploration laboratory
Curiosity has been a target for a range
of a I methods during its development
stages and now in its operation.
This has not only included the rover
itself, but also the communications with
it, spacecraft to support it, the
operation centers which are used to
control and communicate with the robot,
and even some of the proprietary work
which has gone into the design simulation
of the rovers and other equipment that's
relevant to these missions.
Take a moment to think about the
curiosity mission.
Imagine the opportunities for AI methods
from its design and inception as a
mission right through to the launching of
the spacecraft.
The landing of the spacecraft on Mars.
And then its operations.