Hello, my name is Nils Nilsson.
I helped in the development of A Star and
STRIPS,
and I'd like to explain a little bit
about the history of those programs.
In the mid 1960's at SRI, then called the
Stanford Research Institute, I was
working on a robot called Shakey.
Shakey had several programs, some for
dealing with perception. We had machine
vision programs, for example, and some
controlled Shakey's actions as it moved
around in it's environment.
There were two problems in developing
these programs for controlling Shakey's
actions. One problem was how Shakey should
navigate throughout a, a room strewn with
obstacles without bumping in to any of
them.
Another problem concerned how Shakey
should put together its high level
actions in order to achieve high level
goals.
With regard to the navigation problem, we
set up waypoints that were adjacent to
and somewhat standing off of various
obstacles in the room.
These waypoints could be considered nodes
in a graph.
The edges of the graph would be the
straight line distances between way
points that Shakey would be able to
travel.
So the problem of navigating from one
point in the room to another is the same
as the problem of finding the shortest
path in a graph.
Edgar Dykstra had an algorithm for doing
just that, but the problem with the
Dykstra algorithm was that it searched
outward from the start node toward the
goal in all directions.
What we wanted was an algorithm that
focused its search more in the direction
of the goal.
Now I was aware of a program developed at
Edinburgh University, a graph traverser
program, by Jim Dorin and Donald Rickey
that did focus toward the goal.
Their algorithm assigned numbers to nodes
in the graph that were purported to be
the difficulty of achieving the goal from
that particular node.
I suggested that, that number ought to be
an estimate of the distance from the node
to the goal, ignoring any obstacles that
might be in the way.
A colleague at SRI, Burt Brofel,
suggested that the number ought to
involve, also.
The distance from the start node to the
node in question and that would prevent
Shakey from being led down promising but
ultimately futile paths.
Another colleague, Peter Hart, suggested
that if the estimate from the node to the
goal was a lower bound on the true
distance Shakey would have to travel from
that node to the goal. Then the
algorithm, which we named A Star, would
in fact achieve the shortest path that
was possible.
Then Peter Hart and Burt Rayfield /g and
I together set about to prove Peter's
conjecture and that was the development
of the A star algoritm which involved
this number associated with each node
that in, that was a sum of the distance
from the start node to the node in
question plus the estimate of the
distance from that node to the goal.
With regard to the second problem, the
one I'm stringing together, Shakey's high
level actions to achieve higher level
goals, Richard Fikes and I, another
colleague at SRI, developed a system we
called STRIPS for Stanford Research
Institute Problem Solver.
STRIPS used high-level models of Shakey's
world, that is instead of just the
coordinates, the positions in Shakey's
room, we used a database of facts that
were true of particular situations that
Shakey could get itself into.
So we still wanted to be able to solve
the problem of achieving these high-level
goals by some sort of graph searching
program.
And so the starting node of the graph
would be a list of all the facts that
were true in Shakey's present situation.
The goal then was also described by some
statements of facts that we wanted Shakey
to make true by achieving, by applying,
actually, these high-level actions.
So what we needed in order to convert
this into a search problem in the graph
would be a computational way of producing
states of the world, that is, other
databases describing what a particular
state of the world would be when Shakey
applied one of it's high-level actions.
To perform that computation, we invented
something called STRIPS rules.
Now, a STRIPS rule would consist of a
pre-condition, that is to say all of the
facts that had to be in a particular
world, in order for Shakey to apply one of
it's high-level actions.
A delete list, that is to say a list of
facts which could no longer be guaranteed
to be true if Shakey did apply one of it's
high-level actions, and an add list,
which would be those facts which the
high-level action would make true.
And so what we did is use these strips
rules to go from one state, that is one
database describing Shakey's current
situation, to successor states in the
graph.
So we could even use the A Star algorithm
if we had a good way of, estimating what
the distance would be from one of these
databases, to one which had Shakey's goal
achieved.
So we could use A Star, if we had that
particular system.
Actually, in the system that we employed
at program, the STRIPS system, we worked
backwards from the goal by applying these
STRIPS operators in a somewhat backward
direction.
Those of us who were involved in the
development, A star and STRIPS, are
gratified to know that these systems are
used in many present day AI applications.