>> And here is part of the planning graph
for the simple dock worker robot example
you've seen earlier.
You remember the initial state consisted
of 6 proposition symbols and in our
proposition layer P0, we find nodes for
these six symbols.
So, each of these proposition symbols,
represent a node in our graph.
Which means we have six nodes.
And the blue background is simply to
indicate the layer as a whole.
So this is proposition layer p zero.
And with this proposition layer fully
defined we can see which nodes are in the
following action layer and these are only
those action symbols that would be
applicable in this state.
Again, these are four individual nodes
here, all together making up the action
layer A1.
And before we look at the next position
there, we can introduce those edges that
connect these actions to their
preconditions, and they are shown here.
As black lines.
Now given our proposition layer P0 and our
actual layer A1 we can define our
proposition layer P1 which contains all
the notes from P0 plus all the positive
effect of actions in A1 and these are all
those propositions we see here.
Again these are individual notes even if
they are not shown as such, the blue
background indicates what constitutes this
proposition layer, and that is all that is
in proposition layer P1.
And we need to connect this layer to the
preceding action layer on the one hand,
through the positive effects of the
actions, so these are the green lines
here.
And then, we also have the negative
effects that are indicated as red lines
here.
And this is the planning graph up to and
including proposition layer p1.
And we can now continue with the action
layer a2.
Now we take proposition layer p1 and
interpret it as a state and see which
actions would be applicable in that state.
And that's this list here.
That's all the actions that are in action
layer a2.
And again we have to introduce edges or
arcs from p1 to a2 representing all the
pre-conditions of these actions, and they
are given here.
And with p1 and a2 defined, we can now see
which nodes are in proposition layer two,
p2 and these are given here.
Again, they're individual nodes rather
than just one set.
But that is the whole set of nodes in
proposition layer p2.
They are all the nodes from P1, plus the
positive effects of actions in A2.
What's missing are of course still the
edges.
And we need edges that connect
propositions in P2 to actions where they
are positive and negative effects.
And again, we have green lines for
positive effects and red lines for
negative effects here.
And so on here come the propositions, that
are in action layer A3, and they are
connected through edges to their,
preconditions.
And we will do 1 more.
Here come the propositions, in proposition
layer P3.
And again, we have to have edges that
connect them to actions where they are
positive or negative effects.
And of course, I could be continuing with
this graph here, but A, I'm running out of
space, and B, I think you get the point
now.
Earlier, I talked about reachability,
reachability of goals and reachability of
individual propositions in a goal.
Now, we will look at the planning graph,
and see what the planning graph can tell
us about reachability.
So here is what we can say about the
planning graph.
Suppose we are given a planning problem,
and construct the planning graph for this
problem, then we have the following.
If a goal, g, is reachable from the
initial state si, then there must be a
proposition layer Pg in our planning
graph, such that all the goal conditions,
all the nodes representing those
propositions that are goals, are a subset
of this proposition layer Pg.
The proof of this is very simple, as you
can see.
If the goal G is reachable from si, then
there must be a plan, which is an action
sequence that achieves this goal.
And if we construct a planning graph,
consisting of 2n plus 1 layers, where n is
the length of our solution plan.
Then, this plan is contained in this
planning graph.
Where we select the first action in the
first action layer, and so on.
And that must achieve the goal.
So that means, in our last proposition
layer.
All the gold proposition.
Must be contained.
One caveat here is that this only works in
one direction.
So if we have the first part true, then we
can conclude that there must be such a
layer in the planning graph.
So, you can look at it the other way
around.
If there's a goal condition g.
That is not contained in our final
planning graph layer PG.
Then this goal condition can't be acheived
within this planning graph, and that of
course means that the overall goal can't
be acheived in the planning graph.
So what this gives us is a neccasary
condition for when a solution must exist
but not a sufficient condition.
So we can compare this to the reachability
tree we have looked at earlier.
The reachability tree was a sufficient
condition for testing whether a goal state
exists.
And that is because all the nodes
contained sets of propositions that must
necessarily hold in that state, and all
the propositions in those states, were
consistent.
Whereas the planning graph contains
propositions in these proposition layers
that may hold, but whether they hold or
not depends on the action we select and
the previous action layer.
Also the proposition layers quickly
contain sets of inconsistent propositions.
That means, propositions that can never be
true in the same state.
As we've seen, a robot can never be at
location one and at location two at the
same time.
Similarly, the actions in one action layer
may never be applicable at the same time.
So that where actions for moving a robot
from one location to another and back in
the same action layer Those two actions
can of course never occur in parallel.
So the planning graph only gives us a
necessary condition for goal existence.
We can look at the last proposition layer,
and if our goal is not contained in the
last proposition layer, then this planning
graph does not contain a solution Plan.
The big advantage of the planning graph is
of course the low complexity.
The planning graph is polynomial in size
and it can be computed in polynomial time.
And this can be seen quite easily because
each action layer and each proposition
layer can contain at most all the
propositions we have.
And that is a finite number.
And we have n layers in our graph so we
can have n times the number of symbols we
have and that is polynomial.
In other words, we have a criterion for
plan existence that we can evaluate in
polynomial time.
But unfortunately it's only a necessary
condition.