After the knowledge engineering process,
we should have a planning domain and maybe
planning problems that we can give to a
planner as input.
The planner then does the plan generation,
and that's what we've looked at so far in
this course, algorithms that synthesize
plans.
But the algorithms we have looked at make
some assumptions which may not hold in the
planning problems we are trying to solve.
I will now try to give you an overview of
some other issues and problems that may
come up during plan generation and how
those can be addressed.
Before we talk about different types of
planning problems, here's another approach
to the planning problem as we've described
it so far.
Up to now, we have looked at planning
algorithms that take a planning problem,
apply some algorithm, and the result is
some plan that is a solution to the
planning problem.
Another way to solve planning problems,
the same planning problems, is to
transform the problem into a different
type of problem as a first solution step.
And in this approach here, the problem we
transform it to is a SAT problem, a
satisfiability problem.
I'm not going to describe the details how
this is done here, but SAT problems have
been for around a long time, and in fact,
three SAT was the first problem to be
proved and be complete.
So, there are a number of efficient
solvers that we can use to solve SAT
problems and what they give us is the SAT
solution, which is an assignment of truth
values to propositional variables in the
SAT problem.
And given such a SAT solution, it is
fairly easy to extract a plan from this
solution.
So you can see, this approach is quite
different from everything we've seen
previously, because it doesn't tackle the
problem head on, but transforms it into a
different problem, solves that problem,
and extracts the solution from the other
solution.
And the main reason why this approach
works so well is, of course, that we have
efficient SAT solvers.
This approach was quite successful in the
mid to late '90s, and the planner that
implemented it was called blackbox.
All the planning algorithms we've looked
at so far deal with planning problems
where the actions are deterministic.
That means, if we apply an applicable
action in a given state, we end up in
exactly one other state and that state is
known.
However, there are many problems where the
outcome of actions is uncertain, and if
the outcome of an action is uncertain,
that means, after we apply this action, we
don't know exactly which state we are in.
So, the state we are in is also uncertain.
Now, there are at least two different ways
in which this type of uncertainty can be
dealt with.
The first approach is called belief state
search, and our search space in this
approach is a state of belief states,
where each belief state is really a set of
world states.
And we know that only one of these states
is the actual states, but we don't know
which one, but we know it as one of them.
So that's what we call a belief state,
it's a set of world states.
Then, when we apply an action in a belief
state, of course, the outcome is the union
of all the successors of the individual
states.
So again, it's a belief state, a set of
world states.
So this gives us a search space, as we've
seen it before, and the result then is a
solution plan, which is a sequence of
actions as we have before.
Another approach to dealing with
uncertainty is called contingency
planning.
In contingency planning, what we have is
actions that have multiple possible
outcomes and these action outcomes are
known as contingencies.
Usually, the number of contingencies is
fairly small and not every action must
have contingencies.
So that means, when we search through our
search space, we can still deal with
individual world sets.
But now, our solution plan has a tree
structure that branches where we have take
into account the different contingencies.
And also, our solution plan will contain
observation actions at the branching
points Where we, during execution, observe
which of the branches is actually
happening.
Of course, both these approaches are a lot
more complex than what we've seen so far.
In belief state search, we have sets of
world states as our notes so an
exponential increase in the size of the
search space.
And in contingency planning, we look at
plans that are trees, so they are also a
lot larger than the plans we've looked at
so far.
Sometimes, the degree of uncertainty that
we have in a planning problem can be
quantified.
That is, we know with which probabilities
the different outcomes of an action can
occur.
This approach is called probabilistic
planning and is based on a different
conceptual model.
So we're no longer looking at simple state
transition systems, as we have so far, but
the new conceptual model is called a
Partially Observable Markov Decision
Process.
This one here.
And in this model, we have a lot of
familiar things.
So firstly, we have a set of world states
through which we are searching, and then,
we have a set of actions that give us our
state transitions.
And of course, in some sets, certain
actions are applicable and they must be a
subset of all the actions that are
available.
What we also have is a cost function that
gives the cost of an action applied in a
given state and this cost must be greater
than 0.
So far, this should all look familiar.
But then, in addition to all this, we have
the transition probabilities.
That is we have a function that gives us
the probability for each action that we
end up in state as prime given that we
started in state s.
So this is the probability that we get
from s to s prime when we execute the
action a.
Then, our planning problem also must
include an initial belief state, that is,
a probability distribution over all the
states in s.
So we don't know exactly which state we
start in, but we have a probability
distribution that tells us how likely it
is that we are in a given state.
And, we have a final belief state, which
corresponds to our goal.
Now, the solutions to our probabilistic
planning problems look quite different
from what we've seen so far.
They are no longer action sequences, but
they are something known as a policy.
A policy is effectively a function that
maps states into actions.
Namely, if we are in a given state, that's
the action we should execute.
That most likely leads us to a goal state.
And often, the policy we're looking for is
an optimal policy, which is simply one
that has a minimal expected cost.