>> What I still owe you is a definition
for mutual exclusivity, or mutex, between
actions, and again, I will start by
illustrating this with an example.
We are looking at the same planning graph
as before here but now, our first layer,
we're looking at is the proposition layer
p1, that was on the right-hand side on the
previous graph.
So, we have p1, a2, and p2 in this graph
here.
And I'm sure you will remember from the
previous example that in proposition layer
p1, the propositions r1 and r2 were
incompatible.
So, they were mutex.
Now, we know that our proposition r1 is a
precondition for the action Lar1 in our
action layer A2.
And the proposition r2 is a precondition
for Mr21 in the same action layer.
And it should be clear to you that if
these two propositions that are
preconditions for these two actions are
mutually exclusive, so they cannot be true
in this proposition layer together.
Then, the two actions cannot occur in the
following action layer.
So, these two actions must be mutually
exclusive here.
So, what we've seen now, is that mutual
exclusivity between actions can lead to
mutual exclusivity between propositions,
in the following proposition layer and the
other way around.
Mutual exclusivity between propositions
can lead to mutual exclusivity in the
following action layer.
And now, we can formally define what it
means for two actions in the same action
layer to be mutually exclusive.
And this definition is quite simple.
We can say that two actions, a1 and a2,
that are in the same action layer, Aj, are
mutex if one of the following two
conditions holds.
Firstly, if a1 and a2 are dependent.
So, if the dependency we've defined
earlier holds between these two actions,
then they're also mutex.
Or a precondition of a1 is mutex with a
precondition of a2.
If there are preconditions that are
mutually exclusive, then the two actions
are also mutually exclusive.
And these are the only two reasons why two
actions in the same action layer are maybe
mutually exclusive.
Note that the first of these two
conditions is problem-independent, so
dependency does not need to be recomputed
for each action layer Aj, it's always the
same whether two actions are dependent or
not.
Whereas, the second condition does depend
on the action layer in which the two
actions are because we're referring to
preconditions which are propositions in
the preceding proposition layer.
And now, again, a bit of notation.
I want to introduce the set mu Aj which
we've already used in the previous
algorithm, which is the set of all pairs,
a1, a2, in an action layer Aj that are
mutex.
So, these are all the mutex pairs of
actions in a given action layer, namely
the action layer Aj.
And I can now tell you that in the example
we've just looked at, in the action layer
a2, there were actually 24 mutex pairs of
actions that may help you to understand
why I'm not drawing these mutex links into
the graph every time I draw the graph.
And a final remark about the mutex
relation and this applies to propositions
as well as actions, this relation is
symmetric.
So, if a1 is mutex to a2, then a2 must
also be mutex to a1 and again, the same
goes for propositions.
And again, for those of you who prefer an
algorithm to a definition, here comes an
algorithm is pseudo code defining the
function mutex for a given pair of actions
and the set of mutex proposition pairs in
the preceding propositions there.
And in this algorithm, we simply were,
test what we've just defined, namely, the
first thing we do is we test whether the
two actions are not independent, so if
these two actions are dependent, then they
are also mutex, which means we return,
true.
Otherwise, we have to look for a pair of
preconditions of a1 and a2 respectively.
And these are the preconditions p1 and p2
and see whether these preconditions are
mutually exclusive.
So, if we find such a pair of
preconditions for these two actions that
are mutually exclusive, then we know these
two actions are also mutually exclusive.
If we cannot find such a pair and the two
actions are independent, then we return
false, meaning, a1 and a2 are not mutually
exclusive.
As for the time complexity of the
algorithm, you can see it consists of two
parts.
So, we have the time complexity of the
first part plus the complexity of the
second part.
And this is simply O of b squared, where b
is the maximum number of preconditions and
the fact we have per action.
Now, that we understand what mutex
relations are and how to compute them, I
want to see how mutex relations propagate
through the planning graph and that is
quite important.
So, we have two propositions here that
tell us how mutex relations propagate
through the planning graph.
And the first one says that if we have a
pair, p,q that is in our proposition
layer, Pj minus 1, and they are not
mutually exclusive in that layer, then,
this same pair of propositions will also
be not mutually exclusive in the next
proposition there.
This means, once a pair of propositions
that has appeared as mutex in the planning
graph, once this pair has become
non-mutex, it can never become mutex again
in a later layer.
So, the mutex relations are, in some
sense, decreasing the further down the
planning graph we go.
And to see that this is true is actually
quite simple.
So, we assume that p and q are in our
proposition layer Pj minus 1.
And, of course, that we means we have the
no-op operations for these two
propositions in the following action
layer.
And we have assumed that the propositions,
p and q, are not mutex in that proposition
layer.
So, that means the two no-op operations
are also not mutex in their action layer.
And that, of course, means we have a
non-mutex pair of actions that produce p
and q in the next proposition layer and
that means they can't be mutually
exclusive.
And we have a similar proposition from the
mutex relation between actions.
Namely, that if two actions are in one
action layer and they are not mutex in
that action layer, then they are also not
mutex in the following action layer.
And again, the reason for this is quite
simple.
So, if we are given that a1 and a2 are not
mutex in this action layer Aj minus 1,
then by definition, that means a1 and a2
must be independent, and the preconditions
cannot be mutex in Pj minus 1.
Now, I've already told you in the previous
proposition that because mutual
exclusivity between the preconditions
carries forward, the preconditions for the
actions in the next layer must also not be
mutex and, of course, action independence
is constant.
So, what this means is both of these
properties remain true for the next
proposition there, and hence, our two
actions remain independent and therefore,
mutex.
So, this is a very important property of
the mutex relation that it's decreasing
with increasing layer.
That's true for propositions and for
actions, and we will get back to that
later.
Now, before we move on with the graph plan
system, there is one further refinement to
the planning graph that I want to
introduce to you.
And this is actually quite simple, now
that you understand the mutex relations
between propositions.
So, suppose we have two propositions, p
and q, that are mutex, and that are
preconditions for the same action.
In this example here, we have the action
Uar2, and it has two preconditions, r2 and
ar, and they are mutually exclusive.
That, of course, means that we can never
execute that action Uar2 in that action
layer.
And what we do in this case is simply
remove the node that represents that
action and all its edges from our planning
graph.
We remove Uar2 from A2.
It's as simple as that.