The topic for week one is limits and
derivatives.
And the topics we're going to cover are,
so
I'll start of with a concept called
present value,
and this is just a way to decide how
much a future stream of payments is worth
today.
And then I'm going to use the idea of
present value to motivate a mathematical
idea called a limit.
And a limit is just,
it's the value of a sequence of functions
or
a sequence of numbers as you just keep
going.
So it's something that you can never
actually
arrive at, but it's something you can
approximate.
In section four, we'll talk about
evaluating limits, so
this is a very a very common mathematical
operation.
Section five, I'll introduce a concept
called continuity, and so you can think of
a continuous function as just one that you
could draw without lifting up your pen.
Mathematically, the way I would say that
is that
a continuous function is a function where
the limit
of a function as I approach a certain
value
is just equal to the function evaluated at
that value.
In section six, I am going to then apply
the limit to a.
To an estimate of the slope of a function.
And then when I take the limit I end up
with something called a derivative, so
that's, going to be differentiation.
And on the rest of the lecture, is
just going to be methods for evaluating
derivatives.
So we'll talk about something called the
product rule and the chain rule.
So this is when I have
a, a complicated function, a function
that's made up of smaller functions.
I can express the derivative of my
function
in terms of the derivatives of those
smaller functions.
I can do higher derivatives, so a higher
derivative
is just a derivative of a derivative of a
function.
And then, I'll give an example using a
concept called Duration Of A Bond.
And then, finally, finish this week with
L'Hopital's Rule.
And L'Hopital's Rule is a way of
evaluating a limit
that's undefined.
So, I could end up with a limit of, of
something like 0 divided by 0.
I can actually use derivatives to make
sense of a limit like that.