So we'll pick up, where we left off last
time.
with differentiation.
So last time we, we went through present
value.
We used that, a little bit to motivate the
idea of a limit.
And then I tried to give an example of
when a limit's not going to work.
And when a limit is going to work.
And then I gave some rules for evaluating
limits.
And then we talked about continuity.
And now we're going to talk about
differentiation.
So differentiation is basically the, the
problem.
We want to solve is we have some curve, so
you can imagine in a xy plane.
You just define the value of y as some
function of x.
And I want to find the slope of a tangent
line to this curve, at a point a.
So, this is sort of a picture of what I'm
trying to do.
So, this blue line is my curve, y equals f
of x.
Then I choose some point a on the x axis.
The corresponding point on the y axis.
So, what's going to make up this curve is
just going to be f of a.
And, I want to touch a line to this curve,
so that it only touches at exactly one
point.
And I'm going to call that a tangent line.
And the problem I'm trying to solve is if
I know this point
right here, I want to know what the slope
of this tangent line is.
And so just to make that, this idea of a
tangent line a, a little bit more rigorous
I want to say that there's a a
neighborhood of width
delta, so it's delta to either side of
this point a.
And I'm going to say that this line here,
so
the the straight line is tangent to the
curve.
If f of x so l of x is going to be my line
f
of x is my function, if f of x is equal to
my function if
l of x is less than or equal to f of x so
in my little neighborhood there
goes to delta of either side because I'm
using a round bracket here.
I mean every point up to a but not
including a, so
every point less than a down to a minus
delta and every
point greater than a up to a plus delta, I
need to
have f of x greater than l of x so that
means
the curve has to be above the line
everywhere.
Or it has to be below the line everywhere.
So basically, what I'm trying to, to do by
having these two conditions.
I either have this shape here.
So the line is always below the curve.
Or I just have that upside down, so the
line would always be above the curve.
And I just need to have that true in some
little neighborhood.
So you can imagine.
A neighborhood about that
big around the point.
And I'm going to say then that this line
is tangent to the curve at
that point as long as f of a is equal to l
of a.
So, the function and the line have to have
the same value at a.
So, it touches at just one point but any
little bit to either side of that
point, the line is either always greater
than
the curve or always less than the curve.
So, that'll be a tangent line.
And the
interpretation I'm going to give that is
the slope of this tangent
line is going to be the slope of the curve
at the point.
So at this big blue point, the slope of
this curve
is going to be equal to the slope of that
tangent line.
So that's the problem I'm going to be
trying to solve by differentiation.
And so the way I'm going to approach that,
is, I'm going to try and approximate it.
So the normal definition of slope is rise
over run.
So, you know, you go forward a certain
amount.
You go up a certain amount.
And if I go up more, it's steeper.
If I go up less, it's, you know, less
steep.
But that's the concept I have of slope.
And so if I tried to just do this
approximation but using only one point,
it's not going to work.
So I have to pick two different points and
there has to be some non-zero
distance between them in the x direction
and so I'm going to call that the run.
And then I just evaluate the function at
the two points.
So I have f of x and f of x plus h.
And that's going to give me the, the
difference in height.
And so that becomes the rise.
And so in this picture because these
points are reasonably far apart.
I don't get a particularly good estimate
of what I'm after.
So this, this line, you know, it, it
clearly looks like it's steeper
than the curve at the point x where I'm
trying to estimate the slopes.
So it's a lot steeper than, ops.
If I go back one slide, it's a lot steeper
than this line that I'm trying to,
trying to find.
Oh, ops, I guess I had it one forward
there.
But, the idea is now once I've set this
up, so
I have an estimate of the slope, so rise
over run.
So, it's f of x plus h minus f of x.
So, that's just this distance here, the
rise.
And then, the run is just going to be h.
So, it's x plus h minus x.
And I'm just going to try and improve my
estimate by letting this
point here, so the one on the right,
because I'm adding h.
I'm going to let that point slide along
the curve towards
x and hopefully as, as I get closer to x.
So as h is getting smaller The slope of
this line here is
getting closer and closer to the slope of
the line on the right
until finally in the limit hopefully the
slope of my approximation is going to
be the same as the slope of the tangent
line that I'm trying to get.
And so that's actually how we're going to
define the derivative.
So the derivative.
And we'll say a function f is
differentiable
at a point x, so it's this point x here,
if the
limit of my rise over run approximation
exists.
So I'm basically, I'm just looking at.
The rise divided by the run taking the
limit as that, as the
sort of bottom side of that triangle goes
to zero.
If that exists then I'm going to say the
derivative
exists so the function is differentiable
at this point x.
And I'm going to call that f prime of x.
So f prime of x Is my notation for the
derivative of f of x.
And then just like for continuity, we're
going to say a
function f of x is differentiable on an
open interval a, b.
If it is differentiable at every point in
a, b.
And so for a lot of functions, it's just
going to work on the entire real line.
If it's you know if it's differentiable
at all, it's differentiable at every real
number.
But you do have to be a little bit
careful,
so open, here, means that the interval
doesn't include the endpoints.
And so that's why I've used
the parentheses here rather than square
brackets.
And the only reason we have to do this, is
imagine if I wanted to compute the
derivative at b.
So the, where I'm going to run into a
problem, is in order to compute the
derivative
at b, I'd have a b here.
And I have to add, ops, I have to add a
little bit of h to that b.
And if I can actually use the very last
point in the interval,
then if I add h to that, I'm going to be
outside of my interval.
So I have to just chop off the
last point and surprisingly that actually
always works.
So I can always find enough points to make
this limit exist.
And so for, for the purpose of this class
we're really
going to be more interested in actually
being able to compute limits.
Oh, sorry, to compute derivatives.
So, we can use just the definition of a
derivitive to
try and figure out what the The derivative
of a function is.
So for a, a quick example of this, just
consider this quadratic expression here.
So 3x squared
plus 5x plus 1.
So if I want to compute the derivative of
f of x using the definition Well, this is
my definition.
So I'm just going to start plugging things
into the definition and see what happens.
So the first thing I want to do is
evaluate my function f at x plus h.
So what that means I'm going to do is
replace every x up here.
With the quantity x plus h.
So now I have 3 times x plus h squared,
plus 5 times x plus h, plus 1.
So that's just this function up here
evaluated at the point x plus h.
Then I'm going to subtract f of x.
So that's just
me substituting in the definition of f of
x for this particular exercise.
And divide by h, and then, I'm going to
try and evaluate this limit and see what
happens.
And so the, the way you generally approach
this when
you have a, a polynomial, you just expand
These things, and
do the math and see what pops out.
And so that's what I've done
here, so x plus h squared is going to be x
squared plus 2xh plus h squared.
So I multiply that by three, and that's
where this bit comes from.
Then I have plus 5x and plus 5h.
That, it's here.
And then plus 1.
And then I'm just going to subtract each
of these terms.
And so what ends up happening is my, my
3x squared here, and 3x, negative 3x
squared here.
That gets rid of that x squared term.
I have a plus 1 here.
And a minus 1 here, a minus 5x and a plus
5x.
So a lot of these things are going to
cancel
each other out and if it works out, what's
going to happen is only the terms up here
that
still have an h in them are going to be
left.
Once I do
just this subtraction in the numerator.
So I end up with 6xh
3h squared and 5h, and I'm dividing that
by h.
And because I'm looking at the limit as h
goes to
zero I can pretend that h is always
greater than zero.
So if h is greater than zero I can
multiply the
top and the bottom by one over h, and get
rid
of this h in the bottom.
And so that means I can cancel out one h
from each term in the top.
So I end up with the limit as h goes to
zero, of 6x plus 3h plus 5.
And now this is a continuous function.
So it means that the limit as h goes to
zero is just equal to that function
evaluated at zero so I can just put Plug
in zero for h here.
And I get 6x plus 5.
And so this is telling me that the, the
slope of this curve
at a point x is equal to 6x plus 5.
Okay.
And really what we're going to do with the
derivative,
so sort of like continuity, or sort of
like limits.
Working with the definition is not very
much fun.
So what we want to do is use the
definition to
prove some rules that are going to make
computing derivatives easier.
So all of these rules can be proved, and
if you, if you
took a more rigorous math class that's
sort of what they would do.
we're going to be moving a bit faster, so
I'm just going to say the rules.
if you look in the textbook, there will be
proofs of some of these.
Or if you look in a first year calculus
book
in particular Stewart has all the proofs
for these things.
So the derivative of a constant is zero.
So if you ever see a constant.
That's something you're pretty happy to
take the
derivative of, it's hardly any work at
all.
second property is linearity.
So linearity means that if I have two
functions, so f of x and g of x.
And really what you're going to do is
you're generally going to be given one
function and
you're going to look at that and say that
one function is really made up of two
functions.
Two simpler functions, how am I going to
take the derivative of that?
And so, if I have f
of x and g of x differentiable functions,
and if a and b are real valued constants,
then I'm going to define l of x is a
linear combination of f of x And g of x.
If I just say a times f of x plus b times
g of x.
And the derivative of l of x,
so for, for linear combinations of
differentiable functions,
the derivative of a sum is just the sum of
the derivative.
So the derivative of this Is the sum of
the derivative
of the first term ops, and the derivative
of the second term.
And also note what happens to the
constant.
So if I have a times f of x, then the
derivative is just a times f prime of x.
So if I make the function twice as big.
Then the derivative, you know, at every
point that sort of
going to be twice as steep, so really
what's happening when you
multiply something by a, say, a is two,
that it stretches your
function, so that it's twice as tall as it
used to be.
And when you do that, what you're going to
end up doing
is just making the derivative twice as
steep as it used to be.
And then the final rule is called the
power rule.
So, sorry, final rule for this section.
There will be more rules.
So let n be a real valued constant.
Then the derivative of x to the n.
So for instance, this could be x squared,
x cubed, something like that, or any real
value.
So, x to the 2.5.
The derivative of that function
is n times x to the n minus 1.
And so, this this simple little trick is
called the power rule.
And then you can make combinations of the
power rule and this linearity property
and that makes it possible to take
the derivative of polynomials without too
much trouble.
So just a, a quick summary that definition
of
a derivative was f prime of x is the
limit.
Of f of x plus h minus f of x divided by
h.
So, that's just the limit of of the rise
over the run, as the run is going to zero.
Deriv derivative of a constant is zero, so
if f of
x is equal to the same value, no matter
where I choose
x that just means f of x is a flat line.
Then a derivative of a flat line is zero.
The slope of a flat line is zero.
Linearity so if I have a linear
combination of two differentiable
functions f of x and g of x, then the
derivative is just the linear combination
of the two derivatives.
So, af prime of x plus bg prime of x.
And then, the power rule.
And so, this time, instead of n, I wrote
it as c.
So, c is supposed to be my, my letter for
a real valued constant.
so for any c not equal to zero, x to the
c,
the derivative of that is c times x to the
c minus 1.
[BLANK_AUDIO]