Once we have computed the potential
resolvers for a given flaw in our plan,
we need to select one of these and apply
it to the current partial plan.
So, we'll refine our current partial plan
using the resolver we've just computed.
And the way this is done is very simple.
We have to add elements to the plan,
namely those elements that are specified
in our resolver.
So, this could be an ordering constraint,
it could be one or more binding
constraints in our variables,
it could be a new causal link, or it
could be a new action.
Or a combination of any of those,
whatever our resolver specified.
In general, we have to make sure that our
constraints that are maintained in the
plan are consistent.
But this is not required here.
This is the case because our function
that computes the resolvers for a given
flaw already took care of that.
So, we never consider resolvers that
would make our variable binding or
ordering constraints inconsistent.
But when we resolve a flaw and when we
introduce new causal links or new
actions, what we can do is we can
introduce new flaws into the plan by
doing so.
And that means we simply have to update
the flaws that know about in our plan,
and these are unachieved preconditions,
and we've seen that earlier how this can
be done with open goals computation, or
the threats.
And again, we had a function earlier that
does that incrementally.
During our plans based search, we
maintain a set of ordering constraints.
And here are a few words on the
implementation of ordering constraints.
In fact, you could see the ordering
constraints as an independent module that
can be plugged into our planner and that
has two access operations that we need to
support.
The first one is, we need to query
whether an action in our plan must come
before another action.
So, we need to be able to find out
whether two actions are already ordered
with respect to each other.
And then, of course at some stage, we
want to add new orderings to our
constraint network.
So, we want to assert that an action ai
must come before an action aj.
And let us assume that we don't have to
do consistency checking when we add an
ordering constraint to our constraint
network.
The first internal representation is this
one here.
Where we maintain the sets of
predecessors and successors for each
action, simply as they were given to the
constraint network.
So, if we have an action, we say this
ordered with respect to some other
action.
And then, we add more orderings as we go
along.
Then, we would just store these as we
were given these.
So now we're starting a third, fourth
ordering, here that says this action has
to come before this action.
So, the first option is to store the
orderings as given, which would store
four ordering constraints in this case.
This means we have a polynomial number of
orderings that we need to store,
polynomial in the number of nodes.
And every time we query this constraint
network, we have to compute the
transitive closure.
For example, if we want to query whether
this node comes before this node, we have
to compute the transitive closure.
The second option would be to store only
direct predecessor-successor relations.
So in this case, we would not store this
relation here.
This would not be a part of our internal
representation.
That would save some storage.
But the problem is, if we query the order
between these two nodes, again we have to
compute the transitive closure.
The final option would be to maintain the
transitive closure explicitly.
So, in this case, every time we assert a
new ordering we have to compute the
transitive closure with respect to all
other actions in our plan and maintain
every link explicitly.
That means when we query, we're very
fast.
But the problem is now that the
assertion, the adding of an ordering,
becomes a relatively slow operation.
In general, there's a trade-off between
space and time complexity between these
different representations.
But in the planner, we can assume that
the query is probably the most common
operation so we want this to be the
fastest, and therefore the third
representation is most likely to be the
best.
Similar to the ordering constraints, we
can think of the variable binding
constraints as the module that we can
plug into the planner.
And then, we have several types of
constraints that we've already looked at.
Firstly, there are unary constraints that
say that a variable x has to be of a give
domain.
This domain is a set of values, including
the case where it can be just one single
value, so we have a specific value for
our variable.
Then, we have equality constraints that
assert that two variables must have the
same value.
So, we don't know what values they will
take, but we know that eventually in our
final plan, they must have the same
value.
And finally, we have inequalities where
we say the two variables must have
different values.
The unary constraints and the equality
constraints, they are quite easy.
So these can be dealt with, in linear
time and don't cause any problems.
This, however, the inequality causes a
lot trouble because inequality
constraints cause exponential complexity
in this type of constraint network.
So with the inequalities, this becomes a
general constraint satisfaction problem
and a general constraint satisfaction
problem is NP-complete.
In some sense, this is really bad news.
Introducing variable inequalities was one
of the ways we had to resolve flaws,
namely flaws that are threats.
So, we have to deal with variable
inequalities.
But, that means that every step in out
plan refinement gives rise to an
NP-complete problem that we need to
solve, namely to maintaining the
consistancy of the variable binding
constraints. Finally, our generic plan
space search planner has the same two
properties that our states based planner
had,
namely it is sound and complete.
And that means whenever our planner is
given by zero or initial plan,
and that can be refined into a solution
plan,
then our function PSP of pi zero will
return a solution plan.
Or more explicitly, soundness means that
if the planner returns a result, then
this is indeed a solution plan.
And completeness means if there is a
solution plan, then our planner will be
able to find the solution plan.
The proof of this type of proposition is
similar to what we've seen earlier.
So, we do it by induction, and as our
loop invariant, we use that the ordering
and variable binding constraints are
consistent at every stage of the
algorithm.
So, we maintain this as part of the main
loop in the algorithm.
Then, we know that the planner only
returns a plan if this plan is flawless.
So, the plan is flawless and the ordering
and variables bindings are consistent,
therefore, it must be a solution plan.
And completeness can also be shown by
induction, this time induction on the
number of actions in our solution plan.
So, we start off with our initial plan
that contains two actions, the two dummy
actions.
And then, we show that for every plan
that is one action bigger.
There exists an execution trace of our
non-deterministic algorithm that can find
that solution plan.