Okay.
Second half of number seven, so week seven
is Taylor series.
So I'm going to go over something called
Taylor's formula for a function of one
variable.
And then just introduce a concept called"
Big O" notation.
Hopefully a lot of you have seen this
before but it's a pretty simple idea.
Just give you an idea of how fast a
function is growing or shrinking.
Then
I'll talk about a generalization of
Taylor's formula to functions of several
variables.
Something called Taylor series expansions.
And then some applications to bond
convexes.
So this is just carrying on from one of
the lectures from the
first week, where I talked about making a
linear approximation to our function.
And now we can add more terms to
that approximation to make it a little bit
better.
So I'll start off with Taylor's formula
for a function of one variable.
So my function is going to be f of x
and I'm going to assume that it's at least
n times differentiable.
So when I say that I mean I can take the
derivative of f of x to get f prime.
And then I can take the derivative of f
prime to get f
double prime and I can continue doing that
until I have n primes.
And each one of those functions is going
to be a differentiable function.
Then I'm also going to assume that a is
some
real number.
And the Taylor polynomial of order n
around the
point a is just defined to be this thing
here.
So what I do.
So I evaluate my function at the point a.
So the idea is, I know the value of my
function
at certain points and so I'm going to pick
one of those.
So a is going to be that point.
And then for points that are near a, I'm
just going to use the derivatives to make
an approximation.
And basically what's going on with this
polynomial, I
have x minus a times the first derivative.
I have x minus
a squared, times the second derivative
divided by two.
And then I can just keep going and the
general formula is
going to be x minus a to the kth power
times the kth derivative
evaluated at a, divided by k factorial.
And so that's just what the, the final
term here is.
Except that the last one is n, because I
said it's a Taylor polynomial of order n.
So that just means I go up until I'm using
x minus a
to the nth power and then that's the last
term in my Taylor polynomial.
And the idea of this Taylor polynomial is
that I want to be
able to use it to approximate f of a at
points x that are near a.
And so I can write this in a little bit
more compact notation just
like this, so I'm, I'm going from zero up
to n, so here's the.
Here's the nth term on the right here and
I can think of just evaluating the
function as
[COUGH]
as taking the zeroth derivative.
And then there's no x minus a here because
anything to the zero power is just one.
And so I want to use P sub n to
approximate f of x.
And so that the idea here is if I just
approximated f
of x by f of a, you know that might be
reasonably close.
it would just depend on how steep the
function was and how far away from a I am.
And then I could make my, my approximation
a little
bit better by if I, if I know the
derivative
of my function at a.
Then I can use a linear approximation on
either side of a.
And then I could make it again a little
bit better by adding a quadratic term so
I add a little bit of a parabola
and hopefully that'll make the
approximation a bit better.
And so the idea is as P sub n, as I add
more terms I'm getting
a better and better approximation of f of
x, but I want to be able to understand
how how good my approximation is.
And so that's what most of today's lecture
is going to be.
So the questions are does P sub n.
Whoops I've got this wrong so this should
be f of x.
But does P sub n of x converge to n, f of
x as n goes to infinity.
So as I add more terms.
You know, it's going to be a lot more work
to calculate
[UNKNOWN]
all these additional terms, so I want to
at least know that
each term I'm adding is getting me closer
to what I want.
And then order means how well does P sub n
approximate f of x?
So, suppose that this actually did
converge to f of x.
I would still need an infinite number of
terms to get exactly f of x.
So I'd like to know suppose I want to use
a third order polynomial.
You know, how far away from f of x am I?
So we'll
measure that distance using something
called approximation error.
And that's just going to be defined to be
the difference
between f of x and P sub n of x.
So P sub n of x is my polynomial that I'm
using for approximation and
then f of x is the target, that's the
function that I'm trying to approximate.
And if I, if I measure the error using an
order n.
Taylor polynomial.
I call
that the nth order Taylor approximation
error.
[COUGH]
And there are two forms, there are two
ways for me
to get a, a handle on the approximation
error.
So there's, the first one is called the
derivative form.
An so now, I had to assume that f of x was
least n times differentiable
in order to be able to make the
Taylor polynomial that I'm using to
approximate it.
If
I assume that I can take one more
derivative than that
and that, that derivative is a continuous
function.
Then there's a point c, so c is just some
point in the
interval between a and x.
So a is the point where
I've expanded my, my Taylor polynomial.
So I'm writing my Taylor polynomial in
powers of x minus a.
And then x is the point where I'm trying
to evaluate
the function, so ideally you want to have
x pretty close to a.
[COUGH]
And then there's going to be some point c
in
between a and x where the following
relationship holds.
So I have x minus a to the n plus one, so
sort of looks like it's the next term.
But instead of evaluating the derivative
at a exactly?
I'm going to evaluate it at this point c,
that's somewhere between x and a.
And that's and then I need to divide
by the n plus one factorial.
And that's actually not just an
approximation of
the air, but that's exactly equal to the
air.
So it depends.
On the choice of c but there's some choice
of c in this interval ax.
Where the approximation error I have
highlighted on the left hand
side is exactly equal to the thing on the
right hand side.
[COUGH]
And then there's also an integral form of
the approximation error.
So again I need the, the same condition.
But now I can express the Taylor
approximation error.
So the thing on the left hand side is, is
the same for both both
forms of the Taylor approximation error
for the
differentia, derivative form meant for the
integral form
[COUGH].
And now on the right hand side instead of
having this thing that looks like the next
term, it
looks more like the, the final term in the
Taylor
polynomial except it's multiplied by the n
plus first derivative.
And now I'm going to integrate this with
respect to t from a to x.
And so I've made this, this, I guess it
kind of looks like a Taylor term
but I now instead of having x minus a, I
have x minus t.
And then I'm also evaluating the n plus
first derivative at the point t.
But this is just a function.
And then I'm just going to multiply it by
this factor out in front.
That'll be another function.
I integrate that function with respect to
t and then use the limits a to x.
And now that's going to be again exactly
equal to the Taylor approximation error.
But this has
a sort of added bonus that there's not
this kind of indeterminate c.
So this is something you can just compute
directly but it's, it ends
up being a bit more work because to get
this form here, you've already taken
n plus or n derivatives, so you just have
to take one more derivative.
And you're basically finished with this
form up
here, except that you don't know what c
is.
Here, you do have to still take one more
derivative but then you have potentially
a complicated integral you have to
evaluate, to
figure out what the Taylor approximation
error is.
So let's look at a quick example.
I'm going to make a linear approximation
of the function f
of x equals log x around the point a
equals one.
So the black curve is just log x.
That's my target function.
I'm going to use a first order so P,
whoops
I guess I can't highlight stuff in the
picture.
P sub one of x is just a Taylor polynomial
of order one,
so that's just a linear approximation.
My point a was chosen because
I know log, log of one is a particularly
easy thing to evaluate, it's zero.
So the red line touches the curve at the
point x equals a.
So it's one zero.
And then you can see sort of in this
interval here maybe, plus or minus a
quarter from one.
It's actually a pretty good approximation
of
the function that I'm trying to
approximate.
[COUGH]
And so this is the, this is the general
form for our order one Taylor polynomial.
And then the derivative of log is just one
over x.
When I evaluate that at my point a equals
one, I just get one.
So this is my derivative one over one.
My point a is one, so I have x minus one
that quantity to the first power.
And then f of a is equal to log of one
which is zero.
So it turns out that x minus one is my
first order
Taylor polynomial to approximate log x at
the point a equals one.
So now let's look at Taylor approximation
error and again I'm
going to choose another point where it's
going to be easy to evaluate this.
So I'm going to choose x equals e, so the
log of e will just be equal to one.
So at log of one was zero, log of e is
one.
So that'll mean that I can figure out
easily
what the value on the left hand side is.
And let's see if we get the same thing
using the integral
form of the Taylor approximation error.
So the definition here, I have my limits
are going
to be a to x, so that's one up to x.
X minus t to the first power over one
factorial times f.
So, first derivative take the derivative
of that again, so f double prime.
And then I'm going to integrate that with
respect to t.
So I said I want to find the Taylor
approximation error at the point x
equals e, so the first thing I'm going to
do is just replace the x's in this.
With e's.
And now t is my variable of integration.
So hopefully it should be pretty easy to
see that this is just going to be so
I have minus t times negative one over t.
That just becomes one over t.
Then I have e.
times minus one over t squared, so that
gives me minus e over t squared.
That gives me log of t plus e over t,
evaluated at e and one.
And then on the left hand side the, it's
pretty easy to figure out what this is.
So I just end up with log of e.
Minus e plus one, so log of e was one.
So I get one plus one is two and then I
still have this minus e, so I get two
minus e.
And on the right hand side I evaluate my
integrand at
the upper limit and subtract it, evaluate
it at the lower limit.
And so I end up with log of e which is
one, plus e
over e which is another one minus log of
one which is zero plus e.
So this is going to be two and this is
going to be e.
So I get two minus e as the approximation
error on both sides.
Yeah?
>> Why are you integrating from one to
x?
Where did that one come from?
>> So that domain of integration is a to
x.
And so I did my expansion around the point
a equals one.
So I guess maybe up here I should have put
an a.
And then when I replace these with the
actual values it would be one to e.
Because I'm, I've built an extension at
the point a.
And I'm trying to evaluate how good that
is at the point e.
So now let's see if we can figure out the
same thing using the derivative form of
the Taylor approximation here.
I guess one thing I wanted to point out,
let's just remember that the approximation
error was about 0.7.
[COUGH]
So I want to know what is the Taylor
approximation error again at the point x
equals e.
So I built a Taylor polynomial around at
the point a equals one and
then I want to see how well that
approximates f at the point x equals e.
So this is my formula for the derivative
form of the Taylor approximation error.
And again f double prime here is going to
be one over x for
the first derivative and then minus one
over x squared for the second derivative.
So I get this minus and then I'm
evaluating it
at c, so this is where the c squared came
from.
I have a two factorial, that's where this
two came from.
And then I'm interested in the point x
equals e, so I'm going to replace
the x with an e, so I get e minus one
squared in the numerator.
And now, because I happen to know what the
true value of the Taylor
approximation error is on the left hand
side, I can solve for this point c.
And so what I get is that c is equal to
1.434 roughly so the,
these are probably irrational numbers, so
they go on forever.
But I've just rounded them to rounded them
to three decimal places.
E is definitely an irrational number.
So it has an infinite decimal
representation.
[COUGH]
And so I found that c is in fact in
between.
So a was equal to one.
And then x was equal to e.
So I found that the value c is in that
interval.
[COUGH]
But I had to know what the Taylor
approximation error was
in order to be able to find that value of
c.
So you might ask how is that useful?
[COUGH]
And so what we are actually able to do
with this, is we can't find with the
derivative form
the exact value of the Taylor
approximation error but
you can find a bound on the Taylor
approximation error.
So I know that the true approximation
error
is going to, for this particular example
so normally this
would either be ax or xa depending on
whether
x is greater than a or less than a.
But in this example I know my a is
equal to one and my x is equal to e.
So I know there's some point c
in between one and e where the true
approximation error is going to occur.
And then what I want to do.
Is say well that, the absolute value of
the error then must be less than or
equal to the maximum value this function
takes on the interval one e.
And so that's going to say well I, I
don't know exactly what the Taylor
approximation error is.
But I can tell you that it's definitely
less than whatever
value I'm going to calculate on the right
hand side here.
And so in this case if I, if I take the
absolute value of the expression I
had on the previous slide, I end up with
e minus one squared divided by two c
squared.
And now I want to find the value of c
that's going to make this the biggest.
And so it turns out this is, if I put in,
so since I'm dividing by
c, if I want to make this thing big I
want to make c as small as I can.
But c has to be in this interval one e, so
the
smallest I can make c and still stay in
that interval is one.
So that tells me that the absolute value
of
this Taylor approximation error is less
than or equal
to one half e minus one squared and that's
equal to about 1.476.
So my bound on the error is roughly twice
what the actual error is.
because if you remember from the integral
form we were able to
find it exactly and it was about 0.7
something, the absolute value was.
And so the idea here is?
If this is not good enough.
So if I want my approximation to be better
than within 1.476 of the true value,
then I need to use a more complicated
polynomial to make my approximation.
But I also need to know that polynomial
is actually getting closer as I add more
terms.
And so this lets me put a bound on the
Taylor approximation error.
So this is the Taylor approximation error
using a
first order Taylor polynomial expanded
around the point a.
And this is the error at the point x
equals e.
And I know that I'm within 1.47 of the
true value.