Welcome to Week 3 of the AI planning
course. In week one we've already seen in
informal introduction to the planning
problem we're trying to address in this
course. And we've seen some of the context
in which planning takes place. In Week 2
then, we've seen two main things. We've
seen search algorithms, and we've seen the
Strips Planner. For search algorithms, we
first talked about heuristics, and how
they encode knowledge that helps us guide
the search. And then, we've used this
knowledge in the a-star algorithm for
graph search. Finally we've talked about
how to find good heuristics, as good
heuristics are vital for the performance
of A star algorithm. Then we've moved over
to the Strips system. The Strips system
gave us the Strips' representation which
describes operators as consisting of
preconditions and effects and the effects
are often divided into an add and a delete
list. Then we've had a formal definition
of the planning problem we are trying to
solve in this course. And we've seen some
algorithms that we can use to solve this,
this problem. The first algorithm we've
seen is forward state space search. And
then we've described a variant of that,
which is backwards states space search.
Both searching the same state space. In
addition to all this technical material,
we've shown you some features. In Week 1,
we had a feature on planning for robots.
And in week 2, we've seen a feature by
Nils Nilson on the X star algorithm and
the Strips system they developed at SRI.
And this week, we'll have another feature,
and I hope you will enjoy this. So far in
our search for solutions to planning
problems, we have considered plans that
were sequences of actions. They may not
have achieved the goals, but they were
plans in their own right. In the first
half of the this week we're going to, to
look at a different search space that
consists of partial plans. Partial plans
still consists of the same types of
actions we've seen previously like the
move action here or this move action or
the load act ion so they're the same
actions. What is new is that we explicitly
record the rationale of why we have an
action in a plan. For example here, we see
that we have an effect of this action, and
we're using this to achieve the
precondition of another action and we've
introduced this link here. To record this
fact. Also we have explicit ordering
constraints, something you see here and
here, that tells us in which order we have
to execute the actions. That makes it
possible for us to have partial plans that
include a partial order, so actions can be
in paraelle. Finally, partial plans may
not have fully instantiated actions. Some
of the actions may contain variables. That
is something I've already mentioned during
lifted backward search, that is possible
and impartial order planning that is
usually done. The first planner that
implemented this algorithm was the UCPOP
planner in the early 1990s. And we will
see the pseudo-code for this planning
algorithm later in this segment. In the
2nd half of this week we're going to do
something completely different, namely,
we're going to change the planning problem
that we are trying to solve. So far, our
planning problem consisted of, amongst
other things, A goal which defines a set
of goal states. In the new type of
planning we're going to look at here.
We're not trying to achieve goals. But
we're trying to accomplish tasks. Tasks
can be seen as high level disruptions of
activity that we want to execute. But they
are so high level that we don't know how
to directly do them. So the approach we're
taking, usually, is to break them down
into smaller tasks. And we do this until
we reach a level where tasks are so small
that we have an operator in our planning
domain, that directly accomplishes this
task. For example, the first sub-task
here, that we have in this decomposition
tree, that decomposes our overall tasks
into smaller tasks, would be to take
something with a crane excetera. And we've
already seen that our planning domains
contain Operators that can directly
accomplish these so called primitive
tasks. And that is the approach we take in
hierarchical task network planning, or
short HTN. A lot of practical planning
systems take this approach as you've
already heard my colleague, Austin Tate,
tell you in week 1. We will look at a
slightly simplified version of this
problem called STN planning. This will be
described in detail, but then I'll
describe what is different about HTN
planning. And hopefully you will
understand that the power of HTN planning
largely comes from the fact that it
handles constraints on world states
explicitly. And since there are many
different types of constraints that can be
handled. HTN planners can be adapted to
specific applications. So, now, before we
start with the technical material for week
3. I want to, again, remind you of the
social platform that comes with this
course. There is the discussion forum,
which you can use to post questions and
get help. And there's also the Course Wiki
that you can use to collect useful
information. Please make good use of them.