So far I've talked about STN which stands
for simple task network.
The more general approach is known as
hierarchical type planning and that's
what we'll be looking at next.
HTN planning is more general than STN
planning, but that also means there isn't
a single algorithm that implements HTN
planning.
So I can't show you any pseudo-code here.
Instead, I will just give you an overview
of the general approach.
In STN planning, as I have just described
it.
There were 2 types of constraints that
were part of the representation and the
procedure.
The first type of constraint we've seen
are the ordering constraints.
And if you remember the definition of a
task network, consisting of nodes and
edges.
These edges represented the ordering
constraints.
So.
They were built into the representation
of a task network.
This means there was exactly one way in
which ordering constraints between tasks
could be handled.
The other type of constraints we've seen
are the preconditions.
Preconditions are constraints on the
state before a method or an action is
applied.
And what we have done in STN planning is
that we have written it in to a planning
procedure that preconditions must hold.
So preconditions were enforced by the
procedure.
And to be able to enforce preconditions
the planning procedure have to rely on
knowledge of the state before a method or
an action is applied.So you must know
what exactly that state is to be able to
test for applicability.
And that means we must perform forward
search, because of the way we represented
preconditions are part of methods in our
Approach.
In HTN planning, we try to take a more
general approach.
HTN planning does not deal with a
specific type of ordering constraints, or
of specific representation for
preconditions.
But maintains general constrains
explicitly as part of the representation.
So of course this will require additional
bookkeeping, but it means we are much
more flexible.
If we want to have a different type for
ordering our network, then we can plug a
different constraint management system
into our HTN planner.
Similarly for other types of constraints
we want to handle, they can be included
in our representation as part of a
general constraint network having
different types of constraints.
Although I won't go into as much detail
as before, I at least wanted to give you
a flavor of HTN methods look like by
presenting you with a formal definition
here.
This will allow you to at least contrast
STN and HTN methods.
So we start off with a set of method
symbols that we use to uniquely name our
methods, just as for STN planning.
Then we say an HTN method is a 4 tuple
consisting of 4 things.
And these 4 things are, firstly, there is
the name of the method.
And that name is.
Just like for STN method, consisting of a
method symbol, and then has a syntactic
expression of the form n of x1 through
xk, where n is a method symbol, and so
element of our set ms.
And x1 through xk are the variables
representing the objects that are
manipulated by this method.
So this is exactly as for STN methods.
And then, also, like for STN methods.
is the task of the method the second
component? This must be a non primitive
task that is accomplished.
By this method.
And then again as for STN methods, we
have a set of sub task, these are the
tasks into which the method breaks down.
So, so far there's nothing new.
What's really new is that we have a set
of constraints associated with an HTN
method and we're not going to be specific
here about what types of constraints
these are.
These can be simple ordering constraints
of the type we seen them or they can be
preconditioned constraints of the type
That we've also had an HTN methods or
there could be more complex things like
we could of time-point network if we want
to do a more elaborate temporal planing
or we could have constraints on the
resources that are consumed by the
different tasks in our method.
The HTN approach is not specific as to
what necessarily must be involved here.
So let's look at an example of an HTN
method.
And again, we'll use an example from our
Dock Worker domain the example we seen
previously as an STN method.
We want to move the top-most container
from one pile to another and this is
again a take action followed by a put
action.
So as I've said before the first three
parts are actually the same as before, so
we have A method name, describing this
method.
Then, we have a task that is accomplished
by this method, and the method name
contains the same variables, representing
the same objects, as before.
Also, the task is the same as before, so
I won't go into this in In detail.
What is new is the network of sub tasks
here, consisting of sub tasks as before,
but what I've also done, is I've given
the sub task names that allow me to refer
to them in the constraints.
So the first sub task is called, t1 here,
that's a local name for the sub task, and
the 2nd one is called T2 other than that
the sub tasks are the same.
But then I add general constraints to
this network to complete this HTN method.
And the first constraint I have is that
T1 must be before T2 so that's an
ordering constraint I have here.
Then I have other constraints
representing the preconditions.
Looking at this example I say here that
before the set T1 so this is a set Of
tasks, there could be more than one here,
we must have the condition that the
container, c, is on top of the origin
pile, true.
So that's a before constraint, applied to
a set of tasks, and a condition, and we
have several other constraints Of this
type here that effectively represent the
pre-conditions of the STN method as we've
seen it previously.
But one thing that is different here is
if you look at this constraint here, here
we don't have a t1 but a t2.
We have the same here for the second
pre-condition.
What this is saying is that these two
conditions must only be True before the
second task in the network, so can, we
can be more specific here, about where we
want preconditions to be true.
And looking at the second one, we only
need the fact that Xd, the destination
container onto which we are putting our
container, needs to be at the top of the
destination pile, before we put it down
there and when you think about it that
makes a lot of sense.
There's no need for this to be the case
before task 1.
But instead, before we put down the
container, we must have this true.
So, this approach of handling constraints
like this can be more explicit as to
where those constraints must be.
True.
But sometimes, a more general approach
can also come with difficulties, and
that's what this 2nd example of HTN
methods illustrates.
This is again taken from our dock worker
robot domain, and this is the example of
moving a stack by repeatedly moving the
top-most container until the stack is
empty.
And again, we have 2 methods that
accomplish this, and these are the
recursive move method we've seen earlier,
from Po to Pd, moving container C from
container Xo, and it accomplishes the
task of moving the stack from Po to Pd.
And it has the following network of
subtasks.
The tasks themselves haven't changed.
So, again, we have, moving the top most
container and then, moving the stack.
We've introduced names for those tasks so
that we confer to them in the
constraints.
the first contsraint is the ordering
constraint and the pre-conditions are
attatched to the first task.
So there's nothing different about this
first HTN method from the STN version we
have seen earlier.
But the second method shown here, move 1,
is very different from no move, what
we've seen earlier in the STN methods.
And the reason for this is that
constrains are always attached to the
tasks in our network.
So If our network consist of no tasks,
then we really can't attach any
constraints to this.
method.
And that is of course what we had in the
no move method.
There were no tasks so in this approach
we couldn't attach any constraints.
What we've got to do to solve this
problem is simply introduce a method that
moves the last container in the network.
And that means we only have one sub-task,
moving the topmost container which is the
last here, and we add constraints to this
sub-task that ensure that this is the
last container.
So it needs to be on top of the pile, but
more importantly The container that we
are trying to move here must be on the
pallet and if it's on the pallet it's the
last container in the stack.
So you can see it's not all that
different from an STN method.
I want to take a step back now, and
compare HTN planning to the STRIPS
planning we've seen previously.
And the first thing I want you to
understand is that HTN planning is far
more expressive than STRIPS planning.
So you can encode problems in HTN that
you can't encode in STRIPS planning.
And this applies to HTN and STN planning
alike.
So I will argue here that this holds for
STN planning.
And since HTN planning is a genealization
of STN planning, it will also hold for
HTN.
Planning.
And the way you can see that STN planning
must be a more powerful approach is by
seeing that STN problems can be
undecidable.
So, thinking back to STRIPS planning,
what we did was we encoded a finite
search space, we had a finite number of
objects, a finite number of predicates.
Which means, we have a finite number of
combinations, how we can build our world
states and we can do a graph search in
the state.
So, it cannot possibly be undecibale
whether there is a plan.
Or there isn't a plan.
STRIPS planning may be hard but it is
decidable.
To see that STN planning is undecidable
requires a little more background.
Ground.
But when you compare the STN formalism,
to programming langueages, you will see
that they are quite similar.
In fact, the basic conststructs you find
in any programming language, are also in
STN planning.
You have branching by having alternative
methods that have different
pre-conditions.
Just think back to the second example
we've just seen.
And we also have methods that accomplish
a given task, but have the same type of
task as a sub-task, so these methods are
effectively recursive.
And with recursion, and branching, we
have the power of a general programming
language.
And that is why STN Planning is so
powerful.
The STN and therefore the HTN formalism
is more expressive than STRIPS planning.
That's what you need to remember here.
But, if you leave out the recursive
aspect from STN Planning so if you have
no methods that are effectively
recursive, then you can translate these
domain into equivalent STRIPS problems
that solve the same problem.
Unfortunately this translation process
may lead to an exponential blow up in the
size of the problem.
As a final point there is also a set of
STN domains called regular STN domains
and that also is equivalent to STRIPS
planning.
Regular STN domains contain some degree
of recursiveness but not much.
So this is the end of this segment about
STN or HTN planning.
I've told you all about tasks and task
networks which were the new nodes in our
search space.
We've seen what methods are.
They refine task networks to give us
state transitions in our search space and
they way they do that is through
Decomposition of tasks in the networks.
Then we've seen the usual definitions of
problems and solutions.
And we have seen how we can do planning
with the TFD and PFD algorithms.
This whole approach can be generalized to
HTN planning, where we explicitly handle
constrains of unknown types.
And although I've just compared HTN and
STRIPS planning.
Keep in mind that these two approaches
really solve two different types of
problem.
The one is goal-based planning, and the
other is task-based planning.
And that concludes this segment.