In the second week of this course, I told
you about heuristic search and the A-star
algorithm.
Then, I showed you how a strips planning
problems can be solved using forward state
space search, which implicitly assumed you
could use the A-star algorithm for this.
But of course, one of the things that
A-star needs is a heuristic that tells us
how far from the goal a current state is.
And that's what we're going to look at in
this segment.
And we're going to start off by some
simple heuristics that can be directly
derived from the planning graph we've just
seen.
Here is a quick recap of one of the things
we've already learned about A-star.
Mainly, that A-star is optimally
efficient.
This means that for a given heuristic
function, no other algorithm is guaranteed
to expand fewer nodes than A-star.
This means that if we are given a
heuristic function and that function is
fixed, we cannot change it.
And we insist on having a minimal length
solution plan.
Then, there cannot be an algorithm better
than A-star that we can use for search.
But there are a few caveats.
For example, the guarantee that A-star
returns a minimal length solution relies
on the fact that the given heuristic is
admissible.
Now, if we don't have a admissible
heuristic, then the guarantee doesn't
exist anymore.
Or if we don't insist on having minimal
length solutions, then we can imagine
algorithms that ignore certain parts of
the search space.
Thereby missing certain solutions, but
still come up with a non-optimal solution.
And, you may remember that I told you,
that A-star still uses exponential memory.
So, depending on the size of our problem,
this algorithm may simply run out of
memory and we need to do something else
then.
So, A-star is not the answer to all
questions, but is a very good algorithm
for performing search.
And, there is one way we can improve the
algorithm, and that is simply by using a
different heuristic function.
If we can find a better heuristic
function, then A-star will perform
significantly better.
And that is what we want to achieve.
Now, when I showed you the planning graph,
I talked a lot about what this graph is
doing namely that it is doing a
reachability analysis for our given goal
from the initial state.
And now, I want to see if we can use this
reachability analysis to derive a
heuristic that we can use during forward
search.
And the reachability analysis performed by
a graph plan and encoded in the planning
graph looks as follows.
We're given a propositional planning
problem and we construct the planning
graph consisting of node and edges for
this problem.
Then, let us assume that our goal consists
of subgoals, g1 through gn here.
And then, the analysis showed us that for
each of these goal components, this goal
component is reachable from the initial
state.
If there's a proposition layer, Pg, such
that the goal component that we're looking
for is an element of this proposition
layer.
Or, we can look at this the other way
around.
Namely, if we look at a proposition layer
Pm, then we can say that if our goal
component that we're looking for is not in
this proposition layer P, then that goal
component can not be reachable in m steps.
If it was reachable in m steps, then there
would be an m step plan that makes that
goal condition true.
And that means that plan would have to be
part of our planning graph and would add
proposition, gk, to our planning graph in
layer Pm.
But we've seen it is not in that layer, so
there can't plan with m steps.
So, this gives us an idea how we can
define a heuristic for our goal component
gk and that's the heuristic that we find
here.
It's m and this m, what that is, is the
first layer, first layer Pm, such that our
goal component, gk, is in that layer.
Note that we have to choose the first such
layer here.
So, we know that in Pm minus 1 gk is not
contained so it cannot be reachable.
But in Pm, it is contained.
So, in theory, it may be possible to reach
the goal condition, gk, in m steps.
So, we can use that as a heuristic.
And because this is minimal, because we've
used the first layer, it is actually an
admissible heuristic for this goal
condition.
Of course, this only works for a single
goal condition, not a conjunction of
goals.
And we've already seen that in the
planning graph, we can select multiple
actions from one layer.
So, m often underestimates the number of
required actions quite significantly.
But, it is the best heuristic we've seen
so far.
And, here is our familiar planning graph
example, that we've used a couple of time
now to illustrate this concept of using
the planning graph to compute a heuristic.
Remember, the original goal that we were
looking at was to swap the 2 containers,
so we went to container a at location 2
and container b at location 1.
So there's two goal components to this
overall goal, and we can compute the
heuristic function we've just looked at by
looking at the planning graph, and seeing
where those two goals first appear.
And if we look at a2, it's already circled
in red here.
Because at first, that appears in
proposition layer P3 and we can look at
this as not in this layer, not in this
layer P2 and it appears here for the first
time and similarly b1 appears here for the
first time.
So, what we have is that the heuristic we
have just defined.
4a2 is 3, because it takes at least three
actions to make that proposition true and
we know that from looking at the planning
graph.
And the same applies for b1.
It takes at least three actions to make
this proposition true.
But note that we have said nothing about
which actions these are, so these actions
will be from the three action layers.
But for all we know, they might be the
same three actions for both goals.
So, that is a problem.
How do we combine these two values into a
single heuristic for a composite goal?
So, the question is, how do we combine the
information gained from the planning graph
as a heuristic for individual goal
conditions when we have multiple goal
conditions?
So, we are given a planning problem, but
our goal consists of more than one goal.
G1 through gn, and we need to combine the
heuristic values for the individual goals
into an overall heuristic value.
And there are two obvious ways in which
this can be done.
The first option is we simply take the
maximum.
So, this option assumes that the actions
that we need to achieve all the goals
overlap significantly.
And therefore, taking the maximum will
tell us how long it will take, in the
worst case, to achieve all the goals.
The advantage of this approach is that the
heuristic is still admissible.
So, it was admissible for each individual
goal.
But now, taking the maximum gives us an
admissible heuristic for all the goals.
In practice, it turns out that this
heuristic is very inaccurate, and the
problem comes when we have independent
goals.
For independent goals, the actions we need
to achieve these goals often don't overlap
much, in which case, this heuristic badly
underestimates what it takes to get to the
goal.
The second obvious option, instead of
taking the maximum, would be simply to add
all the values for the individual goal and
combine them in this way.
So, the first drawback of this is that
this approach gives us no longer an
admissible heuristic.
This may well over estimate the distance
to the goal because there are shared
actions and they often are.
And if we don't take this into account, we
count these actions multiple times when we
compute our heuristic.
And that means, this heuristic becomes
quite inaccurate for dependent goals.
Now you could ask, are dependent goals
very realistic?
And in many domains, unfortunately, they
are.
Think back to what relations we've defined
for the dockworker robot domain.
There's the at relation that tells us
where a robot is, and there's the occupied
predicate that tells us whether a location
is occupied or not.
These two are always dependent.
If they both appear in a goal, then just
adding the values to achieve the two
doubles the amount of effort that we
estimate.
But at least we now have two heuristics we
can now use to apply a start to forward
state space search.
And one thing to note about for both of
these heuristics, which is quite
interesting, is they're based on the
planning graph but neither of those really
requires the computation of the mutex
relations.
So, we could use them in a planning graph
with or without mutex relations, meaning
we actually have four different heuristics
already.