Planning usually occurs in a human
context where tasks or objectives are
assigned, where plan execution must take
place.
We introduced earlier a model for
planning and showed some simplifications
to it.
We explained that a richer model is
needed for realistic planning in dynamic
situations.
In such a context, we've got to observe
the performance of activity in the world,
and try to observe and interpret the
effects of our executed activities there.
This can allow for possible plan revision
and replanning where that's necessary.
O-Plan for example, could be configured
with three separate planning agents.
Which represented reasons about plans at
different levels.
The first was concerned with the human
level of task description, setting
objectives, giving guidance, or overall
constraints.
A second level is a more technical
planning level which could propose
options to meet the state's objectives,
and allow for choices between those
options.
And a third level supported plan
execution and monitoring.
And could facilitate local planned repair
where that was feasible.
However, note that in each case here,
each agent has a similar structure which
is supported by the open planning
architecture, in which the O-Plan planner
was built.
For example, the multi-agent planning
architecture platform is the basis for
the SRI International Side Planner.
The Open Planning Architecture is the
basis for O-Plan designed to handle
multiple plan roles and levels as you
just seen.
And the I-X platform is intended to port
multiple types of command, sense-making,
analysis in planning for instances to
build the I-plan · planner, as well as
decision making, execution, and
communication between agents even in
mixed agent frameworks.
Several practical AI planning systems
have been used in emergency response
applications.
Often working in the context of a wide
range of other agents and services.
They're often in an environment where
communication and collaboration is taking
place with some sort of infrastructural
layer.
And then the core might concer, be
concerned with command and control-type
issues in search-and-rescue or emergency
response situations, but also dealing
with people in the field.
And so they are also manipulated the
plans that they're given and adjusting
them to a local situation.
We may also be including the people who
are in trouble or are isolated or being
rescued as part of the framework of
collaboration and communication that's
taken place.
And again, they have to deal with
elements of the plan that are coming from
these different levels and different
centers.
And we perhaps have to deal upwards with
decision making authorities by giving
briefings of the options that we're
generating, explaining those, and looking
for decisions on, on which ones are going
to be executed and handled.
We'll show you a couple of examples of
I-X multiagent applications.
This is an I-X process panel which sports
a search and rescue coordinator and the
communications with various other
agencies and services in a coalition
peace keeping operations.
The second application called iGlobe
handles the tasking and coordination of
mobile ground and air vehicles in a
disaster response scenario.
Often, planning is just a small part of a
wider collaboration and communication
situation involved in a realistic
application.
The I-plan planner here sits in the lower
right, and it's quite a simple tool.
But it operates in a much broader context
of planned communication, messaging, map
views, sense making, and so on.
A paper written in 2001, was part of a
special issue in Mayhem Magazine on
Robocop, explored emergency response as a
grand challenge for multiagent and
intelligent systems.
It explored the very many areas involved
in effective emergency response, which
could be supported by intelligence
systems.
These included dealing with the
environment.
Supporting the people and organizations
involved, and of course, using
intelligence systems to assist in the
emergency itself.
The key element of this support in both
planning and activity management and the
sharing of plan related information
between agents.
Plenty used for communication and
collaboration between agents and systems.
So upon representation itself, is an
important area of research.
Plenty used in many areas beyond activity
planning.
Such as in, situation understanding
summarization, natural language
interpretation, and generation and so on.
Plents provide nontological informal
representation call for a wide range of
practical applications and uses.
A good representation of plans can be
used as a target for knowledge
acquisition, for user communication, for
system manipulation, and as a basis for
formal analysis.
AI planning work has influenced standard
related process and plan representations
used by many industries and fields.
For example, in the MIT process handbook,
its process interchange format or PIF.
In the NIST, The National Institute of
Standards and Technology in America.
the Process Specification Language, PSL.
And the DARPA, Shared Planning and
Activity Representation SPAR.
And has even become the basis for an ISO
standard.