>> You have now seen the basic planning
graph, the nodes and the edges that make
up this graph, and you have seen how it
can be understood as a reachability
analysis.
The planning graph is a layered graph
consisting of proposition and action
layers.
When we search for a plan in this graph,
what we will get as a result is a layered
plan and we will look at those next in a
little more detail.
In layered plans, we will have multiple
actions, that come from the same action
layer.
Which means we will effectively try to
execute these actions in parallel.
Now, we've already seen that this may
cause problems.
But this will not be the case, if all
these actions are independent.
And here's an example of what independence
of actions means.
Looking at the two actions in this action
layer a2 here.
We have the actions of moving the robot r,
from location 1 to location 2.
And we also have the action of loading
container a, onto the robot r at location
1.
And what we see here is that m r one two,
has a negative effect r one.
So it deletes the fact that the robot is
at location one.
But if we look at the other action, l a r
one.
That has a precondition r one.
So what this means is, 1 action deletes a
pre-condition of the other action, which
means these 2 actions cannot be executed
in parallel.
These 2 actions are dependent.
Similarly, if we look at this action
again, and now as another action MR21, so
1 is moving the robot from location 1 to 2
and the other 1 is moving the same robot
from 2 to 1.
What we see here is that the first action
Mr12, has a positive effect Lar1..
Whereas, for the second action, this is
actually a negative effect.
So one action is trying to assert the
effect r1 that the robot is in location
one.
And the other is trying to delete the same
fact.
Again, this means these two actions cannot
occur together, they are dependent
actions.
But to show you that not all actions in
this action layer are dependent, let us
look at Mr12 and Mq21, for example.
These two actions are independent.
There a fact and pre-conditions don't
interfere with each other so we can
execute those two action together and in
parallel.
And here is a general definition for what
it means for two actions to be
independent.
We can say that two actions a1 and a2 are
independent if the following conditions
hold and what these conditions express is
very simply.
They say that the effects and
preconditions of those actions must not
interfere.
And that's exactly defined the way that
we've seen just in the example.
So we've seen that the negative effects of
one action may interfere with the
preconditions of the other.
So we have the negative effects of A1
intersected with the preconditions of the
other.
And that must be the empty set.
And the same goes for the positive
effects.
So, we have the negative effects
intersected with the positive effects.
That, again, must be the empty set.
Or, in other words, the negative effects
of the first action must not be a
precondition, or a positive effect of the
other.
Action.
And the first condition states this for
the negative effects of a 1.
And the second one is, is simply the
symmetric case for the negative effects of
a 2.
Which must not be preconditions of a 1 or
positive effects of a 1.
That's what it means for two actions to be
independent.
And we can easily generalize this
definition to a set of actions pi.
We can say that a set of actions pi is
independent if every pair of actions in
this set is independent.
So we must not have a single pair of
actions that are dependent In the set,
then the whole set consists of independent
actions.
And one important thing here you can see
in this definition is that the
independence of actions does not depend on
the planning problem.
Which means this can be computed before we
start our planner, before we search for a
solution to our problem.
And also you can see quite easily that the
independence relation that holds between
actions is symmetric, because in the
definition we've seen that these two cases
for A1 and A2 are symmetric.
And here is the definition we've just
seen, expressed as an algorithm in pseudo
code.
We define a function, independent, that
takes two action, and returns true, if and
only if these two actions are indepenetns.
And what this function does is simply go
through all the negative effects of the
first action and test whether they're also
either a pre-condition or a positive
effect of the second action.
If this is the case, then we can return
false because we know these two actions
are not independent.
They are dependent in this case.
And then we also need to do the same for
the symmetric case so we To all the
negative effects of the second action and
test wether they are a precondition of the
first action or the positive effect of the
first action.
Again if this is the case we can return
false the two actions are dependent.
If this is not the case but if we go
through both of these loops and don't
return as false then we must have a case
where both of the actions are independent
and we can return true.
In terms of time complexity, you can
easily see that this algorithm has
ponilumial/g time complexity.
In fact, it's linear in the number of
preconditions and effects that an action
might have.
So if the number of preconditions and
effects an action might have is b, this
algorithm runs in o of b.
B.
This assumes that these elements tests
here in the algorithm can be done in
constant time.
And I've already told you, since action
independence is independent from a given
planning problem, this can be all
precomputed.
And I'll leave it up to you to work out
how much storage this will actually take
in computer memory.
Now that we've seen what it means for a
set of actions to be independent, we can
talk about the application of a set of
independent actions in the given state and
this is quite straight forward.
So we can say that a set of independent
actions is applicable in a state s if the
following holds namely the union of all
the preconditions over all the actions.
Must be propositions in our state s.
It should be obvious that if each of the
actions has its precondition set aside in
this state s, then this individual action
will be applicable.
And if this is true for all the actions'
preconditions, then all the actions are
applicable.
And then the result of applying a set of
independent actions so this is our set pi
here, independent actions is defined as
follows.
We extend the definition of our state
transition function gamma to now take A
state s and a set of independent actions
pi.
And the result will simply be all the
propositions that are true in s minus the
negative effects of the set pi plus the
positive effects of the set.
.
And when we talk about the preconditions
if positive effects or negative effects of
a set of independent actions , we simply
mean the union over all the actions in
that set preconditions positive effect or
negative effect.
So this defines applicability and state
transitions for sets of independent
actions.
Going back to what I said earlier, what we
will be looking for is sets of independent
actions in action layers in our planning
graph.
And when we want to turn this into a
sequential plan, we need to be sure that
we can do that and this is what this
proposition gives us.
If we are given a set Pi of independent
actions that are applicable in a state s
then we can take any permutation of those
actions, a 1 through a K, so those are the
actions in pi, and this is a permutation,
any sequential order.
Of those actions, and the following will
be true.
This sequence of actions a one through a k
will be applicable in our state s.
And the state that we get to when we apply
our set of independent actions.
This is the extended defintion of the
state transition function that we've just
introduced in the previous slide, will be
the same state As the one we get when we
take the state S and apply the sequence of
actions A 1 through A K.
And remember, this does not depend on
which sequence we've chosen.
So we can take any permutation and the
resulting state will always be the same as
when we apply the set of independent
actions.
That simply means we can forget about the
execution order of independent actions
because we can take any order we like.
Now, we can define what we mean by a
layered plan, which is the type of plan
we'll be looking for in our planning
graph.
So, suppose we are given a planning
problem consisting of a set of actions.
An initial state and a goal.
The set of actions here is the set of
propositional actions and we're dealing
with a propositional planning problem.
Then we have a planning graph consisting
of nodes and edges where the nodes are
given by the first proposition layer, the
first action layer and so on.
One, always alternating action and
proposition layers, as we've seen it
earlier.
Then we can define what we mean by a
layered plan over this graph, and we
define it as a sequence of sets of
actions.
Denoted here by this big symbol pi.
And this is the sequence of actions, pi 1
through pi k and for each of these sets,
we must have the following conditions
true.
So the i set in the sequence, pi i, must
be a subset of the actions in the[UNKNOWN]
action layer of the planning graph so that
will be for a 1 this will be this one
here.
For a2, this 1 here, an so on.
So pi i must be a subset of the actions in
that action layer.
Which are, of course, a subset of all the
actions that are available.
Then, this set, pi i, must also be
applicable in the state represented by pi
minus 1.
That is the proposition layer preceding
the action layer we're just looking at.
Note that this is not necessarily a
consistent state.
And then, of course, we want all our
actions in pi i to be independent.
So the main thing here is that our layered
plan is a sequence of sets of independent
actions, where each of these sets must be
from the corresponding action layer.
Now that we know what a layered plan is,
it's fairly straightforward to define what
it means for a layered plan to be a
solution to a given planning problem.
So we have a layered plan consisting of
sets pi 1 through pi k of independent
actions chosen from our planning graph.
And we have a planning problem given by
the set of actions a initial state and
goal.
Then, this sequence of sets of actions is
a solution for this planning problem if
the following conditions hold.
Firstly, our first set, pi 1, must be
applicable in our initial state.
Then for every subsequent set pi j, so j
must be greater than one.
This must be applicable in the state that
we get from first applying pi 1 in the
initial state, then applying.
And pie 2 in the state that results from
this, and then applying the next set of
fractions, and so on up to pie j minus 1.
Applied in the state that we get when we
apply these other sets before that.
And in this state Pi J must be applicable.
And the third and final condition is
simply if we look at the state that we get
from applying all those sets of actions
and sequence.
So starting from Pi 1 then Pi 2 and so on
until we get to the last set Pi k, we get
a state and in this state all the goal
propositions must be in this state.
So that is what a layered solution plan is
and that's the kind of plan we'll be
looking for in our planning graph.