We have now seen how planning problems
can be formulated as search problems.
And we have also seen a basic algorithm
that can be used to solve search
problems.
We have also already seen some examples
of search problems such as the
missionaries and cannibals problem.
Now we shall look at some more example
problems.
The first problem we will look at is a
toy problem.
And it's a problem that has been around
for a long time.
The sliding tile puzzle or sliding block
puzzle looks essentially like this.
What we have is a grid.
Here, it's a three by three grid.
And in this grid, we have eight tiles.
That is, one square remains empty.
We can then shift the tiles in the grid.
But, of course, we can only shift them
into the empty slot.
Leaving another slot empty as a result.
The tiles themselves are numbered one
through eight, and our task is to bring
them into the right order, and the right
order is showing here on the right, and
this could be some initial state from
which we start.
So to formulate this as a search problem,
we have to ask, what is the initial
state?
And the initial state for this problem
could be any configuration of the tiles.
So not just this one here shown on the
left, but really any configuration you
can think of.
The goal state is usually fixed depending
on where you look there are different
varieties of what the goal state should
be like.
This is just one possible state that you
see on the right where the tiles are in
the correct order.
Sometimes, you'll see the middle square
should be empty, sometimes it's another
square that should be empty.
But there's usually one fixed goal state
that much be reached in this puzzle.
The actions that are possible, and I've
already told you this.
Are to move, a tile that is next to the
empty space into the empty space.
So I could either move the eight here or
the four up.
Or the six into the empty space.
In this case, for this puzzle there would
be three possible actions in this state.
For the path cost, we simply assume that
moving a tile has a unit cost, so all
actions have equal cost.
So, that's it.
That's the definition of the eight
puzzle.
There are also larger versions of this
puzzle on a four by four grid, with
fifteen tiles, known as the fifteen
puzzle.
Or on a five by five grid with 24 tiles,
known as the 24 puzzle, and so on.
The next problem is also a toy problem.
And it's known as the N queens problem in
general, but we will look at the eight
queens problem here.
And the problem, is to find a
configuration for eight queens on an
eight by eight chess board, such that
none of the queens attacks any of the
others.
For those of you who don't know chess, a
queen is simply a chess piece that can be
somewhere on the board.
And it can move along any diagonal, any
column, or any row.
So, if we look, for example, at this
queen here.
It can move anywhere along this diagonal,
or this diagonal.
Or it can move anywhere in its row, or
anywhere in this column.
So you can see, this queen attacks none
of the other queens, and is attacked by
none of the other queens.
If we look at this queen, however,
we can see that if we move all the way
along the diagonal.
This queen is attacked by this queen.
So this configuration shown here is not a
solution to the problem.
Now you may wonder how this can be seen
as a planning problem because what we're
looking for is a configuration, so a
static state.
And the answer is that we can look at
this as a problem of reasoning about
action.
When we look at this here, it says we
have to place the queens on the chess
board.
And we place the queens, one after
another.
So the initial state is the empty chess
board.
The actions we have available are placing
queens onto the board.
And the goal state is any state where the
queens don't attack each other.
Again we can assume a unit cost for the
actions, so all actions are equally
expensive.
And I'll give you a hint how this can be
formulated a little more efficiently
because, if we allow a queen to be placed
on any board position, we have 64
different positions.
And this would create a pretty big search
tree.
So what we can do is we say that the
first action can only place a queen in
the first column.
So we can only place a queen here.
The second action in our plan must place
a queen in the second column.
And so on.
So our plan will definitely be eight
steps long and we only have eight
possibilities for each step in the plan.
So this defines the N queen's problem as
a general search problem, or as a
planning problem.
The next problem is more like a real
world problem, and it is the dockworker
robots problem that is also used in the
book this, course is based on, so you
will see this problem occur again and
again.
The aim with this problem is to have one
example that we can use to illustrate
many of the techniques and algorithms
that will be introduced in this course.
The advantage of this problem is that it
is not trivial to solve, but it also can
be described fairly quickly.
the informal description of this problem
is this, we have a harbor in which we
have several locations which may be docks
or other places.
at these docks there may be ships, and we
have storage areas for containers that
need to be moved around at the docks or
loaded onto ships.
We also have parking areas for trucks
that can carry containers.
And they will be robots, in our cases, or
trains that arrive with the containers.
There will also be cranes to move the
different containers around.
They can load containers on to ships or
robots or they can unload them from ships
and robots.
And what we will be interested in is
generating plans for the cranes and the
robots that achieve certain configuration
of containers that we give as goal
states.
Now there are some people who say that
block stacking or container stacking,
which is essentially the same thing, is
not a real-world problem.
So this is why I've included this picture
here, so this proves that it is a
real-world problem.
Now let's look at the state of the world
in the dock worker robot example.
What we have in each state are locations
and in this example there are two
locations L1 and L2 and these locations
are connected by paths along which the
robot for example can move.
So these two locations are adjacent
because they are connected by a path.
At each location we have cranes which can
be used to move the containers around.
They can move the containers between the
different piles that are available.
And here at this location L2, we see
there are two piles, P2 and Q2.
In this case they are both empty.
There's no containers on these piles.
But at the bottom of every pile we will
always have a pallet onto which we can
stack the container.
So the pallet tells us where the bottom
of the pile is.
A pile itself is an abstract object.
It doesn't necessarily need to have
anything in it.
An empty pile isn't really something we
can touch.
But it can have containers in it.
And containers are, of course, what we
have the most of in most states.
So here in this example, we have six
different containers.
They're called CA, CB, CC, CD, CE, and
CF.
And they can be stacked on top of each
other in a pile, as I've already
explained.
There's no limit to how high a pile can
be, despite the fact that it looks in
this picture like the crane can only
reach so high, but we will consider
arbitrarily high stacks of containers.
Finally, what we have in these states are
robots.
This is one robot here, though so there's
only one robot.
That is an object that can be loaded with
a container by the crane.
And then once it has a container on it,
it can move to a different location.
It, of course, can also move, when it's
empty, to a different location.
But there can only be one container on a
robot at one time.
Also, at each location, we can only have
one robot at a time.
We consider a location occupied when a
robot is there.
So, I think that's pretty much all you
need to know about the world states and
the dock worker robot example.
But just to clarify this, not all states
will have two locations, and six
containers, and one robot.
We will consider a different world with
many different numbers of robots,
containers, or locations and cranes and
they will give us more complexity to the
problem.
You can probably guess what the different
action types in this domain are, but here
they are just to make sure that we are
all on the same page and understand what
they are.
The first action.
Is the move action and the move action
moves a robot, that's the first argument
in this action, from one location, the
second argument, to some adjacent and
unoccupied other location, L prime.
So as result of this action, the robot
will be now in a different location.
That other location must be unoccupied
and it must be adjacent, which means
there must be a path that connects the
two locations, L and L prime.
That was the only action that is to be
done by the robot.
The other actions are all done by the
crane.
So, the first one of those actions is to
take action and we can take a container
C, with an empty crane K, from the top of
a pile.
And they must all be located at the same
location L.
So this action as a result will have the
crane holding the container and all these
objects must have been at the same
location obviously.
The river's action is to put down the
container C that is held by the crane on
top of a pile.
And they must again all be located at the
same location L.
Two more actions, again, both to be done
by the crane.
The one is loading a container.
But this will involve a robot, too.
So what we do is we load a container C,
that is held by the crane K onto an
unloaded robot R.
So the robot must not already have a
container on it.
And, again, this must all be at the same
location.
And the reverse action is to unload the
container from.
The robot.
That's the robot.
And, again, the crane must be empty so
that we can do this, and all of the
objects must be at the same location.
So, these are the five action types that
are available in the doc worker robot
domain.
Notice that I said action types, because
there can be many instances of these
actions, depending on how I instantiate
these parameters.
So if there's only one robot, then this
robot may be the only one that can move,
but it can move between different
locations, and these are all different
actions.
We will specify all this more formally
when we have introduced an action
description language, and that will be
next week.
And here is a very simple example of what
the state transition system that
corresponds to the dark work or robot
problem could look like.
You can see this is a very simple
problem, because a large state space
wouldn't fit onto one slide, so I had to
reduce everything to one robot, one
crane, one container, and two locations,
which gives us six possible world states,
and they're named here S0, S1, S2, S3,
and so on,
S4, S5.
The objects you see in these states are
exactly the things I have just talked
about.
So we have a robot here.
We have a crane.
And we have a container, a palette, and
the two locations I just talked about.
And the actions are in principals.
Also, those I've just mentioned.
And they give us the state transitions.
And we've labeled them here, the state
transitions.
So the take action gets us from state s
zero to state s1.
And so on, put action would get us back
to that state, we have move one action
which moves the robot to location one and
we have a move two action which moves the
robot to location two.
As you can see from the state
transitions, the system is static.
Which means there are no events
happening.
All the actions are under our control.
Also, the system is deterministic.
Which means, every action leads to
exactly one other state.
So there are no two transitions from one
state that lead to different states given
the same action.
If we do move one in this state, we
always get to this state.
There's no other option.
This is a deterministic state transition
system.
Like I said before you will see a lot
more about the dock worker robot problem
so I will stop here.
So this concludes this first segment of
the course.
And here is a quick summary of what we've
learned so far.
The first question we've looked at
is'What is planning?'.
And more specifically'what is planning in
AI?'.
And the answer we have come up with is
that planning is an explicit deliberation
process that chooses and organizes
actions by anticipating their outcomes.
Planning in AI is the computational study
of this deliberation process.
Next, we have looked at a conceptual
model for planning, which helps us define
the semantics of planning problems.
To this end, we have defined the state
transition system, which consists of four
things.
A set of states, a set of actions, and a
set of events were the first three
components.
And the most complex one is the state
transition function, which maps a given
state and an action or event, to another
set of states.
Then we have looked at the connection
between planning and search.
We have seen that planning problems can
be phrased as search problems.
Search problems can be defined by an
initial state, a set of actions that are
possible in different states, a set of
goal states, and a path cost functions
that tells us how much the individual
actions cost.
And finally, we've seen a number of
example problems that can all be phrased
as search problems.