Topic two, vector spaces and subspaces.
So the space RN, so you'll think of to get started, if I had R1 you can think of that as just a real number lines, so that would be any one real number, or what I've been calling a scalar value R2.
I, I've been using that when I mean points
in the planes, I mean
it's a point in XY plane that I could
write this to say like 1,3.
And in general, you have a space called RN
which is just the space.
That I can get.
So if I have a vector with N components,
then I can describe points in RN.
So the first, just like, so in R2, I need
the first component
to give me the X, the X coordinate.
And I need the second component to give me
the y coordinate.
If it was R3 I'd need the third component
to give me the Z coordinate in RN.
It's gets very difficult to visualize but
you know r or
m can often be medium sized 100s or
thousand or millions.
But everything we're doing still actually
works and sometimes it's actually easier.
Then think about the problem got even
though it's 1 million dimensional space,
to think about this in this column space
rather than in the, the row space.
So RN is generally going to be the whole
space, so that's everything you
can possibly write down, every point you
could possibly write down using n
components.
So R3 would just be what we think of as
space.
So there is no point in space that I
couldn't describe If I knew where
the origin was and I knew what direction x
axis was and the y axis.
Well then just those two then I also know
the
z axis and I could assign any point in
space.
Three numbers that would describe that
point, so
a vector with three components fill up a
space
that we generally would call 3 dimensional
space.
The space R2 is just going to be the x, y
plane.
So once I have an origin.
I can describe any point in the plane by
go, I guess I need an origin and
an x axis and then from that I can
pick the perpendicular direction to get a
y axis.
And once I have those two axis, then I can
describe
any point in the plane just with a single
x coordinate and
a single y coordinate and those would then
be all of the vectors.
I could draw with Putting the tail at 0 0
and the head at that point, x comma y.
In the two essential vector operations go
on inside the vector space so right
now it seems kind of strange because I've
just said, well we have this whole space.
And so every operation that I've already
talked about gives,
you know, if I have a vector of three
elements,
or three components, and I add it to a
vector
of three components, then I get a vector
with three components.
So it means a vector
in 3 dimensional space plus a vector in 3
dimensional
space has an answer that's also in 3
dimensional space.
Can add any two vectors in RN.
What can multiply a vector in RN by a
scalar, And that's
always going to give me a vector back that
is still in RN.
So the result lies in the same vector
space at the thing
that I started out with or the things that
I started at with.
So a subset, or a subspace of a vector
space, is a set of vectors,
so including the zero vector.
So zero vector always has
to be in a subspace.
That satisfy two requirements.
So if U and w are vectors in the subspace,
and C is
any scalar value, then U plus W has to
also be in
the subspace, and C times W has to also be
in the subspace.
And so the way you want to think of this
is
if I was, so we live in three dimensional
space.
But you could have say a piece of graph
paper that you could imagine is the x, y
plane.
And so if you have two vectors that you
draw on your
graph paper.
I'm supposing you are the top of your desk
had z coordinate 0 then those vectors
could also be written with three
components but the z would always be a 0.
So there's still vectors in three
dimensional space.
But if I add anything you can draw on your
graph paper, if I draw
any two graph, or any two vectors on that
sheet of graph paper, the answer.
I'm always
also going to be able to draw on that
piece of graph paper.
So that's, that graph paper you could
think of as a subspace
of three dimensional, so it's a
two dimensional subspace of three
dimensional space.
And so, kind of, there are a few more, so
any line through the
origin, so for instance the x axis would
be a substance of three dimensional space.
Any plane through the origin, so I was
using the
xy plane as my example but you could take
any plane.
I could take this plane and tilt it a bit.
I guess rotating it keeps in in the same
plane.
Tilt it this way, tilt it that way.
As long as it contains the origin, that's
also
going to be a subspace of 3 dimensional
space.
Yeah?
>> What would be a
[UNKNOWN]
example of a subspace
that contains vectors that would not
follow these rules?
[CROSSTALK]
This is how, this is how I'm defining a
subspace, so you can't have a subspace
that doesn't define--
>> So what would be, an example I guess,
of, a region, or I, I guess I can't
imagine a, an area in two
or three dimensions that wouldn't, meet
these requirements.
I guess, sort of the point is, so remember
I'm imagining I'm living
in three-dimensional space, which isn't
really that hard,
because I live in three-dimensiional
space, and I'm thinking of my
piece of graph paper as a sub-space.
And I can make
the vectors in my graph paper vectors of
three components by just
always taking the z to be zero.
So a vector that wouldn't be in that
subspace would be the z axis.
You know if I took the vector 0, 0,
1, that would point directly out of my
graph paper.
So that's, I can't write the z axis as the
sum
of vectors that live in my graph paper
because it would
always, if I made a linear combination it
would always be
something times zero plus something times
zero in the z coordinate.
So that's kind of what you're, you're
decomposing three dimensional
space into the x y plane and the z axis.
That, yeah, the, I, I guess that it's not
something that's easy to visualize, but
what you're after,
>>
[INAUDIBLE]
zero, zero, one, and, or, or something
similar, and does he mention
[INAUDIBLE]
exists in your subspace, or
>> Right and.
>> Maybe I'm missing the point.
The point is that it's a really exhaustive
and specific definition
[UNKNOWN].
>> The, the point is that's the easiest
one is the X Y plain.
But imagine if I tilted the plain.
Now you have points where everything's
still has to live in a plain
but you can have points in that plain that
have X Y and Z all non-zero.
But there's no way.
Because there's no vector in my, in that
subspace perpendicular to the plane.
There's no way for me to get off of the
plane.
So that, that's kind of I need I use the
xy plane because it's an easy example.
But you know what I want is really all
possible planes that could
be you know, they could exist in three
dimensions that contain the origin.
And I, I think really what we're after,
cause that's, that's kind
of is, the highest dimensional thing you
can even really, reasonably understand.
what I'll want to be able to do later on
Is you know these vectors
will be in say like a seven dimensional
subspace of ten dimensional space.
So it's not something you can really
visualize.
but I'm just trying
to give you an idea of what it means you
know.
So you're sort of stuck in the things.
Like, you only need, if you're in a plane,
you only ever need two numbers.
To describe where you are.
If you are in three, like, full,
three-dimensional space, now I need three
numbers.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And so that, that's how it's going to
show up later on.
So, for instance, in in the x-y plane, if
z is always zero, then I only ever need
to know x and y to know where I am in my
subspace.
so being in that subspace is giving me a
constraint that allows
me to get me the first two components of
that vector that
allows me to figure out what the third one
has to be
and so that's the property that is going
to be useful later one.
And also the whole space, so if
I'm talking about Three dimensional space.
All of three dimensional space is also
going to satisfy my definition of a
subspace.
And the zero vector, so this is a
particularly easy one.
There's only one vector in the zero vector
subspace, so
if I add it to itself, I still get zero.
And if I multiply it by any number, I
still get this zero vector.
So that also,
it seems like kind of a strange one to
have, but
it's, a vector that satisfies those two
properties, so it's a subspace.
Okay.
So one subspace It's particularly useful
in statistics
is that column space of a matrix a.
And so this ends up being all of the
linear combinations I can write using the
columns of a.
So, the way I get a linear combination of
columns
of a matrix is I multiply it by a vector.
So this is.
When I, when I want to think
about what are the vectors that live in
the column space of A.
That's every vector I can write as A times
X.
So A is an M by N matrix, that means X has
to be a vector with N components.
[COUGH]
And, it's going to give me a linear
combination then of the columns
of A, and for every vector X that I pick,
I can get
a different output from that, and those
vectors are going to fill
up a space, and that's called the column
space of a matrix A.
Okay, so the, yeah, linear combinations
are things that I can write as ax.
And so remember when we were looking at
solving this problem ax equals b.
Well, this is, according to this
definition of this column space, this is
only going to be solvable if b is in the
column space of a.
So I think in, in the homework, and I also
gave a few quick examples
of, you know, sometimes you're not able to
solve a x equals b.
Or sometimes you end up with an infinite
numbers of solutions.
And so when you're not able to solve ax
equals b,
so you end up getting something like zero
times y equals eight
when you're doing your elimination, that
means that for that particular case,
for that particular a, the b that you are
trying to solve.
in this equation here is not in the
column space of A, so you're not going to
be able to find an answer for that.
So if A is an M by N matrix then the
columns of A have M components.
So the columns live.
In a subspace that they live in the whole
space, r m.
And so the column space has to be a
subspace of r m.
So if a was, if n was equal to m,
that is possible that a can fill up the
whole space.
if there are fewer so for instance if you
just
think of a as being the identity matrix,
and what
the identity matrix really is the first
row or first
column is 1, 0,0 that's a vector that just
points
along the x axis it points 1 in the x
direction, 0
in the y direction, 0 in the x direction
The second column is
zero, one, zero, so that's a vector that
points in the y direction,
and the third one is a vector that points
in the z direction.
And so then when I take A times x, so if I
take i times
x, the reason that's equal to x is it's
just how I would write the,
you know, the point xyz.
In terms of, go so much in the X
direction, so much in the Y
direction, and so much in the Z direction,
it's a linear combination of my coordinate
axes.
If I only had the first two columns, I
could never get in the Z direction.
So, even though my vectors are still
length three, so I'd have
one, zero, zero and zero, one, zero Now,
since I only have
these two vectors, I can't fill up the
whole of the space anymore.
I can only fill up a plane.
I can only get to points in the x-y plane.
And then, just a bit of notation.
So, for some reason, they call the column
space the range
of a matrix, so that the notation is r of
a.
So I think R is going to get used quite
often as a variable or a function here, so
in case when I write it like this, R of a
matrix, I mean the range of the matrix.
And that's the subspace of vectors that I
can write as linear combinations
of the columns of A.
So R stands for range.
Okay.
Then, another space that's, will show up
as being important in statistics is called
the nullspace of a.
And this consists of all of the solutions.
So here I'm looking at solutions x to the
equation a x equals zero.
So remember, I said the zero vector, was,
it's own subspace.
So you always get that one for free.
If I put in
zero for X, then i'm going to get A times
zero
is equal to zero, so zero is always in the
nullspace.
[COUGH]
The nullspace of A is denoted by.
N of A so we had R of A for the column
space and then N of A
for the nullspace and so again remember
when I
was talking about using the identity
matrix as my matrix
A if I took off the third column then
the points I couldn't get to are the
points that
are on the Z axis so that would mean the Z
axis could be the nullspace of that matrix
And the column space would be the xy
plane.
And where you're going to end up with a
nullspace
is if you have a matrix where when you do
elimination.
So for this case I'm going to subtract two
times the first row from the second row.
That's going to give me; 0, 0, 2.
Now I'll subtract three times the first
row from the third
row, and that's also going to give me 0,
0, 2.
So when I look at this
matrix here, there's no pivot for me in
the second column, so
I have to go to the third column to find
the pivot.
And then when I subtract the second row
from the
third row I end up with a row that's all
zeros.
So I end up with pivot only in the first
and third column,.
So I get variables in x1 and x3.
And I, and I'm going to call the variable
x2 a free variable.
And essentially what free variable means
is I can pick that, and then
I can solve for the other two in terms of
whatever I pick there.
So you can think of that as just sort of,
like y equals a function of x.
You have a dependent variable and an
independent variable.
So I can choose any value I want of the
independent variable, but once I've picked
that, I now have a function that gives
me a specific value of the dependent
variable.
And so if I, you know normally what I
expect
to do, what I expect to get when I have
three equations and three unknowns, I
expect to be able
to solve that and get an answer, a single
point.
If I end up with when I, when I've done
eliminations, something like
this, now it's telling me is that I, I
sort of have zero times X2 can be zero.
So that means I can choose any value I
want for X2 and
then I'm going to have, you know, based on
This equation
here I have someway of getting X X1 and X3
from
whatever value I choose for X2, and so I
am going to use that
to, to define kind of 1, 1 last important
property of
a matrix which should be the rank of a
matrix And so the rank
of the matrix is going to be the number of
pivots of that matrix.
And so in this case, since I have, I have
a pivot here
and a pivot here, this matrix that I
started out with has rank two.
If on the other hand, if, if I got the
nice elimitation picture
where have non-zeros down the diagonal,
Then it would be a rank three matrix.
>> What is the null space then?
>> That's a, that, we have to take a
linear algebra class for.
It's, it's not really clear, from this,
exactly what the null space is.
But you can see that it has a, so it,
if you only have x equals 0, as the null
space
That's kind of a trivial null space.
It's sort of like saying anything times
zero is zero.
Here because I have this free variable I
don't have enough pivots.
It means I have a non-trivial null space.
It means I can actually, sorry, I can
actually find non zero vectors,
x, that are going to give, that are going
to satisfy this equation.
Okay, then I think the final concept for
this topic will be
linear independance.
So suppose I have a sequence of vectors,
v 1 up to v n.
And I'm going to call that linearly
independent if and only if the only linear
combination that gives
the zero vector is 0 times v1 plus 0 times
v2, basically 0
times each one of these vectors.
So that's the only way to write the zero
vector.
So that columns of A are independent, so
linearly independent, if
and if the solution to Ax equals 0 is the
zero vector.
So that's just a, another way of stating
the same thing.
So this is the, the vector definition of
linearly independent.
This is sort of the Matrix definition of
And so this is going to be true so that
the columns of A are going to
be linearly independent if when I do
elimination
on A, I don't have any free variables.
So that means I have to end up with a full
set of pivots as I'm doing elimination.
And in that case, the rank a is going to
be equal to
n, so I'm going to get a pivot in every,
in each column.
And if I have a pivot in each column,
there won't be any
free variables, so the null space of a
will contain only the zero vector.
Okay.
And then I'll say a set of vectors spans
a space if their linear combinations fill
that space.
So for instance, if I look at the identity
matrix, so's to
say three by three identity matrix I can
write any point in three-dimensional
space as x times the first column of the
identity matrix plus y
times the second column of the identity
matrix plus z times the third
column of the identity matrix.
So I'll say that the columns of the
identity matrix span the space r3.
So any point in that space.
Can be written as a linear combination of
the vectors that span that space.
And then a basis for a vector space is
going
to be a sequence of vectors so same thing
as this.
They need to be one linearly independent.
And two, they need to span the space.
And so again this is something like my, my
columns of the identity matrix would,
would solve this.
they're linearly independent and they span
the
space and, that's a very trivial example
but that's kind of what you're trying to
say, so it's the columns Of your
matrix, give you a way, so I can write
every point in r3 as some
linear combination of the columns of that
matrix and then the identity matrix is
obviously
just the easiest way to do that, which is
why that's what everybody uses.
Then the dimension of a vector space.
Is going to be the number of vectors in
the basis.
And so since every basis has to have the
same number of
vectors we say it's the, it's the number
of vectors in every basis.
And so again if I'm talking about R three
I need
the columns of the three by three identity
matrix to span that.
That's also going to be a basis for R
three.
And so the dimension is just going to be
the number of vectors which
is the number of columns of the three by
three identity matrix which is three.