Then next topic is going to be something
called Fubini's Theorem.
So first of all, I'd like to say, I just
think, if you have
a name this neat, it's really good that
you attach it to a theorem.
So it's just sort of, for me anyway it's
fun to say.
>>
[LAUGH]
[COUGH]
And so this function, so remember my big
question
at the end of the last set of slides.
If f of x is continuous on the rectangle R
equals a,b cross c,d
so it's just between a and b on the x-axis
and between c and d on the y-axis.
Then Fubini's theorem tells me that the
double integral over that
region over that rectangle is equal to,
and I can do it either
dy dx so I can, it's equal to the value of
iterated integral.
And it doesn't matter which way I do the
iterated integrals
so if I do this dy dx or I do dx dy.
And so remember, we have to be a bit
careful that the ab corresponds
to the dx, so they have to be on the
inside or on the outside,
but you can't mix.
And here, the ab corresponds to the dx.
So, the order of iteration does not
matter.
And so in this particular case, when I'm
talking about a rectangle, it's
not going to make too big a deal which way
you do this first.
Later on, you're going to find that you
look at
a, a region, it's not always going to be
defined
just as, you know, this is a, this is b,
there's going to be functions that give
you the region too.
For instance, if you wanted to integrate
over a triangle or
a circle or something like that.
And it's going to be a lot easier
generally to do dy dx or dx dy.
So one of them is either going to be very
difficult or impossible.
I mean, they both might be very difficult
or impossible.
But sometimes one is very difficult and
the other one is relatively easy.
And so just, just for your own sanity, I
would recommend doing it the easy way.
So, one of the things I like to do when
I have a theorem like that is just test it
out.
So, let's try an example and see what
happens.
So, I'm going to define the rectangle to
be 1, 3 cross 2, 5 so this
is just in between 1 and 3 on the x-axis
and in between 2 and 5 on the y-axis.
My function will be 2y minus 3x and I
want to compute the double integral
over that rectangle.
So using Fubini's theorem, I can say that
this double
integral is going to be equal to the
iterated integral.
And so in this case, I'll integrate with
respect to
x first, and then I'll integrate with
respect to y.
So again the 1, 3 is here and that's my x
limits so I have to do dx
first if the 1 and 3 are in here and then
2 and 5 are the limits corresponding to y.
And so, the way I'm going to do this
inside integral now, I'm integrating with
respect to x.
So, I'm just going to pretend like y is a
constant.
And then I can treat this just as a single
variable integral.
So the first term, this is just a constant
times dx.
So by the anti-Power Rule all that's going
to happen when
I take the antiderivative of that, just an
x shows up.
And if I were to take the partial
derivative of this term with respect
to x, I would just get 2y, which is
exactly what I started out with.
The second term, the minus 3,
minus 3x that's the derivative of minus 3x
squared
so if I take the derivative again, partial
derivative with
respect to x but it's easier to miss that,
it's
a partial derivative because there's no y
in this term.
I would take 2 times 3 half to the the,
times
x to the 2 minus 1 which would just be 3x.
And
now, I can evaluate this at the limits.
So I guess I was a bit lazy when I wrote
the limits here but once I've done
this, there's no more dx in here to tell
me what variable I've integrated with
respect to 2.
So with 2 it's not too bad, but we can use
the
same idea of iteration to do triple
integrals, quadruple integrals, and so on.
So, it's probably a good habit to
remember that this is x equals 3 as the
upper limit and x equals 1 as the bottom
limit.
But otherwise, I do it exactly the same
way
that I would've done using the Fundamental
Theorem of Calculus.
So the value of this integral is just the
antiderivative evaluated at the upper
limit minus the antiderivative evaluated
at the lower limit.
This thing is the antiderivative,
so all I'm going to do is put in 3 for x
in the first term and
then minus and then substitute 1 for x in
the second term.
And so now, I've integrated out the x,
there's no longer an x in here
but there still are some ys, and so this
is now my, my partial integral.
So it's now a function of y that I
can integrate in the second step with
respect to y.
First though I think I probably simplified
it because
addition is going to make this a little
bit prettier.
So it turns out that's just equal to 4y
minus 12.
And so then this is something we should be
reasonably
familiar with now so I'll just go through
this quickly.
So, I get the antiderivative evaluated at
the top
limit and subtract the evaluation at the
bottom limit.
And so that gives me 50 minus 60,
so that's negative 10 minus 8 minus 24.
So tricky again, I know
some of us don't like signs and pluses but
that's minus 10 minus negative 16 which is
equal to 6.
So, in this case, I did the integral.
I iterated with the dx integral first and
then the dy integral.
And so let's try that again.
But this time, I'm going to do dy first.
So I had to, I switched the, switched the
dy and dx.
And then I also had to switch the two
integral signs.
So the, now that the inside limits, the 2
and
the 2, these correspond to Integration
with respect to y.
And the 1 and the 3, the outside
integral corresponds to integration with
respect to x.
So again, just to use the anti-Power Rule,
2y is the
anti or 2y is the derivative of y squared
and then 3x
is going to be constant with respect to y.
So that just becomes 3xy.
And then again, I'll just evaluate this at
y equals 5 and
I evaluate it at y equals 2 and I take the
difference.
So this is the, the function evaluated
when y is equal to
5 and this is the function evaluated when
y is equal to 2.
And now I just have a function, the y is
entirely gone.
So I have a function of only x and
I'm going to integrate that function from
1 to 3.
So first I'll do some simplification.
And then the antiderivative is
trivial again just with the, the Power
Rule.
So I get 21x minus 9 halves x squared from
1 to 3,
so I evaluate this at 3, I evaluate at 1,
take the difference.
And so it's a, a little bit less pretty
this time but if I have 63
minus 21 that gives me 42.
Then I have negative 81 over 2 and then
minus, minus 9 over 2.
So it's the same as negative 81 plus 9
over 2, which is 72 over 2, which is 36
and so I have minus
36 and again I get 6.
And just for people who weren't paying
attention on the last slide, that's the
same answer we got when we did the
integral iterated on the other direction.
So, that's a, a pretty good check.
If I have a, a simple function, at least
it works and this actually does work in
general.
So you don't need to check it but I just
wanted to go through a, a little example.
Okay so the next thing, we might want to
do, so, so
far I've just talked about doing a double
integral over a rectangular region.
but now suppose instead of a rectangle, I
want to
have a more general region that I'm
going to call D.
So I've, I've, I think on the first set of
slides I called the area
in the x,y plane that I was integrating
above, I called that the domain of
integration.
So that's why I chose D here, it just
means domain.
And
I'm going to write this using a set
notation, so these
little squiggly brackets this means I'm
talking about a set.
And set is just a rule to say something is
in the set or something is not in the set.
And so the way you read this is, the set
consists of points x,y
that satisfy x has to be in between a and
b and
then y has to be in between a function of
x and another function of x.
So there's some function of x on the
bottom and some function of x on the top.
And so for a rectangle g1 of x was just
equal to c and g2 of x was equal to d.
And now this is just letting me have a, a
slightly more general region.
So I could have an upward-sloping line and
then that could
be either a trapezoid or a triangle, or
something like that.
And so then when I do my iterated
integral, I don't really
have the freedom to do it dx dy or dy dx
anymore.
So in this case, I have to do the dx last
because those are where I have the
constants in in the limits.
So if I find an antiderivative of f of
x,y, I'm going to evaluate
it at y equals some function of x and
again at y equals this lower bound of x.
So after I've done this inside integral,
I'm going to have a function of x alone
and then that's going to be something I
can integrate in my second integral.
But the, the limits on the last integral
always have to be real numbers otherwise,
you
know, there's no way for me to integrate
if I had a, a function of y here.
And when I did my antiderivative and then
plugged in my function of y, I would
still have a function of both x and
y so it wouldn't be an iterated integral
anymore.
And so this is kind of, this is what I was
getting at when I said sometimes it's
easier or impossible to do an integral you
know, dx dy or dy dx.
You can actually draw a picture of what
this region
looks like And if it's bounded both
directions you'll always be
able to find a way to describe that as a
to b with a function making the top and
another function
making the bottom.
Or you could think of it as, you know, c
to d with
one function making the left side and one
function making the right side.
And one of those might be easier to do
than the other.
So I think there's an example in the
homework of, of how this will work out,
where
one of the limits is basically what you
need to be able to do integration by
substitution in the outside integral.
Okay.
And so this is just the other possibility.
So d can either have x having the real
limit.
So x between a and b and then y between
functions
of x or you can have y between c and d and
then have x in between functions of y.
And so all that happens here is you just
have to integrate.
So here I do dy dx first and here I have
to do dx dy first.
So we might see something like this.
So, if I say x plus y, so
absolute value of x plus absolute value of
y has to be less than or equal to 1.
So, this describes a, a diamond that just
has corners at
0 plus or minus 1 and plus or minus 1, 0.
So, it's usually helpful to draw a picture
of what this looks like.
Even if it's not
a very good picture, it will still help
you figure out which way
is going to be easier whether you want to
do x first or y first.
And then, this is a, a useful check just
to
make sure you've done things first in, in
getting your region.
So if I have, if I define my function, the
integral of f of x,y just to be constant
1 over the entire domain then when I
integrate
that, I'm just going to get the area of my
domain.
So if I have a, an area and I multiplied
it
by one to get a volume then that volume is
just
going to be equal to the area.
So my double integral over this diamond,
I can write that just as 1 dA.
And now this is a bit tricky
so, it's a good example though of how you
can split up an integral.
So I'm going to integrate with respect to
x last so
that means that the x limits get to be
real numbers.
And conceptually, what I want to do is I
want to
start at negative 1 here and go over to
positive 1.
And just like I could break up the, the
interval into two sub-intervals.
So two integrals that together make the
full interval for a single variable
integration problem.
I can split up the domain into pieces so
that all of those pieces together make the
entire domain.
And so what I'm going to do is this
function
will be much easier to define if it
doesn't have this
sharp right-hand corner at the top.
same with the one on the bottom.
So I'm going to integrate from negative 1
to zero and then from zero to positive 1.
And then my limits for y are at a certain
value of x.
I'm going to go from, this is actually
negative 1 plus x.
So negative 1 minus x is the point down
here.
So if x were
equal to negative 1 half, then y would
equal negative 1 half as well.
And so, what I want to do is just set up
a, a function.
So the, the limits here, minus 1 minus x
and 1 plus x given
x, just tell me how far it is from down
here to up here.
And then, the functions are slightly
different on
the right-hand side, the, the slope just
changes.
So
I have just where I had plus x over here,
I'm going to end
up with minus x over here and the same in
the, in the bottom.
And then all that I have to do is start my
iterated integral.
So the integral of 1 with respect to y,
that's just going to be the derivative of
y.
So I end up with y evaluated at the
top limit minus y evaluated at the bottom
limit.
So what I'm going to do when I evaluate
this now,
I'm going to stick in 1 plus x for y and
so, and then the same thing for the, for
the right-hand integral.
And so what I end up with is, top limit
minus
bottom limit for the, for the integral on
the left term.
And then top limit minus bottom limit
for the integral that's the, the
right-hand term.
And then I go ahead and simplify that.
So I get 2 plus 2x and 2 minus 2x.
But now, I have two single variable
integration problems.
And again, they're pretty easy.
So just use the Power Rule backwards.
And we get 1 plus 1 which is 2 and I guess
I'll flip back to this.
So if I were to take this triangle in the
bottom
right side and put it up here, then I'd
have a square.
And if I took this one and put it up here
I'd have another square.
So that would be a rectangle, these two
squares.
So it'd be width 2 and height 1.
So the area of this shape should be equal
to
two.
And that's what we got when we did our
integral.
So everything is working out so far.
Oh, and I guess I should
mention, so in the first slide
when I put Fubini's Theorem up, I
said that it was over a rectangle.