Now that we have seen how the internal
structure of operators and states can be
represented in the strips representation,
it is time to turn to the bigger picture.
And by that I mean planning domains and
planning problems.
Planning domains implicitly define the
graph in which we are doing search.
Planning problems also define the states
from which we are going and to which we
want to go.
Plans are solutions to planning problems.
And we will now define all this formally.
Here's a quick overview of the concepts
we need to define for classical planning.
Most of modern planning, can be achieved
by simply extending this classical
representation.
So, in classical planning.
The task is to find a solution for a
planning problem.
So we need to define, what is a solution?
And what is a planning problem?
A solution, and a planning problem.
The planning problem consists essentially
of three things.
And those are given to the planner to
come up with solutions.
The first component of a planning problem
is the initial state which is a set of
atoms which relate the object in our
planning problem to each other.
This is exactly the type of state we've
just seen in the strip star presentation.
The next component is the planning domain
and the planning domain consists, in
essence, of operators which are described
by names, preconditions, and effects.
And the final component of a planning
problem is the goal.
Note that the planning domain is
essentially a reusable component.
We will often see many planning problems
that refer to the same domain, but have a
different initial state and different
goal.
But domain is reusable.
Finally when the planner has solved the
planning problem, it will return a
solution to that planning problem, which
is a plan.
Here is how we can define a strips
planning domain.
We start with a function free first oral
language L, as we've seen before.
A strips planning domain over this
language L, is then a restricted state
transition system, consisting of these
components S, A and gamma, as we've seen
before.
You may wonder what happened to the set
of events, that can happen in this state
transition system and that's exactly what
we mean by restricted here.
In the restricted state transition
system, we do not have events.
We only have the states S, the actions A,
and the state transition function gamma.
The set S of possible world states is
then defined as the set of all possible
strip's states.
So, all sets of ground atoms that you can
possible define are an individual state.
The set of actions that we need is then
the set of all ground instances of some
strips planning operators.
And these are the operators that are
defined in the planning domain.
And finally, we define the state
transition function.
Which is, in this case, a deterministic
function.
Because it maps to exactly one state.
Again, this is to do with the restricted
state transition system.
So the state transition function takes a
state s, and an action a.
And maps that to a new state.
Which is defined by taking all the ground
atoms that are true in this state.
Removing the negative effects of the
actions.
And adding the positive effects of the
That is true for an action that is
applicable in the state.
If the action is not applicable.
Then, gamma SA is undefined.
So, there is no resulting state if we try
to apply an action that is not
applicable.
This definition of a state transition
function is, of course, what we've seen
before, full of strips, actions, defined
earlier.
Finally, the set S is closed under gamma,
which means there are no states that
cannot be reached through the stationary
illusion function that are in our set S.
So, that defines a strip's planning
domain, and I hope that none of this
comes as a surprise to you, given what
we've seen earlier.
Here is an example of a planning domain
in the PDDL syntax.
The core of the representation, are of
course the planning operators, and that's
what we have here on the right.
These are the five actions defined, or
the five operators, defined for the doc
worker robot domain, and again, they're
called actions in pdl, but these are
operators.
As you can see, they are perimeterized
and have variables whereas actions would
be ground.
So, we have the move action, the load
action, the unload action, the take
action, and the put action.
That is the complete set of operators
defined for the doc worker robot domain.
In addition to the operators, the PDDL
language allows us to define a few other
things.
And that's what we've got over here.
So we can, for example, say that a domain
has a name.
So that we can refer to this domain, in
planning problems, as we will see later,
by name.
Then we can specify requirements, which
allows the language to extensible.
We can specify types.
These are the five types we've seen
earlier.
Locations, piles, robots, cranes, and
containers.
Then, in this domain specification, we
also have one constant defined, which is
the pallet.
This is defined as part of the domain
here, as it will occur in every planning
problem.
And then we have the predicates, which
where are exactly the predicates we've
seen earlier defined for the dock worker
robot domain.
You can see the complete set here defined
with the types of the arguments.
And that is the definition of this
domain.
If you find this a little hard to read
here, or want to download it.
You can always go to the book website.
So this is all based on the automated
planning book, that you see here.
And there's a website for this book.
And you can see here at the bottom is the
PDDL specification of the dock worker
robot domain.
And so if you click this link, you will
get a PDL file which is almost exactly
what you've seen in this slide.
And since the URL is a little hard to
read here.
It isn't bigger.
So it's
http://projects.laas.fr/planning/.
If you go to that URL you get to this
website, and you will be able to download
the PDDL domain.