Okay.
So, this week, we will be talking about
multiple integrals.
So here's a brief menu for what we will
have.
first I'll introduce something called a
double integral.
So it's basically just a two dimensional
version of
the single variable integral we started
with in week two.
And then I'll talk about something called
Fubini's Theorem.
And this is going to be the, the bit
that actually allows us to compute double
integrals.
And then we have something called change
of variables.
This is basically just the substitution
method, but when we're doing
it with two variables there's sort of a
lot more flexibility.
So I'll teach you how to, how to set that
up.
And then in section four, we'll work
through an example of that.
And then section five is pretty short.
There's a special situation where you have
something called
separability, which allows you to write a
double integral.
It's just a product of two single
variable integrals.
So it makes it a lot easier a lot easier
to evaluate.
And then in Wednesday's lecture, we'll
talk about switching to polar coordinates.
So, in section three, we talked about
change of variables.
Section six, polar coordinates is just one
particular change of variables that we can
do.
section seven, a culturally important
integral.
So this is why there's this 1 over the
square root of 2 pi in the front of the
[UNKNOWN]
function.
And then eight is, this is just something
that's going to come
up reasonably often, so we need to compute
a marginal density function.
So, when you have a density function that
has two or more random variables in it,
sometimes you want to know what would the
density
of one of those random variables look
like.
And this is the way to do it.
That's actually a result that'll be more
applicable
to 461, but the, the math definitely fits
in nicely in this class.
So, I'll go through one example of that.
Okay.
So we'll get started with double
integrals.
So just a quick reminder of what
is the integral of a single-variable
function doing.
So the problem that I tried to, I set out
to solve,
was I have this function f of x on some
interval ab.
And I want to come up with how much area
is underneath f of x, in between a and b.
And so, the approach I took was, I just
decided I was going to come
up with a lower bound by fitting these red
rectangles underneath f of x.
And then I was going to estimate the area
underneath f
of x just as the sum of the areas of these
rectangles.
And then I define the idea of a definite
integral to just be this sum.
So, this thing that I'm trying to
highlight right
here, f of a plus i times delta x.
So, if I start with i equals zero, then a
plus i delta x is just going to
be a, and f of a is just going to be the
height of this rectangle.
So it's the height of the first rectangle.
And then I'm going to multiply that by
delta x,
where delta x is the width of the
rectangle.
And here, so delta x is just going to be b
minus a, so the size of the interval
divided by n.
And the as I make n bigger and bigger, so
I try and cram more
triangles underneath this curve, my
estimate, my approximation
for this area is getting better and
better.
And if I take the limit of that as n goes
to infinity, then I'm going
to say that, that's the area of underneath
the f of x in between a and b.
Well, that's what we did in with a single
variable integral.
For a double
integral we're going to try and do the
same thing, but now with two variables.
So it's really a three dimensional
problem.
We're thinking of z as being a function of
x and oops, and y here.
And now, instead of putting rectangles
underneath the curve, I'm going to try and
build these sort of rectangular solids.
And I'm going to try and put
them underneath the surface.
And then the idea is that I'm trying,
I want to compute the volume under this
surface.
So it's going, the interpretation that
I'm, I'm going for
is the volume between the xy plane and the
surface z.
And so again like the single variable
integral.
If the surface is above the xy plane, I'm
going to get a positive volume,
and if the surface is below the x-y plane,
I'm going to get a negative volume.
And then here, just with four of these
things,
you can see that it's not a very good
approximation.
There's quite a bit missing, but if I
instead
used you know, and I'm dividing each
interval into four.
So it's getting a little bit better.
And then you can go to eight.
So now I guess there's 64 of these little
things, and it's starting to resemble the
surface more.
And so my definition of a double integral
then, for this particular problem, the
domain of integration.
So that's the area in the xy plane, where
I'm trying to, where I'm interested in
estimating the volume.
So, the first one is going to be the x
dimension.
So I want to go 0 to 2 in the x direction.
And then I want to go zero to two in the
y direction.
And then, this surface is
my f of x, y.
And now I need something to sort of say
what my
variable of integration is, so I'm just
going to say dA here.
And dA, you can sort of think of that as
the size of one of these little.
In general, they'll be rectangles, but in
this, they're squares.
So it's the base of each one of these
columns.
And then I'm going to take the limit as m
and n go to infinity.
And here, just like I, I did with my red
rectangles.
Essentially, all I'm doing is this
function is
assigning a height to one of these
columns.
And then delta A is the area of the base
of one of these columns.
So the volume of each column is going to
be given by the, the thing in the sum
here.
And then hopefully,
my approximation gets better and better,
and better as as m and n get bigger.
And in the limit, it would be equal to the
volume under the surface, which is what
I'm trying to get.
And so, just at the bottom here, I
have definitions of all the quantities
I've used.
So, in general, when I want to integrate
over a rectangle.
So I'm going to, I'm going to be using
this notation pretty commonly.
So R just means a rectangular region.
There's no particularly good reason, it's
just I had to chose some letter.
And since it's a rectangle I chose R.
And when I write it like this,
[a, b] cross [c,d].
What I mean is the rectangle with one side
parallel to the x axis going from x equals
a to x equals b.
And the other side parallel to the y axis
going from y equals c to y equals d.
And so, now I'm going to say that the
double integral
over this region R, is going to be equal
to
the same limit I had on the last page,
except
on the last slide, except now I'm just
re-writing it.
So instead of just being ix, I have to
start at a and go ix.
And and then for y, I'm going to start at
c and go j times y.
So just stepping along the y
axis in steps of delta y, and stepping
along the x axis and steps of delta x.
And then the interpretation of this So
like I was trying to argue
before, is if f of x y is greater than or
equal to 0.
So that's basically just saying that the
surface I'm
trying to integrate under is above the xy
plane.
Then I can interpret the, the value of
this integral
as the volume of the region above R and
beneath the,
the surface z equals f of xy.
So like the, like the
single variable integral, we get some,
some
pretty useful properties that are going to
just help.
You know, without evaluating the integral
we can at
least rewrite it in, in terms of its
terms.
Split it into two integrals in this case.
So we have one linearity
property, which is just saying that if I
integrate a sum of two simpler functions.
So in this case, I have the function I'm
integrating, can be
written as one function of x and y f, and
another function of x and y g.
Then the integral of this sum is equal to
the sum of
the two, sorry, sum of the two integrals
yeah, had it right
the first time.
Then the second property that I'm going to
also throw under this name linearity, is
if I scale
my function by.
So c here is going to be a real
valued constant, then the integral of c
times f of x, c times f of x, y is equal
to c times
the integral of f of x, y.
And then I didn't really know what to call
this property, so I, I came up with
comparison.
But it should be reasonably intuitive.
So, if I have two functions f of x y and g
of x y.
And everywhere in my domain of
integration.
So this is my, my rectangle R.
If f of x y is greater than or equal to g
of x y.
So one surface is completely above the
other.
or some, some places they might touch,
which is what the equality would mean.
But if they don't touch, then f of x y is
above g of x y.
Then there has to be more volume
underneath the
surface f than there is underneath the
surface g.
So we'd say that that the
[COUGH]
the double integral of f over R is greater
than
or equal to the double integral of g over
R.
Okay.
And then there's another related integral
called an iterated integral.
And so, I'm going to suppose that f of x,
y is continuous on the rectangle R.
So again, R is just a, b in the x
direction and c, d in the y direction.
And I'm going to introduce a concept
called partial integration.
And so this is sort of the, the backward
idea of
partial differentiation.
So, in partial differentiation, if I have
a function of x and
y, and I want to take the partial
derivative with respect to y.
I pretend x is a constant, so I fix x, and
I
take the derivative, treating the function
as a function of y alone.
In partial integration, I'm going to do
exactly
the same thing, except just the other
direction.
So I'm going to fix x.
Basically, when I say fix x, I mean
pretend x is a constant.
And then I'm going to integrate f of x y
as if it were a function of y alone.
And so that's just going to give me a
function of x.
So when I integrate from c to d of f of x
y, dy, the y is going to disappear,
because after I compute an anti-derivative
for f of
x y, treating it just as a function of y.
I'm then going to replace those, the y's
in the anti-derivative with c's and d's.
So, when I'm all done evaluating this
definite integral
on the right-hand side, there aren't
going to be any y's left in it.
But there still might be some x's, and so
that's going to be my function A of x.
And then I can do something called an
iterated integral.
So, an iterated integral is just going to
be
the integral of A of x with respect to x.
So now I consider integrating from a to b
my function A of x dx.
And this is just going to be a single
variable integral.
But then remember how we defined a of x.
That was just the integral from
c to d of f of x y dy.
So I could also write me iterated integral
in
this form that I have on the right hand
side.
And so, I think you can see kind of why
it's called iterated integral.
It's giving me sort of a, a hierarchy, so
I can
evaluate this thing by first doing the
integral in the square brackets.
That's going to give me a function of x.
And then I can integrate that using
this outside integral, which is just an
integral
of a function of x alone.
And then, most of the time when people
write
this down, they are going to omit the
brackets.
So, both sides of the equality here, they
mean exactly the same thing.
And usually when I'm trying to do one of
these on my own,
I put the brackets back in just to make
sure that everything lines up.
So that the important thing to notice,
that the brackets will help you with,
is that this is something that you're
going to do from the inside out.
So the first integral, oops, the first
integral is an
integral from c to d.
And c and d, these are the y coordinates.
So remember on my rectangle, the, the c
and
the d are describing the height of the
rectangle.
So the bottom and the top of the
So they're in the y coordinate.
So, whatever limits are on here, they have
to correspond to the
first, so in this case d y comes first.
So c, d are the limits for integrating
with respect to y.
And then, once that's done, the next layer
out is going to be the dx layer.
And so the integral, the, the limits on
the outside integral ab, they
correspond to doing the dx dy, sorry they
correspond to doing the dx.
And so,
if you put the brackets in here, just as
one more reminder, that the
limits here have to correspond to the
variable that I'm integrating with respect
to here.
And then, there's no reason why we
couldn't iterate
the other way, so I could also rewrite
this.
And notice, all I've done here, I had dy
dx, here I had dx dy.
So in order to rewrite this integral, I
had to change tho, the integral signs as
well.
So I now have ab corresponding to the dx
and then integral c to d corresponding to
the dy
And so, it's a pretty common mistake I
think,
you know, if you don't put these brackets
here.
That you will eventually use the limits
for the
other variable when you integrate the, the
inside function.
And so, then the big question we're going
to
have is, what is the relationship between
a double integral?
So a double integral, this is, this is the
thing we want.
What I want to do is be able to compute
the area underneath a surface.
And this iterated integral on the right
hand side.
This is something I can actually compute.
And so we'll get to that question in the
next set of slides.