The topic for week three is partial
derivatives, and the menu for
week three is going to start out with
function of several variables.
So, remember our goal is we want to be
able to take the partial derivatives of
the black shoals pricing formula, the
black shoals
pricing formula is a function of many
variables.
So we'll start off just defining what we
mean by a function of many variables .
Then in section two I'll talk about higher
order partial derivatives.
So remember higher derivative was just
when
I took the derivative of a derivative.
When I have a function of more than one
variable I
could take the derivative Of that function
with respect to y.
That will give me a new function.
And then I could take the derivative of
that function with respect to x.
So now it's actually possible to mix the
partial
derivatives, so we have to talk a little
bit about how we're going to deal with
that possibility.
In section three I'll give a concrete
example just using a function of two
variables.
Section four, I'll talk about an extension
of
the Chain Rule for functions of several
variables.
And in section five I'll talk about
implicit functions.
So, an implicit function is a function
that I can't write as Y equals F of X.
It's something a little bit more general.
So, a circle, for instance, would be an
implicit function.
Because when I write down it's equation it
has
to be X squared plus Y squared equals R
squared.
In the second half of this weeks topics,
I'll start talking about the Greeks.
And so the Greeks, recall are the
partial derivatives of the Black Shoals
pricing formula.
And I'll start off just by introducing
what the
Greeks are, and also a notion called
put-call parity.
And then I'll talk about four, or, the
five Greeks.
So we have Delta, which is the derivative
with respect to the asset price.
Gamma which is the second derivative with
respect to the asset price.
Then row vega and theta.
And so these will actually be just
complicated
calculations, but it'll be nice just to go
through them once I think in course with
slides so you can see how they're done.
There some very nice tricks you can use to
simplify the calculations that, you know,
if just try and do this on your own, the
first time you might not catch.