We have now seen what the search states
in our new search space look like,
they are partial plans.
And each partial plan consists of the
four components just described.
Next, we will look at the state
transitions in our new search space.
These state transitions can be understood
as Plan Refinement Operations as they
take partial plan and refine it into
different partial plan.
And since there are four components to a
partial plan, there are also four
principle Plan Refinement Operations that
we will look at next.
The first component of a partial plan
where the actions or to be more precise,
partially instantiated operators.
In general, the partial plans will be
considering containing the following
actions.
The first thing they contain is a
representation of the initial state, and
then they will also hold the
representation of the goal conditions.
Having initial state and goal conditions
as part of the actions in our partial
plan simplifies the representation.
Normally, most of the actions in our plan
will be partially instantiated operators
from our domain.
One thing that is important here is that
when an operator is added to our plan as
a partially instantiated deduction, it
gets a new set of variables that is
different than all the variables we
previously used.
So, the actions in our plan don't share
variables.
Adding an action to a plan is a plan
refinement operation.
But, I've already talked about the least
commitment principle in planning, and
that means we only want to introduce new
actions into our plan for a good reason.
And the two reasons we have for adding
new actions to a plan can be that we have
an unsatisfied pre-condition in our plan
that we still need to achieve.
So, there's is another action that has a
pre-condition that is not supported
anywhere, then we may add an action that
has a pre-condition as an effect.
Or the second case is, that we an
unsatisfied goal condition that we still
need to satisfy.
and we may use an effect of the newly
added action to satisfy that goal
condition.
One important distinction to the type of
planning we've done previously is that we
can add an action anywhere in the plan.
In forward search, we've always added an
action to the end of the plan we're
currently building up. And in backward
search, we've added it to the beginning.
Here, we have no such restriction.
We can add new actions anywhere in the
plan.
Here is pictorial representation of what
this could look like.
We start with the empty plan.
The empty plan consists of the initial
state and the goal.
The initial state contains all of those
things that are initially true.
So, all the propositions that are true in
the initial state are added here as
assertions.
The goal contains all the goal conditions
we want to be true.
I've used different colors for the
different propositions here to indicate
what is already true and what still needs
to be achieved.
So, all the propositions in the initial
state are true, and we don't need to
achieve them anymore.
Whereas the propositions in the goal,
still need to be achieved in someway, so
they are red.
Now, adding an action simply takes a
partially instantiated operator and adds
it to this plan as shown here.
When I add a partially instantiated
operator to a plan, I add this number to
give a unique reference to this action.
So, if I add another instance of the same
operator, I can distinguish them by this
reference.
I also use this reference as an index to
the variables of this operator, such that
I can distinguish the different
variables.
Remember, I told you each new operator
instance gets a new set of variables.
And according to the least commitment
principle, I keep these as variables and
don't assign values to them immediately.
And when I add a new operator, of course
it comes with its own set of
preconditions and effects over its
variables.
The preconditions are in red here because
I still need to achieve these conditions
if I want to be able to execute this
operator.
The effects are given as green because if
I execute this action, then these things
will necessarily become true.
There's other activity I need to do to
make these conditions true.
And, of course, I can add any number of
actions to this plan.
As shown here, I've added a second action
this has the index the reference 2 with a
new set of variables.
Its own preconditions and effect.
The next component of a partial plan
we'll be looking at are the Causal Links.
If we only add actions to a plan when we
have a good reason for doing so, then
perhaps it's a good idea to record that
reason, the rational for adding this
action in the causal link.
So, adding causal links is our next plan
refinement operation.
And the causal link always goes from a
provider to a consumer. In the partial
plans we've looked at so far, there are
two possible providers.
Namely, an effect of an action that we've
just added to the plan, or an atom that
holds in the initial state.
Both these can be used as a provider for
a causal link.
The consumer of a causal link can also be
one of two things.
The first is a precondition of an action
that we've added to the plan, or a goal
condition that we need to satisfy to
achieve our overall goal.
Note that implicit in this, we also have
an ordering constraint.
The provider must, of course, come before
the consumer.
But, we will deal with ordering
constraints seperately and later.
Also, while the provider must come before
the consumer, it doesn't necessarily have
to come directly before the consumer.
So, there may be other actions in between
those two.
The main reason for adding causal links
to a plan is to prevent interference
between different actions in a plan.
So, for example, if we add a new action
to the plan after we have inserted a
causal link and the new action could
become between the provider and the
consumer.
Then, we have to make sure that none of
the effects of that action interfere with
the condition that is protected in the
causal link.
Also, causal links help us to keep track
of preconditions that we have already
achieved.
If we have an incoming link to a
precondition, that means this
precondition is somehow achieved in the
plan and we no longer need to worry about
it.
Going back to our example, here is what
adding causal links looked like.
A causal link is denoted by this type of
dotted arrow in this diagram.
And when we added the move action, we did
this to achieve a goal, so we also can
add a causal link that represents that.
We used the move action to use the effect
at r1, m1 to support the goal at robot
location 2.
Clearly, these variables can be
instantiated such that the goal is
satisfied.
Note that with the addition of this
causal link, I've changed the color of
this goal to green.
Because this goal is now supported by a
causal link, which means it is achieved
by an action that is in our current
partial plan.
Similarly, when I added the second action
this has an effect not unloaded that can
be used to support the other goal and I
can simply add a causal link to support
this goal.
Again, the color changes to green because
it's now supported.
This looks like the addition of actions
and causal links should always go hand in
hand.
But, there is a good reason for
considering the addition of causal links
as an independent plan refinement
operation.
And here is an example of a causal link
that was not introduced together with an
action.
We use a condition from the initial state
to support a precondition of an action
that we've just introduced.
Of course, we could also have causal
links going directly from the initial
state to the goal. But, in this example,
only one of the goal conditions was true
in the initial state.