So the next topic is going to be relative
extrema of functions of several variables.
A local minimum, so basically this holds
for a minimum and maximum, but today I'm
going to
be aiming at minimizing, minimizing risk.
So I'm going to talk about local minimum
of
a function, f, is a point x0 that has the
property that f of x zero
is less than or equal to f of x in some
neighborhood around x0, so.
Epsilon is just some value greater than
zero.
And so I'm making an interval here that's
centered on x0, and at every point
in that interval, so every point x in that
interval, x,
f of x, is greater than or equal to f of
x0.
And if that's true, I'm going to call f of
x0 a local minimum.
And so this is, I think everybody has a
good idea
of what a minimum or a maximum of a
function is.
This is just a way to say the same thing
mathematically.
And then this word extrema just means that
a point is either a local
minimum or a local maximum, so it's a
kind of extreme value of the function.
If f is twice differentiable, so the
function f has two derivatives.
And if the second derivative is
continuous,
then any local extremum is a critical
point of f.
So that means that f prime evaluated at x0
is going to be equal to 0.
And then we can also use this second
derivative test.
So this is the second-order condition to
classify a
critical point as either a minimum or a
maximum.
And so I.
If I have a f prime of x0, strictly
less than zero, that's going to be a local
maximum.
If f prime so, if the, oops.
That should be double primes.
so if the second derivative evaluated at
x0 is
greater than zero, that's going to be a
local minimum.
And if it's equal to zero, then anything
is possible.
So, either of these two, or it can be
neither.
So that's a brief review of how this works
for single variable functions.
Now, let's think about a function of n
variables.
So, a local minimum of a function of n
So, remember that's what this notation
means, that f is a function that goes
from an n dimensional space to a single
value, to a single real number.
[COUGH]
So, local minimum is a point x0 in that n
dimensional space And it's exactly
the same criteria as before, except now,
x0 is going to be a vector of n values.
It's all n of the inputs to this function
f.
x is also a vector of n values.
And I'm just going to make a.
So in two dimensions, you know,
this would just be a circle.
Alright?
So all the points that have distance from
x0 less than epsilon, so
a circle and all the points inside it, so
I guess technically, a disc.
it becomes a, sort of a ball in
higher-dimensional spaces.
So if X is within epsilon of X naught.
Then the smallest I can make that function
is F of X0,
so if that's true I'm going to call F of
X0 a local minimum.
And again every local extremum is going to
be a critical point.
So, if I take the gradient of my function
f
and evaluate that at x0, I'm going to get
zero.
If f is twice differentiable and
has continuous second order partial
derivatives then.
So remember that was my condition for
being able to exchange the
order of taking partial derivatives, so
this matrix, the hessian, so the matrix
of second partial derivatives, evaluated
at the point x naught, so you
have to compute the hessian first, and
then evaluate it at x naught.
That's going to be a symmetric matrix, and
the remember from out linear algebra
lectures a symmetric
matrix has real eigenvalues.
So the second order condition then for a
function of N variables is going to be.
If all of the eigenvalues.
Of the Hessian evaluated at x naught.
So I, I compute the Hessian, that gives me
this matrix of functions.
I evaluate each of those functions at the
point
x naught, then I find the eigenvalues of
that matrix.
If all of the eigenvalues are strictly
greater than zero.
Then that corresponds to a local minimum.
If all the eigenvalues are strictly less
than zero, that corresponds to a local
maximum.
If it has positive eigenvalues and
negative eigenvalues
then you have something called a saddle
point.
And what that looks like is, imagine if
you have plane, and then the
a function of two variables is going to be
a surface above that plane.
A saddle point is something where if I go
this way, I go over a hill like that.
So going straight ahead, it looks like a
maximum to me.
And then going left
to right the function goes like that.
So if you were going this direction it
would look like a minimum.
And if your going this direction it would
look like a maximum.
And that looks like looks like a saddle.
Which if anybody doesn't know what that
is, that's just like
the chair you put on a horse before you
ride it.
which kind of has that shape.
It's more comfortable than sitting on a
local maximum, I guess.
And then the fourth possibility is that
the, so when
I, I compute the Hessian evaluated at the
point x naught.
I end up with a, a singular matrix so this
is
going to be a matrix that has one or more
zero eigenvalues.
And this is going to be the same thing as
what happens when I had the second
derivative being zero.
So now anything can happen.
I can have a saddle point, I can have a
minimum or I can
have a maximum.
So it's basically, when I say anything can
happen, what
I really mean is if you have a singular
matrix for
your hessian, then you are not able to
classify the
critical point as a minimum or maximum or
a saddle point.
So let's go through some quick examples
here.
So suppose I make my function f of x y, x
squared plus xy plus y squared.
I can compute the gradient of that.
I get 2x plus y and x plus 2y.
And you can see right away
that if I evaluate that at 0,0, that's
going to give me a critical point.
So the, the origin is a critical point.
When I compute the Hessian, there's no X's
or Y's left so this isn't the Hessian
evaluated at a particular point, evaluated
at 0,0, this is the Hessian everywhere.
So it's also if I put, If I put in 0, 0
here I'll get the same matrix.
And.
Sort of in our linear algebra lectures I
skipped actually how you
compute eigenvalues, so I'm just going to
use r to compute these things.
probably not worth even trying to do by
hand
if there's a three by three matrix or
bigger.
So first thing I'm going to do is just
make a matrix A That has 2, 1, 1, 2 in it.
Eigen is the function that computes
an eigenvector, eigenvalue decomposition,
or factorization.
And then, it returns a list.
And I'm going to use this dollar sign
operator
to pluck only the values element off that
list.
And it turns out the eigenvalues are
three and one, so they're both strictly
greater than zero.
So since both eigenvalues are greater than
zero; 0, 0 is a local minimum.
Okay.
And so hopefully if.
If x squared plus xy plus y squared had a
local minimum
if I just put a minus sign in front of
each term.
That's basically doing exactly the same
problem but upside down.
So this really ought to have a local
maximum.
So, I'll first compute the.
First, compute the gradient, and again,
that's trivial to
see that 0, 0 is the point that satisfies
that.
So 0, 0 is the critical point.
This time when I the Hessian I get the
negative of the previous Hessian.
Use R again to compute the eigenvalues.
And now I get negative one negative three.
And so both of these are strictly less
than zero.
So since both eigenvalues are less than
zero,
0, 0 now corresponds to a local maximum.
And then third and final example If I now
let
my function be X squared plus 3XY plus Y
squared.
My my gradient is going to be 2X plus 3Y,
3X plus 2Y, and
again, it should be obvious that 0, 0 is
going to be the critical point.
So it's just 2 times 0 plus 3 times 0 is
going to be 0.
0,0 is our critical point.
But now the, the matrix, so you can sort
of see when you look at these for awhile.
If this value is greater than what's on
the diagonal, then
it's not going to have kind of the nice
properties that we like.
So this, for instance, can never happen
with a variance covariance matrix.
If you look at a value on the off
diagonal,
and then you look down at what's on the
diagonal
in that column, and what's on the diagonal
in that row.
If you multiply those two things multiply
the square roots of
those two things together, it has to be
bigger than this.
So now I'm going to use R again to compute
the eigenvalues, and now I get five and
negative one.
And so that I have one eigenvalue that's
greater
than zero, and one eigenvalue that's less
than zero.
And so, now this point 0,0 is going to be
a saddle point,
so that means you can go in one direction,
you go over like that.
And going perpendicular direction, you
drop and go back up like that.
Okay and now, so the those three were,
were pretty simple because
everything was just a degree two term when
I was taking derivatives.
The the Hessian ended up being constant.
And so I just want to go through one quick
example of how, exactly how this works
when it's not.
So now I'm going to put something to the
three halves power here,
so that's not ever going to disappear when
I take deriv, it's not ever
going to become constant when I'm taking
derivatives.
So the first order condition says I have
to compute the gradient of F of XY,
and then find the point X, Y that makes
the gradient equal to the zero vector.
So the gradient is two Y, and then two X
plus
three Y times the square root of one minus
Y squared.
But if you notice, this just has a y in
it, and this has an x in it and a y in it.
And so, if I put in 0, 0 again, I'm
going to get 2 times 0, plus
2 times 2 times 0 here, then 2 times 0
plus 3 times 0 times 1.
So again, zero zero's going to be the
critical point.
The second order condition.
So now I end up with a Hessian that's 0,
2, 2.
And now I have kind of a complicated
function of
Y for my, my two, two entry in my Hessian.
And so this is something I, y'know,
there's no way I could tell R to take the
eigen values of this, so what you have to
remember is it's a test at the critical
points.
So to figure out what matrix I want
to take the eigen values of, I have
to evaluate the Hessian at the critical
point.
So I need to take 0, 0.
Plug in those values here, and that's
going to give me then a matrix that's
just numbers and that's something I can go
ahead and compute the eigenvalues of.
So, if I have 0,0 and I plug in zero for
y, I'm going to
get 3 minus 0, divided by the square root
of 1 minus
0, so 3 divided by 1.
So this is my Hessian at the point,
evaluated at the point 0, 0.
So I'll just use, I'll use R again.
Did I skip it here?
Oh, no I just made it a little bit
smaller.
So here I- to
make it fit on the slide I kind of packed
it all into one command so.
This command that I have highlighted here.
This is what was creating the matrix, so
this is just a matrix of 0, 3, 3, 2.
Oops, so it was supposed to be 0, 2, 2, 3.
when you take
the eigenvalues of this, you get one
positive and one negative.
And so this has a saddle point as a
critical point.