Okay, so I want to keep moving along a
bit.
So, Rho and Vega, they're a little bit
easier
so I tried to cram them into one lesson.
So rho is the rate of change of the value
of a portfolio with respect to the
risk-free interest rate r.
And so again r portfolio that we are
considering right now
just has a single asset in it which is
called option.
So, this will be the pricing formula for
my portfolio, and I want to take the
derivative of that with respect to r, the
partial derivative with respect to the
risk-free interest rate.
[SOUND]
So, what's going to happen, here, the
first, the first term will be relatively
easy.
So I'm going to use the, again the
linearity property, so
derivative of a sum, is the sum of the
derivatives.
This Se to the minus q to the minus T
minus t, this doesn't depend on r.
So I can move that across the derivative
operator.
So the derivative of the first term is
going to be S q T minus t.
Se to the q minus q T minus t, times the
partial derivative with respect to r.
Of capital phi of d plus.
And then I need to subtract.
And
now, here, I'm going to take the product
rule.
Because ke to the minus r, t minus t, and
phi of d minus.
Those are two functions that both depend
on r.
So by the product rule, it's going to be
the derivative of the first function
times the second function, plus the
derivative
of the second function times the first
function.
So the derivative of the first
function with respect to R is going to be.
K times minus t minus little t.
So this is going to get a bit complicated.
I probably should have used a, a
substitution to get this.
But this minus sign here came from this
minus sign here.
Then when I take the derivative.
oh, did I make a mistake?
So when
[LAUGH]
when I take the derivative of
K e to the minus r T minus t, so r is the
variable I'm taking the derivative
with respect to, and that's multiplied by
minus capital T minus little t.
Yeah, do I have
the minus?
I switched
the order of the terms.
So it is, okay, it is okay.
Right, okay.
Right?
Well, there's going to be two minus signs.
Because I'm take.
So this is, the mistake is that, when
you take the derivative with respect to
little t.
Little t is minus n here, and the r.
So,
minus.
Oh, sorry.
I'm confusing myself.
>>
[LAUGH].
>> I'm taking the derivative with
respect to r.
I got ahead of myself.
I was.
Working very hard right before class on
the theta, which is the
next lesson where I'll be taking a
derivative with respect to little t.
Yeah, so oh okay, this is correct.
So I have minus capital t minus little t
times k so that's why I get a minus
capital t times minus little t times k
times e to the minus r t minus t.
Times phi of d minus.
So it's a derivative of the first function
times
the second then plus the derivative of the
second function.
So I'm taking the partial derivative of
phi of
d minus and multiplying that by the first
function.
K e to the minus r t minus t, mm okay.
So crisis avoided.
And
now by the chain rule, so I kept the.
So this, first Bit here it's going to stay
the same and now I'm trying
to take the derivative of a function of d
plus with respect to little r.
So I have to use the chain rule.
So I'm starting to do a few more steps in
each line here.
So we've already seen that the derivative
of capital phi of d
plus with respect to d plus, that's just
little phi of d plus.
And then by the chain rule, I need to
multiply that
by the partial derivative of D plus with
respect to R.
And then the same thing is going to happen
in
the second term of the part in the square
brackets here when I have to take the
derivative
of capital fee again with respect to D
minus.
So I'll get the derivative of capital phi
of d minus, is just lowercase
phi of d minus times the partial
derivative of d minus with respect to r.
So that's just the chain rule, so I've
used it here and
I've used it here.
>>
[INAUDIBLE]
So that's the derivative of capital Phi so
remember we've defined capital
Phi as the integral from minus infinity up
to Z of little
phi.
Alright, so little phi is just the
derivative of Capital Phi essentially.
So, next thing I'm going to need are the
partial
derivatives of d plus and d minus with
respect to r.
So, again, this turns out not to be too
difficult because if I look at the
definition of d plus or d minus so I can,
again, look at these same time.
I can write this as, so I have log of S
over K divided by the denominator
minus q times T minus t over the
denominator, plus or
minus sigma squared over 2 times T minus t
over the denominator.
I want to take all of those bits that
don't depend on r.
And just lump them up into something
that's
constant, relative to the risk free
interest rate, r.
And then the only bit that's left over,
the part that's going
to depend on r, is going to be this plus r
divided
by the square root of T minus t.
And so I have, I'll think of this T minus
t, the actual quantity.
As just the square root squared.
So one of those square roots is going to
cancel.
So I end up on the top with r times the
square root of T minus t.
And on the bottom, I just have this sigma
left over.
And now, this is actually a very easy
function to
take the derivative, because I'm, I
want to take the derivative
of this with respect to r, and so this is
just some number.
Times r to the first power, so I can use
the power rule to say
that's just going to be the square root of
t minus t divided by sigma.
And again, because it doesn't have the,
the part with this plus
or minus sigma squared ended up being
constant with respect to r.
That's just gone.
I doesn't matter if I'm taking the
derivative of d plus or d minus.
I'm going to get the same value, square
root of t minus t divided by sigma.
So if I substitute that in for d plus
and d minus, I end of with this expression
here.
So the first term that we, we already had
and then this
is just the, what we had on the, the slide
before, except the
partial derivative with respect to r of d
plus or d minus, that's
just been replaced with the square root t
minus t divided by sigma.
And I'm going to rewrite that like this.
So it might take a little bit of thinking
to
get from, from the top point to the bottom
point.
The first term stayed the same.
And all I did was reintroduce the square
root of T minus t in the denominator.
So I recovered, just a.
Square root of T minus t squared in the
numerator and
then I factored that out and that's where
this came from.
Then, because I've introduced this s in
the denominator here,
I can factor out an s over here as well.
And so may be with the, may be with the
little bit
of staring at this you will convince
yourself that I can move from
this line here to this line here and now
if you look
at the part that's in this square brackets
that's exactly the same expression.
That we showed was zero
[NOISE]
when we were trying to simplify the
expression for delta, so that I
could compute gamma without have to take
the derivative of all three terms.
So if this thing in the square brackets is
equal to zero,
then it doesn't matter what s, and capital
T and little t are.
This whole second line here is equal to
zero.
And so my expression for rho is just
going to
be K, oops, going to do it backwards, so K
times
T minus t times e to the minus r to the,
so e to the minus r T minus t
times capital phi of d minus.
So that's us getting rho.
[SOUND]
Vega is the rate of change of
the value of the portfolio
with respect to the volatility sigma.
So, now, I just need to take partial
derivatives with respect to sigma.
So again we're going to start off with
Black-Scholes formula for the price
of a European call option.
And
I want to take the derivative with respect
to sigma.
So that's my, my definition of vega.
And so this one looks like it should be
fairly straightforward since.
Here, s, e, q, t and t, there's no sigma
there and the
same for, for the right 10 term.
I have k, r, t and t.
So I'm just going to have to, you know, by
the linearity
property this is the derivative of a sum.
This is sum of the derivatives.
And I can move these terms that are
constant with respect to sigma across the
derivative operator.
So I can write this in this form here.
So I have vega equals S e to the minus q T
minus t.
And then I'm, I'm starting to do more
operations in each step, so.
By the chain role the derivative with
respect to sigma of capital phi is
going to
be the derivative of capital phi which
we've,
which I've said now is lower case phi.
So once you've sort of proved something
one
time, or once you've used a result often
enough.
We don't have to keep proving
at every single time that you do it,
and then by the Chain rule because I am
taking the derivative of.
Capital fi of d plus, d plus is the
function of sigma.
So, I have to use the Chain rule, and
so to get the correct derivative I need to
multiply.
Lower case phi of d plus by the derivative
the
partial derivative of d plus with respect
to sigma and then
I am going to do exactly the same thing to
the
right-hand term except that it's just
going to be a lower-case
phi of d minus and then by the chain
rule partial derivative of d minus with
respect to sigma.
Oh.
>> So is the, 'cause I heard earlier
that that guy was,uh,
[INAUDIBLE]
sigma and we had the, you know, phi being
the, the
[INAUDIBLE]
so, is the actual formula then, in this
case, one of several different varieties.
>>Right.
So, v, v is They chose that letter for a
value so it's the value of a portfolio.
>>
[INAUDIBLE]
>> Well I said in the first slide, the
portfolio I want
to consider during this session is a
portfolio that contains one call option.
Okay, so so for this you know v as an
general for instance when
you are doing the homework i asked you to
calculate vega of a put option.
So then you would say you know v of p
that would be partial if p with respect to
sigma.
In general, V is just whatever your
portfolio is, so you
could put, you know, several shares of the
asset into it.
You could put, some options into it.
Yeah, so V is kind of the general idea and
then, because I'm only pricing a portfolio
with a call option, I've just gone to just
using the call option pricing formula.
Okay, did I explain all of this slide
already yes, I did okay.
So what I need now are partial derivatives
of
d plus and d minus with respective to
sigma.
So I
will start out just by writing down what d
plus minus is so again I am
using this sort of place holder so I can
do them both at the same time.
And so it turns out I can separate this
into
two things that are going to be easier to
work with.
So there is one term in the numerator
here.
The sigma squared over 2 times t minus t
that has a sigma squared in it.
So I'm going to put that all by itself on
the right-hand side.
And so, what I've ended up doing is,
taking the sigma squared over 2, divided
by sigma.
So that's just this sigma
here, divided by 2.
Then I have a T minus t in the numerator.
And a square root of T minus t in the
denominator.
So I have.
T minus T, and square root of T minus T
here.
And then I have to just take what's left,
and put that in the other term.
So I have a log of S over K plus R minus Q
times T minus T.
So.
That's just this part here.
Divided by the square root of T minus T.
And then I'm going to, because I'm setting
myself up to use the
power rule, I'm just going to write that
as sigma to the minus one.
Because I'm, you know, for me personally,
less
likely to make a mistake if I write it
this way than if I try and take
the derivative just with the sigma and the
denominator.
So now I'm going to go ahead and take the
partial derivative of d
plus and minus with respect to sigma.
And notice it's, it's going to kind of
carry through
this time, because now I have the plus or
minus.
And there's a sigma here, so when I take
the derivative
I'm still going to have this plus or minus
thing here, so.
It's now getting important that we be
careful with the plus or minus notation.
So it doesn't look like I really did
anything, but all that happened here is
that
in the first term, I took minus 1 times
this coefficient here, so it's minus 1.
Times this fraction, to the times sigma to
the negative 2.
So that's just the power rule for the
first term.
And then the second term is pretty easy.
That was just sigma to the 1, so by the
power rule, I just get 1
times this quantity here, times sigma to
the 0, or just the
quantity, just the coefficient that was
multiplying the sigma in the second term.
And so I'm going to try and unsimplify now
a little bit, to see if
that, that's going to help me because
it's,
none of this is looking particularly
pretty yet.
So, sometimes when you put it back
together
it will resemble something that you have
seen before.
So I'll try doing that.
So, I'm going to multiply the right
hand term, by Sigma squared over Sigma
squared, just so that I
can have the, the same denominator for
both terms.
And so that's going to make this Sigma
squared
over two, pop up in the numerator again.
And so now, my notation's getting a little
bit tricky but
this turns into a minus over plus, which
just means now
that if I'm talking about d plus, I refer
to the
minus one here, and d minus refers to the
plus one here.
But it's starting to look a little bit
more familiar again.
So the sign here is changed, and I've
picked up a sigma
squared in the denominator, but that's an
expression for the, the derivative
of d plus, or d minus, with respect to
sigma.
And
now I need to substitute that, into this
formula here, and.
Generally, when I'm working, I, I like
after every step for things to look like
they're getting simpler and this is,
clearly, going
to make it get a lot more complicated.
So, I, I put this, kind of, wisecrack in
here.
It looks like it's going to get worse
before it gets better.
and so, usually, you know, you can do
this.
And if you don't make any mistakes, you
will get the right answer.
But, when I see something that gets this
complicated, I start thinking
like, you know, may be there's a better
way to do this.
Or to at least You know, if it's, sort of,
a risk management technique.
You know, now all of the sudden investing
a little bit of
time to, maybe, not have to do this might
be a good idea.
So, let's see what I have down here.
So, let's look at this, this results been
handy already.
So, maybe, I can squeeze a little bit more
mileage out of this.
Okay, so, we're here, so I'm going to
rewrite this, so if I,
if I add the second term to both sides, I
just put the equals sign in between here.
And then, since sigma and the square root
of T
minus t are going to be on both sides, I
can, and.
They're both greater than zero.
I'll multiply both sides by that.
And then move this S from the denominator
of this side just into the numerator on
this side so the fractions will go away.
So I can simplify this expression a bit
and I have this.
And so, does that look like it's going to
be helpful?
Well,
I've got an Se to the minus q, T minus t
here.
And I've got a Ke to the minus r, T minus
t here.
So, so far, you know, things are looking
good.
And so this was my expression for Vega, so
this
is exactly what I had on the previous
slide here.
And if
you look at this a bit, I've got this D
plus term, here.
So, the derivative of D plus with respect
to sigma on here.
A derivative of D minus with respect to
sigma.
And so, it turns out I can rewrite this
like this because I have.
On the previous slide I have this equality
relationship here,
and so now this is starting to look quite
a bit
better, and now the next big step that I
can make.
Was that not clear?
I guess I, I didn't mention one thing.
So what I did to, to get that, I took
the derivative of this expression here
with respect to sigma.
And that turns out to be exactly what this
is.
And now I can replace one of these guys
with,
With the bit that I have here with the s.
And so if I can replace this thing with
the, the first bit here.
Then I can just factor that out.
And so, essentially, it's that same
computation that we've done.
You know?
It's, it's kind of complicated.
But just.
changing this d minus, this phi of d minus
into a phi of d plus, and
some other stuff, but since I've already
done
that calculation, I'm just going to reuse
that result.
Then I end up with the partial derivative
of d plus with respect
to sigma minus the partial derivative of d
minus with respect to sigma.
But that's same thing so I can, you know,
do this linearity property backwards.
If I, if I had,
d plus minus d minus, and I took the
partial derivative of
that quantity, with respect to sigma, I
would get exactly this thing here.
And now the, the trick is to remember that
d minus
is defined in terms of d plus by this
relatively simple expression.
So if I want to look at d plus minus d
minus, so the thing that I'm trying to
take the derivative of.
I have D plus minus the quantity D plus
minus sigma times the square root of T
minus t.
And so, that's D plus minus D plus.
So, the D plus goes away.
And then, I have minus negative square
root of T minus t.
So that's just going to be sigma times the
square root of t minus t.
And then I'll take the derivative with
respect to sigma of both sides of this.
And so this is actually pretty straight
forward, this is just the power rule now.
So the partial derivative of sigma times
the square root of t with minus t.
With respect to sigma, it's just going to
be the square root of t minus t.
So that's quite a lot less work than I was
looking at before.
So now I can plug this in here,
and I'm finished.
So that's my expression for vega, so.
This partial derivative here of d plus
minus d minus, with respect
to sigma, that was just the square root of
T minus t.
And so then I have this S, S, T minus t, T
minus t,
and the rest, e to the minus q T minus t
times phi of d plus.