This is demonstration of Nonlin running
in Poplog First, going to change the
directory where Nonlin is located,
and then load the source file.
We're offered the choice of loading a
critical path calculation package which
we're going to do. There's some errors in
it in certain versions of Poplog, we can
just ignore that. And then, we look at
the main menu which is called TF Info.
We'll load a new TF file,
in this case, it's going to be block
zero, block zero.
Which is a demonstration of the Sussman,
and normally block second problem.
And now, we'll give the goal schemer,
which is to plan for the goal on AB and
the goal on BC.
So, we're going to make a stack of
blocks.
And that's the plan already created.
There's some diagnostics that are showing
while the expansion was taking place.
So, we're going to look at the results
network.
We'll go through all of the different
options here.
So we're looking at the main results
network,
it's got a few dummy nodes and so on in
there and we can get a cleaner version
just with the actions only.
We're showing there the predecessors and
successors of each, each node.
And then, we're going to look at the
critical path data.
But in this case, the data is all zeroed
out because there is no data in it.
Then, we're looking at the goal structure
table and the table of multiple effects.
We'll look at any initial context in the
plan and the, the, initial state for the
plan.
And we can do a simulation of what the
state looks like at any point in the
plan.
In this case, we'll just look at it at
the end node.
So, this is the state at the end of the
plan having been executed.
We'll load a new domain now.
In this case, it's going to be a house
building task with some critical path
method data in it,
some durations and times.
So we'll set up a task for this one which
is just to build a house, to expand a
top-level action of building the house.
And again, that's plan created so we'll
just look at the results.
And again, we're going to through all the
options.
We'll just see the main results network
with all of the dummy nodes in, in place.
And we'll look at it just cleaned just
with the actions.
And then, we'll going to look at it with
the critical path method data which will
give us the durations, the early
finishes, and the late finishes for each
node.
And the start, the role starts means it's
on the critical path.
And again, we're looking at the gold
structure table,
and the table of multiple effects.
And again, the initial context there is
none in this case.
And then, we'll look at the context of a
particular node doing a node simulation.
In this case, again, we'll look at the
state at the end of the plan.