So, we have now seen what the search
state look like in our new search-space,
and we have seen what the state
transitions in this new search-space.
look like.
And there were four such transitions
according to the four components of a
partial plan, we could add an action, we
could add an ordering constraint, we
could add variable bindings, and we could
add causal links to the partial plan.
This means we're very close to the
definition of plan-space search as a
search problem.
So, we will look at the missing bits and
pieces next.
The first thing that is missing to define
our problem is the initial search state.
Our initial search state is the empty
plan that contains only the goal and the
initial state, and we will add the goal
and the initial state as dummy actions to
our plan.
To do this, we have one action, init,
that has no preconditions and has
everything in the initial state as
effects of the dummy action.
So, if this is the first action in our
plan, the result is that the initial
state holds.
And then, we have another action in our
plan goal, which contains all the goal
conditions as preconditions and has no
effect.
And if this is the last action in our
plan, that means before we can execute
this goal action, all the preconditions
must hold, which means the goal has been
achieved.
Our initial search state is then the
empty plan, pi 0, consisting of the
following component.
First, we have the two dummy actions,
init and goal, which we just described.
Then, we have one ordering constraint,
namely that init must be before goal.
We have no variable binding initially
because there will be no variables in the
initial state or in the goal.
They're all fully ground.
And finally, there will be no causal
links between any of the propositions in
the initial state or the goal.
That is the empty plan, the initial
search state we'll be using to start our
search.
And here is our empty plan in a pictorial
representation.
We have the two dummy actions, init and
zero.
These are two actions in this plan.
So, each action consists of preconditions
and effects.
The preconditions of init are here and
they're of course empty,
and the effects of goal are here and
again they're empty.
Otherwise, what we see are the initial
propositions from our initial state in
the planning problem and the goal
conditions from our planning problem.
Also, we have this ordering constraint
here saying that init has to come before
goal.
That's it.
That's the empty plan.
And I hope you're not getting confused
with the initial search state here.
So, we distinguish the initial state that
is part of our planning problem which is
a world state consisting of all these
ground atoms.
And we have the initial search state
which is the state from which we start
our search, in this case the partial
plan.
The two have nothing to do with each
other, although, they are both initial
states in some way.
One is the initial state in the world
state space,
and the other is the initial state in our
search.
The successor function we need to define
our search problem is, of course, given
by the plan refinement operation we've
seen previously.
So, we generate successors by applying
our plan refinement operators.
And we can apply one or more of these
operators at the same time to constitute
one step in our successor function.
And the reason why we want several
operators at the same time is simply that
we need to keep our partial plans
consistent.
So, we've already seen examples of that,
namely when we add a causal link, we
should also add an ordering constraint at
the same time in the same step.
This is necessary to keep our plan
consistent.
So, our plan refinement operators are
combined to give us the successor
function.
We use one or more of the following,
adding an action, adding an ordering
constraint, adding a binding constraint,
or adding a causal link to the partial
plan we're currently observing.
And we want to do this in such a way that
our partial plan remains valid.
So that means that all the constraints we
add as part of our plan refinement must
be satisfiable in some way.
You can see that what plan-space search
is doing is decoupling two problems that
we need to solve as part of planning.
The first problem is, which actions to
execute as part of our plan.
And the second problem is, how to
organize these actions.
What is the organizational structure that
underlies our plan?
Another view of plan-space search is that
we view a partial plan as really
representing a set of plans, namely all
those plans that we can achieve from this
partial plan by these plan refinement
operations.
So, every time we apply refinement
operation as part of our planning
process, we reduce the set of possible
plans into which the partial plan can be
refined.
And we do this until the plan is fully
ground and there is only one plan left.
Now, what remains to be defined here for
our plan-space search problem is the goal
test.
But before we define the goal test for
our search problem, we need to reconsider
what we understand by a solution for a
given planning problem.
Just a quick recap, a planning problem
was defined by a state transmission
system, initial state, and a goal
condition.
And the plan pi is considered a solution
for this planning problem if the
application of the plan in the initial
state gives us a new state and that state
satisfies our goal.
That is how we have defined a solution
for a planning problem.
And here is the problem that we have now.
This term, gamma si pi, was only defined
for a sequence of ground actions because
those were the only plans we've
considered so far.
The plans we are considering now are only
partially ordered.
Of course, we can turn this partial order
into total order by respecting all the
partial order constraints.
But then the question is, in our
definition of gamma si pi, which of these
total orderings should we use?
In general, there could be an exponential
number of total orderings that correspond
to one partial order.
Similarly, our partial plan may only
contain a partial instantiation of the
variables which we will need to bind in
our plan.
So, there may be a large number of ways
to turn our partially instantiated
variables into a fully ground plan and we
need to decide which ones of those to use
for our definition of a solution.
The simplest way to address this problem
is to consider a new definition of a
partial order solution.
And here is our new definition when a
partial order plan constitutes a solution
to a planning problem.
A planning problem, of course, consists
of the same component as before. Which
means it's a state transition system, an
initial world state, and a goal
condition.
And we consider a plan that may be a
solution consisting of actions, ordering
constraints, variable bindings and causal
links.
That may be a partial order solution for
our planning problem if two conditions
hold.
Firstly, the ordering constraints and the
variable binding constraints in our
partial plan must be consistent.
The ordering constraints are consistent
if there's no loop in the orderings.
And the variable binding constraints are
consistent if we can find values for all
the variables such that all the
constraints which are equalities or
inequalities are respected.
So, in our partial order solution, all
the variable bindings and ordering
constraints must be consistent. And, we
have another condition. Namely, that for
every total order sequence of a1 through
ak, which are the actions in a minus the
init and goal actions, these were the
dummy actions we've only used in our
empty plan, the other actions were the
ones that were added through plan
deployment operations of the first type,
namely adding actions.
So, every such totally ordered sequence
that is fully ground and respects the
orderings and variable binding
constraints must satisfy the following
condition. That is, if we apply this
total order plan in the initial state,
then the state transition function gives
us a new state which must satisfy our
goal.
So, there is an exponential number of
ways to turn our partial order plan into
a total order plan, and our definition
for a partial order solution now requires
us to have every such total ordering
satisfy our goal.
There are a few things to note here.
And the first interesting thing is, that
the causal links apparently don't play a
role in the definition of a solution
plan.
The second is, if we want to turn this
into a computational procedure that we
can use as a goal test, it is not very
practical.
If we have to test every total order
sequence and there is an exponential
number of such sequences, then we have a
lot of work to do to verify our goal
test.
But, of course, in the construction of
our plan, we pay careful attention to the
the way we combine the action.
And, in fact, if every precondition of
every action is supported by a causal
link, then we know that our plan will
satisfy the goal because the goal is the
final step in our plan.
The problem is, this condition that every
precondition is supported by a causal
link is not quite strong enough as a goal
test yet.
But, we will get there soon enough.