Now, we have seen what the strips
representation for world states looks
like.
The internal structure is represented as
a set of ground atoms.
Where each atom expresses a relation that
must hold between objects in the domain.
The next step, then, is to look at
operators with internal structure.
And actions that are instances of these
operators.
Remember that actions are what give us
the state transitions in our state
transition system.
For states I started with some examples
and some informal definitions and
followed this with the formal dentition
of what a strips representation state is.
For operators I'll do it the other way
around.
I will start with the formal definition
of what a strips operator is.
A planning operator in the strips
representation is simply a triple, so
means it consists of three different
things.
A name, the name of the operator, the
preconditions of the operator, and the
effects of the operator.
The name of the operator, the name that
we can use to refer to this operator, is
simply given by this syntactic
expression.
So it consists of a unique name symbol
that we can use to refer to this
operator.
It must be unique to this operator,
meaning no other operator can have the
same symbol.
And it consists of some parameters which
characterize the objects that are
manipulated by this operator.
These objects are defined as variables
for an operator as an operator is
generic.
They may also be typed if we are using
the types extension in PDDL.
The components that define the internal
structure of an operator are the
preconditions, and the effects of the
operator.
And both of these are sets of literals.
Remember that a literal is either a
positive or a negative atom.
So, a relation between objects.
Where the objects are named by the
variable given in the operator name.
X1 through xk here.
The preconditions are simply those
literals that we want to be satisfied in
the state before we execute an action.
The effects are the things that are true
after we've executed an action.
Again, the effects can be literals, which
means they can be positive or negative,
and traditionally the positive literals
that are effects are often referred to as
the ad list, as this is something that is
asserted in the new state after an action
is applied, and the negative literals are
referred to as the delete list as these
are removed from the state.
An operator is generic in the sense that
it only specifies what is manipulated by
the operator, as variables.
An action, on the other hand, is specific
because there's a ground instance of a
planning operator.
So if we take all the variables and
choose values, objects in our domain, for
these variables, then our operator
becomes an action.
And of course, there can be many actions
that are instances of the same operator
in our planning domain.
Now, here are some examples of operators
defined for the dock worker robot domain.
The first example we will look at is the
move operator.
Move is the symbol that identifies this
operator, and the name of the operator is
given by all of this.
This expression here.
Namely, the symbol that identifies it
plus the three variables that are used to
identify its parameters.
And these are a robot and two locations.
The location we are moving from and the,
the location we are moving to.
Then, the internal structure is defined
by preconditions and effects.
There are two positive pre-conditions in
this example.
Namely that the two locations when moving
between must be adjacent.
The location when moving from must be
adjacent to the location we are moving
to.
And the robot R, the robot that we are
moving must be at the location we are
starting from.
And then we have one negative
precondition and that is given here.
This is simply the symbol for negation,
that's the NOT symbol in logic.
the negative precondition here says the
location m we are moving to must not be
occupied by a robot when we move there.
So three preconditions.
Two positive one negative.
And then we have the effects.
Again two positive effects, and two
negative effects here.
Let's look at the positive effects first.
When we move robot R from location L to
location M as a result the robot will be
at location M.
And the location M will be occupied as a
result of this action.
These are the effects that are added by
this operator.
Hence, this is known as the add list.
the delete list, or the negative effects
of this operator, are that the location L
is no longer occupied.
We've just moved the robot away from this
location.
And the robot is no longer at this
location, L, that we've just moved away
from.
There are a few things that are quite
common about this operator.
But they are not part of the definition
of a strips operator.
And those are, all the parameters are
actually mentioned in the preconditions.
R, l, and m.
All of those are mentioned in these three
conditions.
Also very common is that we have the
negative effects of the operator, the
delete list, as part of the
preconditions, only negated.
For the second negative effect, this is
explicit here.
And for the first one, it is implicit.
Of course, the location l was occupied
before the robot moved away from that.
But because we have this precondition, it
was not necessary to mention that.
Quickly, the two other examples.
The second one is that we're loading.
With crane K at location L.
We're loading container C onto robot R.
These are the four arguments to this
operator.
And all this is the name of the operator.
Again, we have preconditions and effects.
And they are divided into positive and
negative preconditions and effects.
In fact, we have no negative
preconditions for this operator.
So the positive preconditions are that
the crane must belong to that location.
It must be at that location.
the crane must be holding the container.
So it can load it onto the robot, which
must also be at that location.
And must be un-.
Loaded so it cannot have a container on
it.
The effects are.
That now the crane will be empty after
we've loaded the container onto the
robot.
So it will no longer hold the container,
but the container will be loaded onto the
robot, and the robot will no longer be
unloaded.
Similarly there's the put action which
has as parameters a crane, a location, a
container, another container and a pile
into which we're putting the container C.
The crane must be at that location and
also the pile must be at that location
and of course we want the crane to hold
to the container.
And this precondition here tells us the
meaning of this second container D that
is a parameter that to put action, namely
it is the container that is on top of the
pile before we execute our action.
And the reason why we need to know this
is simply such that we can withdraw this
from our state.
So the container D is, after we've
executed the action, no longer on top of
the pile because we have the container C
on top of D and now C is the new top of
the pile.
So C will also be in our pile, the crane
will be empty, and the crane will no
longer hold container C.
there's also an unload and a take action
that reverse the load and the put action
but I won't go through those in detail
here.
In the previous slide, we have seen some
examples of operators, of what they look
like logically.
Now I will introduce the PDDL syntax, for
defining an operator in a planning
domain.
This example, again, starts with a
comment, introduced by the semicolon,
that tells us what this action will
actually do.
And here is the first slightly confusing
thing about the PDDL definition.
Namely, the operator is called an action
in PDDL.
So, in the strips representation, we
consider an action to be an instance of
an operator.
In PDDL, this is what is called an
action.
This is actually not uncommon in the
planning literature, that terminology is
not agreed.
So you always have to make sure that you
understand what authors mean by the
different terms like action or action
type or operator, et cetera.
So in PDDL, this action has the unique
name, move, that can be used to identify
this, action, this operator.
And it has several parameters that are
defined here.
And there is one parameter which is this
one, a variable.
Remember, variables start with the
question mark R, which is of type robot.
And then it has two more variables, both
of the type location.
This is what we call the name of the
operator.
In the definition of a strips planning
operator two slides ago.
Next we have the preconditions and
effects.
So the preconditions are introduced by
the preconditions symbol, and then are
just listed.
It is also exclusively stated in PDDL
that this is a conjunction.
Of pre-conditions.
So they all must hold.
And that's what we introduce with the an
symbol.
PDDL also allows other pre-conditions,
dis-disjunctive pre-conditions.
But we will not look at those here.
So what we have is that, the first
pre-condition is that two locations must
be adjacent.
The robot must be at the first of those
two locations we're starting from.
And this location must not be occupied.
Slightly different syntax, but exactly
the three pre-conditions we've seen in
the previous slide.
Similarly for the effects, they're listed
here.
They are a conjunction of effects.
And it's the same four effects we've seem
previously.
Namely that the robot must be at the two
location, as a result of the action.
And this location will be occupied.
The robot is no longer at the from
location, which is not, no longer
occupied.
You should now be able to express the
other two operators introduced in the
previous slide, in the PDDL presentation.
So why don't you do that as a little
exercise here.