We have now seen a conceptual model for
planning,
namely, the state transition system.
This helped us formulize the problem we
are trying to solve in planning.
A technique that is used almost
everywhere in planning, and in many other
areas of AI is called search.
And this is what we will be looking at
next.
Before we go in to the details of search
algorithms, I briefly want to talk about
the types of problems we will see on this
course.
Namely, toy problems versus real-world
problems.
Toy problems are characterized by a
description that is concise and exact.
The description being concise allows me
to describe the problem in one slide
quickly.
The description being exact means there
shouldn't be too much ambiguity about
what the problem is trying to do.
Toy problems are often used for
illustration purposes,
for example, on this course.
They are also used to compare the
performance of different search
algorithms.
Toy problems have two interesting
properties.
Namely they are rich and simple.
By rich, we mean they're anything but
trivial to solve.
And by simple, I mean, they can be
described easily and precisely.
Real-world problems tend to be very
different.
To begin with, there is no single
agreed-upon description for most
real-world problems.
That means if we were to use real-world
problems in this course, I would spend a
lot of time describing what the actual
problems is and describing the details
that need to be addressed in each
problem.
However, toy problems are good as mental
exercises.
But real-world problems, people care
about the solutions of those.
The missionaries and cannibals problem we
have seen earlier clearly falls into the
category of toy problems.
Now, before we go into search algorithms,
we need to characterize what constitutes
a search problem, and here are the four
components that characterize a search
problem.
The first component is the initial state.
This is simply the state of the world
from which we start our search.
In the missionaries and cannibals
problem, this was the state where all the
missionaries and all the cannibals and
the boat were on the left-hand side of
the river.
Next, we need a set of possible actions.
Not every action will be applicable in
every state,
so we will also need to define the
applicability conditions for actions in
states.
We can define the actions through a
successor function.
A successor function maps a state into a
set of pairs of actions and state.
So, for each state of the world, the
successor function maps it to all those
actions that are applicable,
together with the states that result from
the action being applied in the original
state,
and leading us to this new state.
Together, the successor function and the
initial state span a state space which
corresponds roughly to the states
transition graph we have seen earlier.
The state space is a directed graph with
states as nodes and actions as labels on
arcs.
The third component of a search problem
is the goal.
This can be either an individual state,
in which case, we have just one unique
goal state, or in general, we can have a
function that tests whether a given state
is a goal state or not, which allows us
to have many different goal states.
A solution to a search problem is simply
a path in the state space from the
initial state to a gold state.
The final component of a search problem
is the path cost function.
This simply assigns a cost value to each
possible path in the state space.
we use this when we're doing optimal
search.
When we're looking for an optimal path,
we're looking for the path with the
lowest cost.
A simplification that is often used in
planning is that each action has a fixed
cost and that the cost of a path is
simply, the sum of the step cost,
the cost of each action.
Now, you will have noticed that there are
some similarities between what we've just
defined and stay transition systems, and
the next quiz will give you little time
to think about those similarities and
differences.
Going back to the missionaries and
cannibals example, let's try to define
this as a search problem.
So, we need to define the four
components, which were the initial state
which was given to us as part of the
problem.
And the third component was the goal
state which was also given to us as part
of the problem.
Then, the fourth component is the path
cost function.
And there, we simply assume that every
step has the same cost.
So, the only thing that is slightly more
complex is the successor function.
And we can define this as a table as
shown here.
So, what this table does is simply
enumerate all the mappings of states to
set of action state pairs.
What we have on the left-hand side is a
state.
So, this is the initial state as defined
in the problem.
And I'll decipher this for you quickly.
This has two components.
It says, what's on the left-hand side and
what's on the right-hand side.
On the left-hand side, we have the three
missionaries, we have the three
cannibals, and the boat.
And on the right-hand side, we have no
missionaries and no cannibals initially.
So, that is the initial state.
We describe everything that's on each
side of the river.
This is mapped to three pairs.
One, two, three.
each of which consists of an action and
another state.
So, let's look at the first one.
In the first case, we ship two cannibals
across the river.
And this gives us, on the left-hand side,
three missionaries, one cannibal,
because we ship two cannibals across.
On the right-hand side, zero
missionaries, and two cannibals, plus the
boat, which is also now on the right-hand
side.
Altogether, we see there are three
different pairs here because, there are
three applicable actions in the initial
state.
In the next row, we have a different
And we, again, define what can be done in
this state, these are the two actions,
and the resulting states that we get if
we apply these actions.
This is actually, the same state that
we've looked at just now.
This state here became the state there.
So, we need to do this for the whole set
of states that are available for the
whole states base.
Which means we need to go through a whole
list of states and define where we can go
from these states.
And if we had completed this table, we
had defined the whole state-transition
function and this concludes the
definition of the surge problem.
In contrast to this toy problem, we will
now look at a real-world problem,
namely, touring in Romania.
What you see here is a rough map of the
country with some of its major cities.
To define touring Romania as a search
problem,
we again have to define the four
components of a search problem.
So, let's start with the initial state.
Suppose we are in the city of Arad,
that's where we start our tour of
Romania.
The next thing we need to define are the
possible actions that we can take in this
problem.
Since we are looking at a map, it
suggests that we can drive from one city
to another.
But presumably, when you're touring a
country, that's not all you want to do.
You probably also want to do some sight
seeing, or you need a hotel, so you need
to check into that hotel,
you need to book a hotel.
there are many different types of actions
that you want to do when you tour a
country and you can see, this is a real
world problem.
We already have the first problem,
deciding what the possible actions are.
The same applies for the goal.
When you're going on holiday somewhere,
to tour a country or a region, what is
your actual goal?
Well, presumably, you want to end up in
the same state that you started off,
namely, at home.
So, that can't really be the goal.
You want to have something else that you
need to describe as your goal, something
that happens along the way.
But it's very hard to describe because
this is a real-world problem.
What is the little bit easier is probably
the cost that is associated with each
action and that will mostly be time and
money.
As a side remark, the touring in Romania
problem is taken from a famous AI
textbook, by Russell and Norvig. And if
you want to learn more about search, I
recommend that you have a look at this
book.
The reference to this book will be given
on the course website.
So, what you have just seen is that
problem formulation is itself a complex
problem.
And its the problem of defining the four
components of a search problem.
In problem formulation, we have to decide
what actions we want to consider and what
states we want to consider in the world.
Probably the most difficult decision
there is, at what level of abstraction
are we looking at the world?
What detail do we want to take into
account and what detail do we want to
omit?
So, looking at the touring Romania
examples, we could define actions that
describe how we drive a car that, say, we
have to turn a steering wheel by one
degree left or right and we have to move
our foot from one pedal to the other.
But this would probably give us too much
irrelevant detail and there's a lot of
uncertainty involved in that, too.
So, we probably don't want to go to that
lower level of detail.
Also, if we try to solve our problem at
that level of detail, we would come up
with a solution plan that has many, many
steps.
If we define the problem at a higher
level of abstraction,
say, we consider actions that drive us
immediately to another big city.
Then, we have the problem that we need to
decide how to execute such an action when
we come to plan execution.
Also, if this is the level of abstraction
we consider driving to another city,
we can't really talk about things we do
in between, between two cities.
So, deciding at what level of abstraction
we model our actions and states is
probably the most important decision in
problem formulation.
But to help us with problem formulation,
there are number of assumptions that
search engines and planners often make
and if we take those in to account during
problem formulation, we may have a much
easier task.
The first assumption is that we have a
finite number of world states.
This implies that we cannot have
continuous variables in those states, as
this would automatically give us an
infinite number of states.
Then, we will assume that the world is
fully observable.
Which means everything that is relevant
to us in the state of the world can be
seen and will be known to the algorithm
to our planner that we're using.
The next assumption is that the actions
that were using are deterministic, which
means each action has one well-defined
outcome.
There's no uncertainty which state we'll
be in after we apply an action.
The final assumption is that the world is
static.
Which means, there are no events so
nothing happens that we don't do.
Only the actions that we do modify the
state of the world.
So, these are assumptions about the
environment, but we will also make some
other assumptions that are useful for
planning.
The first one is that we have restricted
goals.
And that means that our goals are either
given to us as a single state that we
want to be in or a set of states that are
all gold states.
The second assumption is that the
solution we are looking for is a
sequential plan, so a solution is a
linear list of actions.
There's no parallel activity in our plan.
We shall also not consider time
explicitly but only implicit, which means
activities will not have a duration for
the time being.
And the final assumption is that we're
doing offline planning, that is, the
state transition system which underlies
our planning process is not changing
while we're doing the planning.
Okay, time for another quick quiz to give
you time to think about this.