Hello, and welcome to this introductory course on General Game Playing
My name is Michael Genesereth and I'm a professor at Stanford Univerity
I'm the primary developer of this course, but I'm not the only one involved
Some of the material is due to Michael Thielscher, professor at the University of New South Wales and a one-time winner of the international general game playing competition
There's also Sam Schreiber, another winner of the international game playing competition and developer of the game playing software used in the course
Some credit here is also due to people like Alex Landau and Peter Pham and Bertrand Decoster and other teaching assistants who have helped to refine the material over the years
Before we get started I wanna make some general remarks about the course
First of all a few words about content: the course is an elementary introduction to general game playing
It presents the theory of general game playing and leading general game playing technologies
Second it shows how to create and test general game playing
programs capable of competing against other programs and humans
And finally it offers a glimpse of some of the real world applications of general game playing
Although the course is elementary, it does assume some basic background
First of all, you should be familiar with symbolic logic
Game descriptions are written in the language of symbolic logic and it helps to be able to read and write such descriptions
Second you should be familiar with the concept of computer programming
At the very least you should be able to read and understand program fragments written in modern programming languages
We use javascript in all of our examples, javascript is fairly simple
If you're familiar with languages like Java and C you should be able to read javascript without any further training
If not, you might want to spend some time learning the language that you can understand the examples
Okay with these two elements you should be able to understand the presentations and the course and you should even be able to configure a player to compete in competitions using some software components provided by us
On the otehr hand if you're adept at programming you may wish to modify the standard components or even build your own player from scratch
There's not restriction on what language to use in building your player so long as it abides by the general game playing communication protocol which we'll see later
The ability to write your own general game playing program or configurable one is desirable but it's not required
Like other online courses all the material in this course is accessible via the course homepage
The material includes online videos, many of these videos include interactive exercises
These exercises do not count towards your grade but they're useful in insuring that you understand the material being presented
There are also written notes for each lesson, these are basically transcriptions of the videos but there's some supplementary material there as well so you might want to take a look
There are online problems and programming assignments, we use these to evaluate your understanding of the material so they are required in a sense
These count towards your grade which is important if you want a certificate at the end of the course
There's some background reading, this material is optional but quite useful and there is a community forum which you can use to discuss general game playing with the instructors and other students
One of the important difference from many other online courses is that the completion of this course requires that you develop a computer program and test it by having it compete with programs developed by other students
In particular, we want you to develop a general game playing system of your own and see how it does in playing games against the general game playing programs developed by others
You can learn a lot about general game playing by simply listening to the videos and doing the exercises
You can learn even more by participating as a player in general game playing matches
But it's our belief that it's better yet if you develop a general game playing program of your own
We believe that this not only increases the fun of the course, but also facilitates and deepens your understanding of the material
For those of you with programming experience, especially those who know javascript or Java, this should be relatively straightforward
In the lectures we present javascript versions of all the techniques discussed in the course
And online we provide a codebase for a high performance player written in Java
You can create a player simply by running this code, and you can prove its performance by modifying it as you see fit
For those of you who are not programmers or are not familiar with Java, we offer an alternative approach
We've created a parametric player, that is a general game playing program whose behaviour is based on the values of various configuration parameters
There's a graphical user interface that allows you to specify different options for these parameters and thereby create general game players with different capabilities
You just start the program and use your browser to configure the player
Whichever approach you use, your job will be to test your player by having it compete against other players on games of increasing complexity as the course progresses
There will also be a final competition at the end of the course to determine an overall winner
and if you like you'll be able to enter your player into next year's international general game playing competition
One requirement for this all to work is that our webpages and our code must run on your computer
Webpages work in most browsers or at least with Safari, Chrome and Firefox
The Java codebase and the parametric player are fairly portable and run on most machines
If you encounter problems we can provide some support, however with a course this large it's not possible to provide individual service for everyone
There are instructions on the website on how to test your browsers and how to download and test the codebase
You should follow these instructions right upfront so you can determine early whether or not the web pages and code are compatible with your system
One frequently asked question is whether you're permitted to collaborate with others in building your general game players
The answer is a resounding yes, in fact it's pedagogically valuable for you to work with others in building your players
If you do form a team we ask only that identify your teammates so that we know you're all working on the same player
And if you do form a team, you'll get the same grade on all problems that test your player
In any case, whether you work alone or in a team one of the first things you need to do is to invent a unique and hopefully interesting name for your player
Anything goes as long as it's a sequence of ASCII characters restricted to letters, numbers and the underscore character
Here are some examples of names used in the past, of course there are the winners of the international competition but there are many more
Here are some: djava_unchained, red_hot_chili_peppers, resolutionaries, michael_genesereth
And no that was not mine but some students have figured that I would not want to see that particular player loose
And so forth, be creative but be careful: once you pick a net player name you're stuck with it for the duration of the course
Your score for the course as a whole will be based on your performance on the weekly problems, the programming assignments and the performance of your player in the final competition at the end of the course
We will issue certificates of completion for all students who atteign an overall score of 70% on these components
Let me close with a plea for patience on your part: although we've taught this course many times in the classroom this is the first time we're offering it online
And it's the first time we're it to so many students at once
We think we've worked out all the kinks in the system but as we go along we may encounter some problems
Please use the forum to let us know of any problems you encounter and suggest solutions if you can
And please if you can be patient with us as we work through any problems that arise
Okay that's it for this introduction, as soon as you're ready click on the video link for the first lesson and get started !