So now we have seen how the reachability
analysis performed in the planning graph
can be used to compute some simple
heuristics.
But the problem with a star that remains
is that it uses exponential memory.
And to address this problem, another
algorithm has been developed, which I
won't introduce here, which is called
Iterative Deepening A star.
This algorithm is also very good, and
specifically it uses only very little
memory.
In fact, it uses so little memory that
most of the computers memory remains
unused.
And that led to the question, can't we do
anything useful with this memory that aids
our search?
And the idea is to compute pattern
databases in advance of our search that we
can use to compute heuristics.
I will now use the 8 puzzle to illustrate
the basic idea behind pattern databases.
In the 8 puzzle, we were given a
configuration of times on a 3 by 3 grid,
and we have to achieve a specific other
configuration by shifting the tiles
around.
There were eight tiles and they were
numbered one through eight, and one way to
simplify this problem is simply to remove
the numbers from some of the tiles.
So we see some of these tiles are marked
with a star now.
And we've marked the same tiles with a
star in our solution.
What this means is, we still have to get
the tiles one through four into the
correct positions.
But, we can't tell where the other tiles
are as long a there are tiles with a star
those are in a correct place and therefore
form a solution.
It should be clear that this problem is
simpler than the original problem.
In fact, it's a subproblem of the original
problem because we only need to achieve a
subconfiguration.
But, what is important here is that the
cost of solving the subproblem, the one
where the tiles are marked with a star, is
less or equal to the cost of solving the
complete problem.
So, the original problem we are trying to
solve.
And if that is the case, that means we can
use the cost of solving the subproblem as
an admissible heuristic for the cost of
solving the overall problem.
The problem remains to solve the
subproblem, we still need to do search.
It will be in a smaller search space, but
in general, search is expensive, and we
want to avoid this.
And here is the idea that helps us avoid
search during the computation of the
heuristic.
What we want to do is we want to
pre-compute and store in a database all
the solution costs for all possible
subproblems that we may encounter.
Clearly, this will take up quite some
memory but that was the idea that we want
to make use of the memory that we have.
Once we have got this database, computing
the heuristic is simply a database
look-up, so it should be possible in
constant time, very fast.
Then, the only question that remains is,
how we can construct this database that we
want to use as a heuristic?
And the basic idea is that we search
backwards in a breadth-first fashion from
the goal state and record the costs of
each of the states as we come across them.
So, because we've searched breadth-first,
we know that the first time we encounter a
node we encounter a minimal depth.
And we can just record the depth in our
database as its heuristic value.
Now, what we've done is shifted the search
operation from the time when we need to
compute the heuristic to before we try to
solve a problem, but the search we're
doing is now a breadth first search, and
that is a very expensive operation because
we need to search the whole search space
in this way, or generate the search space.
The good news is we only need to compute
this once so we pre-compute our pattern
database once, and then we can solve many
problems with the same database.
The next question is, how do we choose the
patterns that we want to record in our
database?
And the answer here is that we start from
the available amount of memory that we
have.
So, we take all of the memory.
We compute how much memory we will need
for search, maybe very little, and the
remainder is how much memory we have for
our pattern database.
And then, we know that if our original
search space had the size, size of S, then
our new search space depends on how much
tiles in the search space we mark with a
star, and that is, let's say, that's the
number n, then we can say that the new
search space has the size of the old
search space divided by n factorial,
because all the permutations of the tiles
marked with a star do not matter.
So, that's roughly the size of the table
we'll generate.
And for each element we need to store the
state, plus a single number that gives us
our heuristic value.
Of course, there is no point in doing this
for the 8 puzzle because the whole search
space of the 8 puzzle already fits into
memory.
So, we don't need to store a pattern
database, we can store the database of all
solutions.
But, for bigger version of the same
puzzle, for example, the 15 puzzle shown
here or even bigger the 24 puzzle, this
does make sense.
So, what we see here is an approach to
choosing the patterns of what we are
looking for and if we try to find a clever
heuristic what we want to do is explore
it's symmetry in this space so.
If we define the pattern consisting of
those tiles here, then we can also rotate
the puzzle and use them here, and here,
and here.
So, the same database can be used to
compute different values for the
heuristic.
And we can simply take the maximum of all
these.
Because we must get all the tiles that
match our patterns into the right
positions.
But you can easily see that the patterns
that we're now checking, are actually
overlapping.
And that's one of the reasons why we have
to take the maximum of all the heuristic
values here, because this pattern and the
next count the same four tiles in the
heuristic value.
And I've just given you the answer to the
first question on this slide which is, can
we add the values instead of taking the
maximum?
And the answer is, no, because the
patterns overlap and that would be
counting the same moves twice in computing
the heuristic.
But there is a way to avoid this problem.
And the first step toward the solution is
to choose the pattern in such a way that
when we exploit the symmetry, we don't
have overlapping patterns and we don't
count the same times twice.
And an approach For this, for the
24-puzzle is shown here.
You can see a pattern that we're choosing,
these six tiles and if we turn this
pattern or the puzzle under it then we get
a different area of the puzzle that does
not overlap with our original pattern.
So, that's half the solution and the other
half is when we record a value in our
database all we have to count is the
non-star tile moves.
So, we only count the ones in the pattern
and not the stars.
Because the stars would appear in other
patterns as well and we don't want to
count them twice.
If we do that, if we choose the patterns
to exploit the symmetry non-overlapping
and don't count the start tiles when we
compute our heuristic, then we can
actually add the different values to get
an admissible heuristic out of our
database.
And this approach is called a Disjoint
Pattern Database because the patterns are
disjoint and we can add the values of the
heuristic.
Unfortunately, it's not always possible to
find disjoint pattern databases that work.
One example where this hasn't been found
yet is the Rubik's Cube.
But where these heuristics exist, for
example in the 24 puzzle, they seem to be
the best heuristics around at present.
Now, we have seen how we can use pattern
databases to generate heuristics for a
specific problem.
The question now is, can we generalize
this approach to generate heuristics for
arbitrary planning problems?
Remember, planning problems are given to
us as an initial state, a goal and a set
of operators.
So, it's very hard to see what a generic
pattern could look like.
But the key idea for generating pattern
databases for the 8 puzzle or for generic
planning problems is the same.
We need to construct abstract problem
spaces.
For the eighth puzzle, we've abstracted
away the names of some tiles.
And for generic planning problems, we're
going to do something similar, we're going
to drop some of the detail from the
problem description to create a more
abstract problem.
Then, we're going to solve this more
abstract problem, and the solution length
for the solution to the more abstract
problem, is a heuristic for our original
problem.
So, the most important question then is,
how do we create this more abstract
problem?
And the answer is actually quite simple.
What we do is, we pick some of the
proposition symbols that we have in our
propositional planning problem.
So, these are some of the symbols that
describe aspects of the state.
And out of the complete set of state
propositions that we have available, we
pick some and drop them from the problem
description.
So we drop them from the goals, from the
initial state, and from the pre-conditions
and the effects of all the operators.
And this gives us a more abstract problem.
This is really all there is to our new
abstract problem space.
We drop state propositions from the
problem description.
Now, the question that remains is, which
state proposition symbols should we drop
from our problem description.
And the way we do this determines the
quality of our heuristic.
And one way to do this, works as follows.
We divide the set of all state
propositions that we have into mutually
exclusive, and therefore disjoined,
groups, G 1 though G K.
So, in each group, we find symbols that
are mutually exclusive, meaning they can't
be true in the same state.
So, in our Dock Worker Robot example, the
symbols r1 and r2, the robots at location
one and at location two are mutually
exclusive and therefore could be in the
same group.
Now, we may have quite a lot of groups
which means our abstract problem spaces
may be too abstract.
They may be trivial to solve and the
heuristic information it reveals is almost
nothing.
So, what we do is we divide this into just
two sets of symbols, namely those that are
in even numbered groups, and those that
are in odd numbered groups.
That effectively gives us two abstract
problem spaces.
So, what we do is simply modify the goal
by taking, on the one hand the goals from
the even groups, and on the other the
goals from the odd groups.
And similarly, for the operators, we
intersect their preconditions and effects
with the corresponding groups.
This gives us our abstract problem spaces
and now, we can construct our pattern
databases.
We pre-compute them as we did for the 8
puzzle, that's how pattern databases can
be used for arbitrary planning problems.
And the result that we get from this is a
heuristic that computes in constant time
because it's just a hash table look-up.
And also the pattern database that we get
with this approach is disjoint.
So, we can add the two values that we get
from the even and odd groups.
The pattern database is, of course, still
slow to compute, but reusable so we can
use the same database to solve multiple
problems.
But again, the re-usability of this
database is quite limited.
Because we can not change the goal, or for
example, increase the number of containers
that we have in our Dock Worker Robot
domain.
For that, we would have to generate a new
pattern database.