>> As you have just seen, there's nothing
too difficult about the propositional
representation.
So, we can now turn to the data structure
that is maintained by the graph plan
algorithm and that is the so-called
planning graph.
I will first describe a basic version of
this data structure which does not contain
mutex relations.
I will define those later as you can see
here.
To understand the properties that the
planning graph represents, I want to
remind you of a proposition we have seen
earlier.
And that was about solution existence to
planning problems.
And this was the proposition I want to
remind you of.
So if we are given a planning problem
consisting of a state transition system,
an initial state and a goal, we can say
that this planning problem has a solution,
if and only if the following condition
holds.
And the condition is that the set of all
possible goal states, intersected with
this set here must not be empty.
And this set really represents all the
states that are reachable from the initial
state.
We also had a similar proposition from the
regression of states, but that's not what
I wanted to remind you of here.
It's the first proposition that I want to
have a closer look at.
This states that if a planning problem has
a solution, then there must be a reachable
goal state.
Now our goal condition, g, actually
consists of a set of subgoals that we're
trying to achieve, let's call them g1
through gn here.
Now, a corollary of our original
proposition is that each of these
individual subgoals must be true in some
reachable state.
It is, of course, trivially true because
they will all be true in the reachable
goal state.
But I can also turn this around now.
Now, suppose I could show that there's one
goal condition in here that cannot be
achieved.
So, one of the goal conditions is not
reachable.
If I can show that one of the goal
conditions isn't reachable, then that
means there can be no state in which this
goal condition is true, which means there
can be no state that constitutes a
solution.
So the planning problem does not have a
And that is exactly the kind of inside
that the planning graph will give us.
Of course, what we have done in our
forward tree search algorithm is
constructed effectively a reachability
tree.
In this tree, our root node was the
initial state, si, that was given as part
of the problem.
And for each node, s, we have the children
of the node, s, be gamma of s.
So that's the immediate successors of that
state s in this set here.
And then, we have the arcs labelled with
the actions that correspond to the state
transitions.
That is the tree we constructed in forward
search.
Now, in this tree, if we constructed the
complete tree, are all the nodes that are
reachable from our initial state.
So this is a complete reachability tree
for our planning problem.
Or if we gave a depth limit to our tree,
so suppose we only go to depth d, then we
would have gamma d of si in this
reachability tree.
So, another complete tree but all the
nodes that are reachable in d steps.
And in this tree, of course, we can find
all the solutions to problems that require
up to d actions in their solution.
Now, we could of course, use this tree to
check whether each of the individual goal
conditions is true in some state rather
than all in the same.
And then, use our criterion just
introduced to see whether the planning
problem has a solution.
But that is, of course, not an efficient
way of solving planning problems.
As we know that even a tree of depth d has
an expectational nodes in it.
Here, k is the number of applicable
actions per state, and d is the depth, so
have k to the d nodes in general in such a
tree.
But there is a more clever solution to
this reachability question as we will see
next.
I will now describe to you the planning
graph which is the fundamental data
structure maintained by the graph plan
algorithm.
And I will start by describing what nodes
are contained in this graph.
So, the planning graph is a layered
directed graph, G, consisting of nodes and
edges, and that means that the edges are
directed.
So they go from one node to another, only
unidirectional.
And the graph is layered, which means the
nodes in the graph can be divided into
disjoined sets and each of these sets is
called a layer.
So, if we look at the nodes, N, contained
in the graph, they consist of the layers
P0, A1, P1, A2 and so on.
These are our layers in the graph
containing the nodes.
And we distinguish two types of layers we
have in our graph.
Firstly, there are the state proposition
layers denoted by symbols with a P, P0,
P1, etc.
And then, we have the action layers
denoted by the symbol A, A1, A2, etc.
And these types of layers alternate in the
graph.
So, we start of with a proposition layer,
P0, followed by an action layer, followed
by a proposition layer, followed by an
action layer, followed by proposition
layer, etc.
So, they alternate in the graph, and the
first layer, P0, is a proposition layer.
So, let's have a look at the nodes we find
in the first proposition layer, P0.
In the first proposition layer, we have a
node for each proposition that was true in
the initial state.
So si, our initial state, is a set of
proposition symbols, and in P0, we have a
node for each of these proposition
symbols.
And given this definition of P0, we can
now define what nodes we find in the
action layer Aj.
So that's not just the action layer A1,
but in general the action layer Aj, which
follows the proposition layer Pj minus 1.
And effectively, we have in this action
layer all the action symbols that
represent actions that would be applicable
in the preceding proposition layer.
So, what we do is we look at our preceding
proposition layer, Pj minus 1.
And we interpret this as a state.
Remember, the nodes in this layer will be
proposition symbols.
So we can simply form a set of all these
nodes and interpret this as a state.
Usually, this won't be a meaningful state
as it may contain symbols that can never
be true at the same time.
For example, that the robot r is at
location 1, and that the robot r is at
location 2.
But never mind that now.
So, we interpret this proposition layer as
a state, and then add to the successive
action layer, all those actions whose
preconditions are satisfied in that state.
Now, we know what P0 contains, and what
the j action layer contains.
We can now define the proposition layer,
Pj, where j, of course, has to be greater
than zero because we've already defined
P0.
And in Pj, we find nodes for all those
proposition symbols that were already in
Pj minus 1.
So, all the propositions that were in the
previous proposition layer are also in
this proposition layer.
But there may also be additional nodes
that were not in the previous proposition
layers.
And what we do to find these nodes is we
take all the positive effects of all the
actions in the preceding action layer.
So Aj is the preceding action layer.
We take all those actions and we look at
their positive effect.
And we add a proposition node for each
proposition that is a positive effect to
layer Pj.
So in Pj, we have all the propositions
from the previous proposition layer, plus
all the positive effects from the previous
action layer.
Note that we ignore the negative effects
of the action here, so we only look at the
positive effects.
We do not remove the negative effects from
any layer ever.
An interesting observation here is that
the layers must be monotonically
increasing from proposition layer to
proposition layer, and from action layer
to action layer.
So, for proposition layers, this is quite
easy to see.
We always take over the propositions from
one layer to the next, and possibly add
new propositions to that next proposition
layer.
So, it must be monotonically increasing.
The action layers must also monotonically
increasing.
Because if an action is applicable in one
action layer, then it must also be
applicable in the next action layer
because all the pre-conditions that were
true here must be true in the next
proposition layer, so they must still be
true for the next action layer.
So, proposition layers and action layers
are monotonically increasing.
So, now that we have seen the nodes that
exist in the planning graph, we can look
at the edges between nodes, or because
it's a directed graph, I like to call them
arcs.
So, the first set of arcs we have all go
from proposition layer Pj to action layer
Aj.
That is, the action layer that follows it.
And they go from a node in this layer,
which is a proposition, to an action in
the following layer, if the proposition P
is a precondition of that action.
Similarly, we have arcs from the action
layer Aj, to the proposition layer Pj.
That's the proposition layer that follows
the action layer.
And we have an arc from action A, in this
layer, to a proposition P in the following
layer, if either P is a positive effect of
that action, or P is a negative effect of
that action.
In other words, each action in an action
layer Aj is connected to its preconditions
and its effects.
And it's connected to the preconditions in
the preceding proposition layer and to its
effects in the following proposition
layer.
And these are all the arcs that exist
between different layers.
So, there are no arcs between other
layers.
Arcs only go from one proposition layer,
to the following action layer.
And one, from one action layer, to the
following proposition layer.
They don't go between other layers.
Now, I should mention that these edges
aren't all the edges that exist in the
planning graph.
There are other edges.
But these edges are strictly internal to
the layers and we will look at them later.