Next section is evaluating limits.
So I'll start off by just pointing out
working with the definition is not very
fun.
So luckily there are a lot of rules that
you can use.
I'm just pretty much here just going to
try and list them off.
These slides are more meant to be a
reference.
you probably would be able to find these
know, I, I just Google for stuff most of
the time.
but, it would be in the first year
calculus text book.
That I think that's where I found most of
these rules.
So, I'm going to suppose that C is a real
valued constant.
And that the limits, as X goes to A of F
of X.
And as X goes to A of G of X, both exist.
So, they don't necessarily need to be
finite, but they
need to be something that I can make sense
of.
So they can't be 0 divided by 0.
Infinity divided by 0.
Infinity divided by infinity, things like
that.
Then, so we have a linearity property.
So if I have a function that I can see is,
you
know, made up of two sub functions, so f
of x plus
g of x, and I'm looking at the limit of
that, and
the limit of a sum is equal to the sum of
the limits.
Similarly if I scale my function, so here
my function is f of x, I'm going to
multiply that by my constant c, so c could
be anything.
It could, if I want to double function it
would be to 2 f of x and so on.
the limit as x goes to a of c times f of
x.
Is just c times the limit of oops, c times
the limit of f of
x as x goes to a.
So I think most of these are pretty
intuitive, but they are all things that
are proved in
a calculus textbook so, you know, you can
use them.
The limit of a product, the limit as X
goes to A of F
of X times G of X is equal to the product
of the limit.
So, here I have the limit of F of X as X
goes to A and the limit of G of X as X
goes
to A.
And I'm going to multiply those two
numbers
together and that's going to be the same
as
the limit of the product of these
functions going when as x goes to a.
also works for rational functions.
So,
the limit as x goes to a of f of x divided
by g of x is just going
to be equal to the limit of f of x divided
by the limit.
Of g of x as x goes to a, we have to make
one, one little copy it here
So the, oops, so the limit as x goes to a
of g of x can't be equal to 0.
And then finally
So here this little
thing here is an n.
So if it was square root, that would be a
two, three would be a cube root and so on.
And then if P(x) and Q(x) are polynomials
and
c is a real constant that's greater than
one.
So by, by polynomial I just mean this is
equal to
something like P(x) would be ax squared
plus bx plus c.
but it can be arbitrarily large orders, so
you know
the first one could be x to the thousand
or something
like that.
Then the limit as X goes to infinity of
any polynomial divided by c to the x.
And I could also write that as the limit
of any polynomial
times c to the negative x is going to be
equal to 0.
So it doesn't matter how big the order of
this polynomial is.
Even if I have x to the thousandth, if I'm
dividing it by a constant
raise to some power.
That's eventually
going to go to 0.
And then kind of a, a similar result If I
take the log of the absolute value -- so I
need the absolute value just because of
how log is defined know, it's not going to
work very well if I give it a negative
number.
the log of any polynomial divided
by any polynomial.
If I take the limit as x goes to infinity,
that's also going to be 0.
And so, just some, some examples.
If I had x squared times e to the minus x.
Now x squared is something that would grow
arbitrarily large as x goes to infinity,
but
e to the minus x is something that's
going to be getting smaller as x goes to
infinity.
But, because this, this part of the
product has the
x in the exponent, but here, it's in the
base,
this term is going to dominate and so the,
the limit is going to go to 0.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then as an example of, of the second
result if I have the log of x cubed
and here the cubed doesn't really matter.
I put any power here.
I could put 1,000, 10,000.
Eventually, as x goes, you know, as x gets
large, as x goes to infinity, this
x in the denominator is going to dominate
because of the logarithm on the top here.
And this limit
will go to 0.
And I'm going to add a little bit more
notation.
So If I instead of using my arrow, my goes
to arrow, as just a horizontal
arrow, so that means goes to a value but I
don't care how I get there.
I just have to be getting closer.
But I could be bouncing from side to side
if I wanted to, to get there.
If I use this down arrow, I'm going to
mean that x goes to 0.
With X
always being greater then 0 so it can
bounce around a little bit but I'm
starting
only on one side of the value and
moving towards my limiting point from only
one side.
And also just encase you never seen this
notation before the K followed by
a exclamation point is read K factorial
and it just means k times k minus1.
Sorry, it's defined for integer values,
positive integer
values of k.
It means k times k minus 1 times k minus 2
and so on, times two, times one.
And then one factorial and zero factorial
are both equal to one.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then again, we'll, let's see the
positive constant.
Then if I look at C to the 1 over X, so,
you can sort of think of, kind of
intuitively what's going to happen here.
1 over X as X gets large is going to get
closer and closer to 0.
And c to a 0 should be anything to the 0.
Power should be 1.
So it makes sense that this this function,
it's limit should be going to 1.
also x to the
1 over x.
So even if my base is getting bigger
linearly.
The limit of this as x goes to inifity is
still going to be equal to one.
And then if x goes down to 0, x to the x
power, this limit is also equal to one.
[COUGH]
If k is a positive integer, and if c is
greater than
0, or if c is greater than 0 is a positive
constant, then
k to the 1 over k, so this is just a the
same
thing as a in the second bullet point just
re expressed using integers.
So the only difference between the, the
second set and
the top set is just now I'm sort of
restricting k
to be integer values, so it makes sense
that we would
get the same, same sort of result that we
got above.
And then al so what this is
telling us is this factorial
function defined here,
this is getting big very quickly.
It's getting bigger faster.
Then a constant to an exponentail power.
So, you know, our previous record holder
for how could something get big fast was
this exponential function.
But that's dominated by this factorial.
So somehow this factorial's growing even
faster than that.
So I have two examples in the slides.
I'll just go through the first one and
then the second one you can take a
look at one your own because I need to
speed up this session a little bit.
So I want to evaluate this limit 1 over
the square root of x squared
minus 4x plus 1 and then minus x.
And so basically the
strategy you use to evaluate a limit like
this you want to get the square root out
of the, out of the denominator.
So the first step I'm going to take.
If I have minus X here And
then I'm going to get minus X,
oops, minus X times this
square root and then
also, oops, plus X
times that square root.
So I've got minus something plus the same
thing and they're going to cancel each
other out.
And then in the last bit, I'll have minus
x times postive X.
So that's going to give me a minus x
squared.
And then I'll pick, pick up this thing in
the numerator of, of my fraction.
And now I have x squared minus x xquared.
So get rid of that.
Oops, I was supposed to put a little pause
here.
So on the bottom I just have the plus 1
minus 4x, and to help me make a little bit
of
sense out of that, what I'm going to do is
just
multiply the top and the bottom by 1
divided by x.
And that's a safe thing to do, because I'm
looking at the limit as x goes to
infinity.
So infinity is a long way from 0, and
the only time I would have trouble
dividing something
by x, is when x is equal to 0.
And so this 1 over x is going to get
multiplied by x here, and then
it's going to show up as a 1 over x
squared under this square root sign.
So what I end up with is the x squared,
square root of x
squared, or x squared times 1 over x
squared, that gives me the 1.
The minus 4x becomes 4 divided by
x, and then the positive 1 becomes 1 over,
1 over x squared.
And then my x gets multiplied by one over
x, just give me a one.
And then in the denominator I get a one
over x and a minus 4.
And now what I'm going to do, this is sort
of
two steps in one.
So, I can take
this limit And because this is a rational
function
Ii can put the limit on the top and
bottom.
And then also because I have the square
root
I can put this limit inside my square root
sign.
And then it should be pretty clear what's
going to happen.
When I look at this as x gets bigger, 1
over x squared is going get very small.
4 over x is going to get very small,
but this 1 is always going to stay the
same.
So this is going to become 1, square root
of 1.
And on the bottom, my 1 over x is going to
get very
small, but my negative 4 is always going
to stay the same.
So I'm going to get 1 plus 1 divided
by negative 4, which is equal to negative
1/2.
And then just this
is almost exactly the same example so,
here I had minus x.
Oops, which I can't seem to select for
some reason.
Here I have minus x plus 2.
But if you go through that and I'm doing
exactly the same trick in
this case just by adding this little plus
two here has made the value of
the limit divergent now.
So it goes to minus infinity.