So now I'm going to look at something
called bond duration.
This is just meant to be a little bit more
involved example of taking a derivative.
So a price of a bond is given by a
following formula.
so P oops P is the price of the bond.
And if you look at this it looks a lot
like what we talked about on tuesday for
present value.
And so what basically the way a bond works
is or
at least the one that I've written down
the formula for.
It has a face value, so let's just pretend
that's $100.
And it has coupon payments, and that's
going to make n coupon payments.
And so the agreement I'm going to enter
into with somebody
is, I sell them the bond.
So they end up with a piece of paper.
I end up with $100.
And then every year.
So this is, this is sort of set up for
yearly coupon payments.
I'm going, let's see, I have the 100
dollars, they have the bond.
I'm gong to pay them the coupon payment.
So that might be say, 5 dollars.
So
I'm borrowing their money, and the price
of doing that
is that I have to give them 5 dollars
every year.
And after N payments, I have to give them
5 dollars, plus their money back.
So they get their 100 dollars back.
So, all I'm doing to calculate the price
of my bond.
So I'm taking the face value, and I'm
discounting that N periods.
And then I'm taking this stream
of coupon payments And I'm cou, I'm
discounting the first coupon payment
for one year; I'm discounting the second
coupon payment for two years.
Looks like I might have forgotten some
parentheses
around this, but it's better on this side.
yeah.
And so it's essentially just it's the same
rules
that we had before for doing present value
calculation.
Just applied to this slightly more
complicated payment
scheme of a bond which is what we
did with the annuity plus you're going to
get the, the face value of the bond back.
So c is a coupon payment, n is the number
of periods remaining, f is the face value
and then this value lambda, which is sort
of playing the role of the interest rate
from our last calculations.
For bonds it's called yield to maturity.
So, I'm going to
make just a small change to that.
And instead of calling
the coupon payments capital C, and having
them all be the same, I'm going to say
C sub little k.
And the only real reason I want to do this
is now I can just say that the.
All of the short term ones.
So, you know, one up to n minus one are
all of, sorry not short term but only
coupon payments one.
Those are all going to be the same c and
then the
last one is just going to be the coupon
plus the face value.
And so that's going to give me my present
value for whatever payment I'm going to
receive in the
[UNKNOWN]
period.
So now I can rewrite my, my bond pretty
much using the same formula we had last
time except that instead of having a
constant value, so I think I called
it A last time, I now have something that
can be different every time but for
this particular type of bond it's going to
be the same for N minus one periods.
And then the last one is just going to be
face value plus coupon payment.
And then I have to divide them by
1 plus the yield to maturity to the case
power, because
I need to discount money that I'm going to
receive in the future.
The duration of a bond is a weighted
average Of
the time that these payments are going to
be made.
So I'm going to define, the weights as the
present value of the payment received
in period k, divided by the price, and
then I'm going to multiply that by k.
And so k is just the index here, it's
going from one up to
n, so this is going to be You know, pv1
divided by p.
So that's weight 1 times 1.
Pv2 divided by p is going to be weight 2.
So it'll be weight 2 times 2 plus weight 3
times 3 and so on up to n.
And when I sum all of those things up, I'm
going to call that D, which is duration.
And if you think about this, what are the
units of PVK.
It's a present value of something, so it's
going to be made in dollars.
>>
[INAUDIBLE]
present value, of the
made in PDK?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> And then P is just the sum of all of
them.
>> OKAY.
>> That's the price of the bond today.
>> Yeah.
And so, what's going to end up happening
here is, present value is measured in
dollars.
The price of the bond is also measured in
So when I do this division, I have
something
measured in dollars divided by something
measured in dollars.
So, I get a unit less quantity.
And, K, this is going to be dates.
So, K is actually, has some sort of units
in time.
So, the way I've written this down, this
is for yearly coupon
payment So k is going to be one year, two
years, three years, four years.
So kind of interestingly
this quantity duration is measured in
years.
And I guess that will sort of seem a
little bit more strange
once we see how duration's going to get
used in this bond pricing formula.
And so then another thing I can do is just
take this P
out the denominator here and put it on the
left side of the equation.
And I'm just doing this because this sum
of K times PVK
is going to be something that falls out of
a calculation later.
And I'm going to want to be able to
replace that with duration times price.
Yep.
>> I'm confused
why we're waiting payments further into
the future more heavily.
>> the present value of something in the
future is going to be less.
>>
[CROSSTALK]
Less.
Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> so, is that
[UNKNOWN]
undo that to get the price.
I mean here it's not really clear.
>> Why someone tried to do this in the
first place.
I think, as we go forward you're going to
see that this
sort of pops out as a useful quantity in,
in the equations.
And so I guess yeah, next bullet point.
So, sensitivity, Is suppose that this
yield to maturity rate changes.
What's going to happen to the value of the
bond?
So I'm asking said, that's a sensitivity
if, if that rate
changes a little and there's a big change
in the price, we're
going to say that's highly sensitive and
if the rate changes
and the price stays pretty much the same,
then that's low sensitivity.
So the present value of the payment
received in period k, so here
Ck is the nominal payment so that's, you
know, the $5 or the $105.
So I, in period n I'm going to get a
hundred and five dollars.
And every other period I'm going to get
five dollars.
And then this number in the bottom is
going to be bigger than one.
So the present value of that's going be
getting smaller.
And so I can write that as Ck.
Times 1 plus Lambda to the minus K.
So, I'm basically just taking this out of
the denominator, and writing it like this.
So, I've always been doing this when I
want to take a
derivative, so I'm just setting myself up
to use the Power Rule here.
So now, if I want to take the derivative
of the present value of the Kth
payment, with respect to Lambda Well it
should
be pretty straightforward, the power rule
of linearity.
And then you have to be a bit careful
because the chain rule
comes into play here too because I
actually have a function of a function.
But luckily the derivative of this inside
function is one.
So that's a time where you can forget the
chain rule and
still get the right answer.
not a very safe habit.
So this just becomes minus k times C sub
k,
my argument here and then minus k minus 1.
So that's just a, the power rule to take
the derivative.
And
then I can rewrite it like this.
So that's sort of just undoing this
negative exponent trick.
And minus k minus 1 is the same as the
quantity k plus 1 times negative 1.
So that's why we get a power of k plus 1
down here.
And now if you look carefully at this, we
have C sub k divided
by one plus lambda to the k.
But that was just Where is it?
Right here.
Our definition of PVK.
And then I have this plus 1 down here,
which
gives me 1 extra 1 plus lambda in the
denominator.
And I have a minus k in
the numerator.
So I end up with minus k over 1
plus lambda times the present value of the
kth payment.
And now let's look at, the price.
So my goal was to figure out what's the
sensity of sensitivity of the price not
just each payment.
So if I want to take the derivative of
that with
respect to lambda I'm going to take the
derivative so
my definition for the price was just the
present value of this future stream of
payments.
And by my linearity property of
derivatives,
I can move this derivative inside the sum.
So, the derivative of a sum is the sum of
the derivatives.
And we've already computed this.
This is what I just did on the last slide,
the derivative
of the present value of decay of payment
divided with respect to lambda.
And so I'm just going to plug my formula
from the previous slide in here.
And I get this guy.
And
now if you look at that, remember what did
we say duration was?
Duration was k times pvk Summed up.
So what I'm going to do is take the
negative one
and the divided one plus lambda out in
front of the sum.
And then I'm left with just the sum of k
times pvk
which is this quanitty duration.
That just sort of falls out of us taking
the derivative.
And this, this quantity here, so negative
1 divided
1 plus Lambda times the duration, is
called, oops.
Not the negative, everything but the
negative.
There.
Is called Modified Duration.
And so the sensitivity, the rate of change
of the price, with
respect to the, you can think of this as
the interest rate.
Is equal to minus the modified duration
times the price.
M'kay, yeah, so dm is modified duration.
And so, this is what we've found now.
That the derivative of the price which
repsect to the yield
to maturity, is the negative of the
modified duration times the price.
And I'm going to make one more Little
substitution here, so since the price
it's obviously going to be non zero, I can
divide both sides by price.
And now I have the change in price, with
respect to
a change in the yield to maturity, divided
by the price.
So the change in price, That's going to be
something that's measured in dollars.
So if the price changes from $100 down to
$180, The change
in price was negative $20.
If I divide that by the price, now I have
some sort of rate.
So, it doesn't matter what the price was.
If it, if it went from 100 down to 80 or
if it went
from 1,000 down to 800, this thing on the
left is going to be the same.
And so, that's going to be our
interpretation.
For the
modified duration.
So it's going to give us some measure of
the relative
change in price as the yield to maturity
is changing.
And kind of in summary, duration then
which is something measured in years.
Is a measure of interest rate sensitivity.
Yes?
>>
[INAUDIBLE]
sensitivity will price things, will price
change
[INAUDIBLE].
>> You mean like that?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> the other question is.
>> M'kay, and so
essentially all we've, we've done here is,
we've just figured out what this
curve.
So this is that curve in the price-yield
[UNKNOWN]
space, so it's called a "price-yield
curve." And I've calculated the
derivitives,
so it's just going to be the slope of this
tangent line.
And so then, one of the, one of the main
things
you're going to use a derivative for, when
you can find a
tangent line like this is if you, if you
look at
this, maybe between about eight percent
and maybe twelve or thirteen percent.
This tangent line is very, very close to
the actual curve,
and it's going to be easy to evaluate
points along
the tangent line because it's just a
linear function.
It actually can be quite difficult
especially, you know, when people were
trying
to do these computations before you had
computers, to evaluate points along this
curve.
So one of the ideas of doing this, this
approximation and finding the tangent line
is it gives us a good way to make local
approximations to our function value.
And you can actually improve this so.
What we've done here, is just the first
order of approximation.
What we're trying to approximate this
function
with a linera function so a tangenr line.
You can use convexity, which is sort of
how quickly
the second derivative so the size of the
second derivative.
It's sort of how quickly this curve is
changing slope.
And that allows us to make an even better
approximation.
And we'll, we'll come to that, in the, the
second half of this course.
So after the midterm.
Okay.
So just a quick summary.
This is a formula for duration.
You can also multiply the price on the
left hand side and get this k times PVk.
Modified duration is just one divided by
one plus lambda times duration.
And then the price sensitivity formula is,
so
the, the rate of change of the price with
respect to a change in in interest rate.
Is minus the modified duration times the
price.
[BLANK_AUDIO]