Hi I'm David Wilkins I'm a Senior
Computer Scientist at SRI International's
Artificial Intelligence Center.
SRI is a not for profit contract research
institute in Silicone Valley.
I got my PhD in Stanford in 1979.
My adviser was John McCarthy, who taught
my first list class.
Immediately after graduating I moved
across to El Camino, to SRI's AI center.
Primarily because Nils Nilson was here
and I wanted to work with him, My first
boss at SRI was Earl Sacerdoti the author
of NOAH before NOAH AI planning was
generally search in a space space and
NOAH introduced search in a planned space
AI planning.
Inspired by Earl and NOAHI became
interested in solving real world planning
problems and found that this regard of
more domain knowledge and more expressive
representations.
I divide past research in AI findings in
two camps.
The first are systems that take a
minimalist approach to main knowledge,
they use strip style descriptions of
primitive actions, I call them primitive
action planners.
The second are the systems that focus on
leveraging as much domain knowledge as
possible.
I use this approach in developing the
sight planning system.
System.
On the first slide we'll see an example
of one of the domains that site and coded
for planning it's the response to oil
spills.
And in this picture we see several boats
deploying boom around an island to
protect it from an oil spill.
The key point here is that there multiple
boats executing this plan and that it's
important to have a sufficient amount of
boom to go around the island.
On the next slide, we'll see a number of
techniques I've developed to address real
world problems.
This list was driven by client needs to
solve their problems, not by any research
attempts.
Some of these techniques are now called
hierarchical task network planning in
SIPE known as an HTN planner.
The first technique is multiple
abstraction levels.
Many real problems have distinct natural
attraction levels making them natural
fits for HTN planning.
These levels are a powerful way to
control the search and they're a great
way to interact with humans because a
primitive action strip style plan at the
lowest level of detail can be very
difficult to understand.
Next item is parallel actions.
Realistic domains generally have parallel
agents executing activities at the same
time and these agents must coordinate
their activities.
Parallelism can cause computational
problems in AI planners and some AI
Planning systems produce only sequential
plans.
Next is context dependent effects which
are ubiquitous in real world problems.
For example if you move an object to a
new location all the objects attached to
it are on top of or moved with it.
So I could deduce these context-dependent
effects where as an strip style planner,
you would generally need a different
operative for every possible combination
of things that might be attached to the
block.
The next two items constraints and
resources come from the fact that
reasoning about numbers are essential to
almost every realistic domain.Time is a,
is certainly a key element in most plans.
Resources also have a specific capacity
or must be accumulated in, in certain
quantities.
An example of a goal in accumulation is
obtaining the boom in the previous
example a planner had to plan to obtain
enough boom to surround the island and it
had to reason about numbers to do that.
SIPE developed heuristics and
representations to efficiently reason
about actions which we needn't go into
detail here and the real world problems
plans never executed as expected so you
wanted to re-plan during execution to fix
the plan.
Many AI planners never address that
problem.
And finally, we found a need to have an
interactive graphical user interface.
SIPE had perhaps the most advanced GUI
and AI planning in the 80s and 90s.
Interacting with people is a critical
aspect of real-world planning.
Realistic problems are embedded in the
world and aren't precisely defined.
They have fuzzy edges.
The person almost always knows
information the planner doesn't and can
use that to help make good choices.
Another important reason to have the
Gooey is that it helps the user
understand the plan.
A large plan full of primitive actions
can be very difficult to understand.
And the ability to use the abstraction
levels and the Gooey and trail down and
see network displays is very crucial.
So in the next slide, we actually see a
screenshot capturing part of an oil spill
response plan from the site, Gooey.
We'll look at the top three nodes of this
plan.
And and the top right you see a Blue
oval.
Blue ovals represent primitive actions
that are already in the plan.
In this case the action is to deploy
3,000 feet of boom to the Berkeley
eelgrass at Time 3.
This spill was in the San Francisco bay.
Right before that is a aqua hexagon.
They represent goals that need to be
expanded at the next level of details.
This particular goal was to get this
3,000 feet of boom located at Berkley.
So look at the goal immediately below
this.
It turns out that the higher level goal
was to get 9,000 feet of Boom to Berkley.
SIPE new of 3,000 feet of Boom in some
locations so it split the goal into two.
The first one was to get to 3.000 feet
Feet there.
And parallel I posted another goal to get
the additional 6,000 feet of boom to
Berkely.
The entire plan for this oil spill
response had a few hundred notes when it
was complete.
And the next light I'll show you a brief
overview of how sight produces plans.
It has a representation of the state of
the world which you see on the left side
of the slide.
And that's for example where it
represents the fact that it knows that
there's 3,000 feet of boom in some
warehouse somewhere.
It then has operators that represent
actions, these are multiple levels of
extraction they represent Things about
how to transport boom and how to deploy
it when you have goals and objectives
you're trying to achieve.
The plan generator then combines these
and on the right side you see a depiction
of how it applies these operators level
after level to expand down to the most
primitive plan.
And when it finally gets a Plan composed
of primitive actions then it's ready for
execution and the plan executed will then
take over, and if we plan in as needed it
will cycle back and give some new goals
and give the new beliefs and constraints
that represent the world.
This concludes my description of the
motivations behind sipe.
For more information on the last slide,
there is a URL to the site homepage and
to my publication's homepage.
Thanks very much for your attention.
[MUSIC]