A partial plan is a solution for a given
planning problem if it contains no more
flaws.
So, our goal test will be to check
whether our partial plan is a flawless
partial plan.
Of course, we haven't defined a flaw yet
so that's what we will do next.
And when we have done this, the search
problem will be complete.
We have defined the initial state.
We have defined the successor function,
and we will now look at the goal test.
I will now introduce the concept of a
threat in a partial plan and I will use
an example to illustrate this.
What we see here is a partial plan to
which I've already added two actions to
support the two goal conditions.
We also the dummy action for the goal
over here.
And there should be a second dummy action
for the initial state.
But since we're not going to use that in
this example, I've left it out here to
save a little space.
Now, what we do is apply more plan
refinement operations.
In this case, we add an action to the
plan,
this new move action over here.
And the reason why we do this is because
we want to support the precondition at
robot location one with this new
operator.
So, we haven't started a cause link for
this, and we insert an ordering
constraint because the action that is the
provider must come before the consumer.
Now, let us also look at the condition
that are protected by the cause links.
These are at robot location two here the
not unloaded robot here the two goal
condition that we want to support.
And over here, it is the precondition of
the load operator that the robot must be
at location one that we're protecting
with this causal link.
Now, the problem is the following.
Our first operator, the move action, has
a negative effect at robot location one,
which is exactly the condition we're
trying to protect down here.
This means if we first executed action
number three, the move robot location to
location one.
Then, action number one moving the robot
from location one to location two, and
finally action number two loading the
container onto the robot with a crane,
etc.
Then, this plan would not be valid
because the second action in our totally
ordered plan will destroy the protected
condition that we need to execute the
final action in that plan.
So, the final action would no longer be
executable.
This is what is called the threat.
We have an action that may possibly occur
in parallel with a causal link and that
has an effect that is complementary to
the condition we're trying to protect in
the causal link.
That is what is called a threat.
And in this case, there is a simple way
to get rid of this threat, namely to
introduce another ordering constraint
that says, action number one must come
after action number two. In which case,
the action with the effect that is
potentially harmful cannot be in parallel
to the causal link that protects this
condition.
So, the insertion of the ordering
constraint removes the threat and that is
what is called a resolver for this
threat.
Now that you've seen an example of a
threat, here's the formal definition of
what constitutes a threat.
We start of with a plan pi consisting of
the four usual components.
We have actions, orderings, variable
bindings, and causal links.
In this plan, we have an action ak that
may cause a threat for a causal link,
That links an action ai to an action aj
protecting condition p.
And we say that the action ak threatens
our causal link if the following
preconditions hold.
Firstly, ak must have an effect, not q,
that is possibly inconsistent with p, the
condition we're trying to protect.
If p and q are ground, then of course,
they are possibly inconsistent if they
are the same.
But, if they contain variables, then they
are possibly inconsistent if p and q are
unfiable.
That means, they can be made the same if
we substitute values for variables.
The second condition is that the
following ordering constraints must be
consistent with the ordering constraints
in our plan.
And the ordering constraints that we
consider are ai could come before ak, and
ak before aj.
What this means is that our action ak can
possible be in parallel to the causal
link because the provider comes before ak
and the consumer comes after ak.
But, the condition here is, that this is
possible, not that it is necessarily so.
So, these orderings, constraints must be
consistent with our orderings in the
plan, but they need not be in the plan.
Similarly, the third condition states
that if we introduce new variable
bindings as part of our unification up
here, then, these new variable binding
constraints must be consistent with the
binding constraints that we currently
have in our Plan.
So, ak can threaten our causal link if it
has an effect that is possibly
inconsistent with the proposition we're
trying to protect.
And it may possibly occur in parallel to
our causal link.
And finally, the bindings that we need
for making p and w the same are
consistent with the bindings used in the
plan, that is the definition of a threat.
Threats however, are not the only types
of flaws that can occur in a plan.
The good news is there are only two types
of flaws we need to look out for.
So, in a plan pi, that consists of the
usual four components, we can have two
types of flaws.
The first is an unsatisfied sub-goal in
that plan.
And an unsatisfied sub-goal is a
precondition of an action that does not
have an incoming causal link that
supports it.
So, this could be the goal dummy action
which, of course, has all the goal
conditions as preconditions.
All of those need to be supported for the
plan not to have this type of flaw.
And then, every action that we have added
to the plan also must have all of its
preconditions supported by causal link
for the plan not to have this type of
flaw.
And the second type of flaw is a threat,
so that's what we have just seen in
action that may interfere with a causal
link.
And that's it. That's all the type flaws
we need to consider.
And here is the proposition that gives us
our goal test.
Suppose we are given a partial plan,
consisting of actions, orderings,
bindings, and links and we can say that
this solution to a planning problem
consisting of a state transition system,
initial state and goal, if three
conditions hold.
The first one is that the plan pi has no
flaw.
That's the two types of flaws we've just
described.
Then, the ordering constraints must not
be circular, so they must be consistent.
And the variable binding constraints must
also be consistent.
So, while we are doing our search for a
plan, we have these three conditions to
maintain.
The first one that a plan must have no
flaws, well, we cannot really have that
because initially our plan has flaws.
The goal has unsatisfied preconditions.
But, the other two conditions That we
keep up our ordering constraints and our
variable binding constraints consist in
these two conditions,
we maintain this consistency during the
planning process.
Why is that? Because once we introduce an
inconsistency into either set of
constraints, this can never be removed.
So, we maintain the consistency of the
constraints and try to remove the flaws
from the plan.
And once for all the flaws are gone,
we're done.
I won't go into the proof of this
proposition in detail,
but just tell you that this can be done
by induction quite easily.
So, we start off with the base case, that
is the empty plan.
And in the empty plan, the only causal
links can go from the innate action to
the goal action, the two dummy actions
that we have in this plan.
And if all the goal conditions are
supported from the initial state, that
must be a solution plan to our problem in
which case the goal was already satisfied
in our initial state.
And the induction step simply consist of
removing one action from the plan and
showing that the shorter plan now still
is a solution to a planning problem, the
modified planning problem.
And the action we pick here, as you can
see, is one of the actions in the plan
that has no predecessors.
So, this is it.
This is our goal test that completes the
planning problem.
And now, a goal test is that our plan
must not have flaws.
If it has no flaws, it is a solution
plan.