We have now, almost reached the end of
week two, and we have just seen our first
planning algorithm.
Some of you may be a little disappointed
that it took so long to get to the first
planning algorithm, and for those people
here comes the next planning algorithm.
In the algorithm we've just seen, search
states are exactly those states that are
world states in the planning problem.
States are sets of ground atoms.
The algorithm then searched forward from
the initial state through all the
reachable states, until it comes across a
goal state.
The algorithm we will look at next is
Backwards State-Space Search.
In this algorithm we'll start form the
goal, and search backwards through the
state space, until we reach the initial
state.
This is quite straight forward, and very
similar to forward search, as you will
see.
We will start by defining two concepts,
namely, relevance and regression sets.
Relevance is really the equivalent
concept to applicability, as it tells us
which actions we can use to move through
our search base.
Again, we start with a planning problem
consisting of the usual things.
Namely, a state transition system that
tells us how the world can evolve, a
initial state from which we're moving
away, and a goal description which tells
us which states are goal states.
Then we can say an action, A, of our
action set, is relevant for goal, G, if
the following two conditions hold.
Firstly the goal in intersected with the
affect of the action must not be empty.
This means they must be an element that
is in both sets, so there must be element
there is on the one hand go, and on the
other hand an infect of the action.
This means the action must contribute to
the goal in some way.
Secondly the positive goals of the goal
description and the negative effect of
the action must not intersect and the
negative goals and the positive effects
must also not intersect.
This means the goal must not conflict
with the effects of the action.
Looking at the first case, if we had a
negative effect of the action, that was
also a positive goal, that means this
action would delete this goal from our
state.
So it would no longer hold.
The second case is just the other way
around.
We have a positive effect that adds a
negative goal to the state, which we
don't want.
So, an action is relevant for a goal, if
it contributes to the goal,
that's the first condition.
And if it does not interfere with the
goal in a negative way.
That's the second condition.
Now we can define the regression set of a
goal G for a relevant action A.
And as you can see this is meant to be
the inverse of the state transition
function gamma and it is computed as
follows.
We start off with the original goal which
is a set of ground literals and we remove
all the effects of the action from that
goal and then we add all the
preconditions of the action to the goal.
Effectively, this computes from a given
goal G.
We remove all the effects, meaning we
remove all those things that have been
achieved by the action that we have
selected.
So we no longer need to achieve these if
we execute this action as the last step
before the goal.
But then, we need to have all the
preconditions true, so that we can
actually execute this action.
So what this gives us, is a new sub-goal.
And if we can somehow achieve this
sub-goal, then we know that through the
action A, we can achieve our original
goal.
Relevance and regression sets tell us how
we can move through our state base
backward.
They tell us how we can, given a goal and
a relevant action for this goal, compute
a new sub goal that constitutes a new
search state for our backward search.
So here is how we can define the
successor function for the backwards
search, which is equivalent to the
reachability analysis we did for forward
search.
We start with regression through a single
step from a given goal.
This is defined as the set of all those
sub-goals, gamma minus one GA, so the
regression sets, for a relevant action
for G, our original goal.
To compute this we start with our
original goal, then compute all the
relevant actions for this goal, and
regress through these actions two new sub
goals.
So this is a set of sub goals that we get
as a result.
The next step is that we extend this
function to take multiple goals as input,
so the input is now a set of goals rather
than a single goal.
And if we regress through zero states
that means simply the set of goals stays
the same.
There's no change.
If we can go one step backwards in our
search from a given set of goals, this is
simply the union over all the individual
goals and we regress those through our
regression function defined earlier.
And then we can apply this for M steps
backwards from a given set of goals by
simply doing a recursive definition as we
did for reachability.
So we apply it for one step after we've
applied it to M minus one steps for the
same set of goals.
What this means is that, from any of the
sub-goals that we've computed in this
way, we can reach the original goals in
exactly M steps.
M actions are necessary to go from the
sub-goals to one of the original goals.
And we can define the transitive closure
for this function, which is the set of
all regression sets that are possibly.
So these are all the possible sub goals,
that we can compute from our original
goal.
This is, pronounced gamma backwards, is
simply the union over all lengths of
plans that we can implement here, where K
is the length of the plan, and we compute
gamma minus K, of our original goal.
So for any K from zero to infinity, this
gives us all the sub goals that are
possibly reachable in our search base
from our original goal.
Now, given these definitions we can
define a search space for backwards
search planning.
The input to the algorithm is again a
statement of planning problem consisting
of a set of operators in a initial state,
and the goal to description as before.
Then the search problem can be defined by
the following four components.
We start with the initial state for a
search.
That is not the initial state not a state
base but the goal.
So we're searching backwards from the
goal.
And in our search space the goal is the
initial state.
And if the goal is our initial state that
means we need a new goal test for the
search space.
And this goal test is that the intitial
state in our problem specification
satisfies our sub-goal S.
Remember, we move through the search
space, or that is the idea, from the goal
backwards by computing sub-goals and S is
meant to be one of these sub-goals.
Now if we come across a sub-goal that is
satisfied the, in the initial state, that
means we can reach the goal state from
the sub-goal according to our regression
function just defined.
So, if our initial state satisfies the
sub-goal, we have reached a goal state in
a our search space.
The path cost function remains unchanged,
it is simply the length of the plan.
And the successor function, will be using
is simply the regression function we've
defined in the previous slide.
In general this function takes a sub-goal
that we've come across, and computes its
successors in the search space.
So, this concludes the definition of the
search space for backward search
planning.
Next I could show you the backward search
planning algorithm and pseudo code, but I
won't.
The pseudo code would look almost
identical to the code defined for forward
search and I'll leave that to you as an
exercise to modify that algorithm so that
it performs backward search.
Now that you understand how two planning
algorithms work, I'll even given you the
idea for a third one.
And to introduce this, I'll give you an
example.
Suppose our goal, our original goal we
start from is that we want the robot to
be at location one.
There is one operator in the dock loc
robot domain, that can achieve this goal,
and that is the move operator for moving
a robot r from location l to location M.
And we can see that this operator is
relevant because it has an effect at r m
which we can use to achieve our goal at
robot location one.
So all the actions that can be relevant
for this goal must be of this form that
we want to move the robot from some
location L to location one.
But, l remains a variable here.
So we don't know what this value of l
should be.
In fact, if you choose the wrong value
for ,, it may even interfere with the
goal.
Because we also have a negative effect,
not at rl.
In the backwards search we've considered
so far, we've only looked at actions for
regressing goals to sub-goals.
So what we could do in our algorithm is
simply replace this value L through all
possible constants that are of the right
type.
But if there are many places from which
we can move to location one that means
there are many options and that increases
the branching factor in our search
unnecessarily.
So what we can do is simply keep this
variable as a variable and that is what
is called lifted backwards search, which
can also deal with partially instantiated
operators where not all the parameters of
the operators are replaced by actual
values.
This does reduce the branching factor but
unfortunately it also makes the algorithm
a lot more complicated.
Keeping variables in a plan is an example
of what is sometimes called least
commitment planning where we try to make
as few commitments as possible during the
planning process unless we have a good
reason for making a specific commitment.
We will see a lot more of this type of
planning next week.
So this concludes the segment on
states-based search planning.
In this segment we've learned a lot about
the STRIPS representation for planning.
In the STRIPS representation we have seen
a standardized way of representing the
internal structure of states, namely a
sets of ground atoms.
So we have objects that are related by
some relations, and sets of these atoms
describe what the world state looks like.
And then we have defined what the
internal structure of operators looks
like.
Namely, an operator consists of a name
with parameters, a set of preconditions,
and a set of effects.
The effects are often divided into
positive and negative effects or the add
list and the delete list.
Based on this we can define strips
planning domains which are simply sets of
operators, and we can define strips
planning problems and consisting of a
domain, an initial state, and a goal
description.
And all this we've learned together with
a new syntax, the PDDL syntax, for
describing planning domains and problems.
Pbdl is probably the most commonly
understood language by planners today.
And next we have seen how forward states
space search can be used to solve
planning problems.
And there is a variant of that we have
also seen how we can search this space
backwards from the goal to the initial
state.
Unfortunately this planning algorithms as
of described them here are very
inefficient.
But as we will see later on the course it
doesn't take all that much to turn them
in to the state of our planning
algorithms.