So, now we have seen what search problems
look like, we can turn towards search
algorithms.
But before we describe the algorithm, I
need to describe the data structure that
we manipulate during the search.
And this is called a search node.
A search node is really a bookkeeping
structure that encapsulates a state.
Note that I say search tree here because
we will be using the search graph as a
search tree.
This is simply to make the algorithms
slightly easier to explain.
but there is a simple extension that you
can come up with that turns this back
into a graph search algorithm.
So,
here is the data structure we're looking
at.
Each search node consists of five things.
The first thing is the state, the state
that is encapsulated in the search node.
So a state corresponds to a configuration
of our world, and a node is a place in
our search tree.
Note that two search nodes may contain
the same state.
The next component of a search node, is
the parent node, that we store in each
node.
That is the immediate predecessor in the
search tree, the parent in the tree.
The only node that doesn't have a parent
is, of course, the root node in a tree.
Then we have to store an action in a
search node.
That is the action that gets us from the
parent node to this node.
Or, more precisely.
From the parents nodes state to this
state.
Then we also want to store the path cost,
in a search node.
That is the total cost of the path
leading to this node in the tree.
And finally, we can store the depth in
the tree as part of the node,
which allows us to do for example,
a simple cutoff, if we go too deep in the
search tree.
So these are the five components, that
make up a search node.
The state.
The parent node.
The action.
The path cost, and the depth.
So now, we get to the first algorithm
that you will see in this course.
This is the general tree search
algorithm.
The algorithm is implemented as a
function tree search, that takes a search
problem as input, and a search strategy.
I will get to the search strategy in a
minute.
The search problem is simply what we've
seen before,
the thing that consists of four
components.
The initial state, the successor
function, the goal, and the path cost
function.
The algorithm starts by creating a new
search node.
So that's the structure we've seen in the
previous slide,
from the initial state of our search
problem.
And this is stored in a set of nodes.
These are set braces.
and the set is called the fringe.
It is often also called the set of open
nodes,
as opposed to the set of closed nodes.
What this means is, these are all the
nodes in our search tree that we have not
yet explored.
And initially, we have not explored the
initial state,
and that's the only state we know about
initially.
So what we do then is we go through a
potentially infinite loop.
And the first thing we do in this loop,
is, we test whether there are still nodes
in our fringe that we can examine.
If there are no more nodes on the fringe,
that means we've explored the whole
graph,
and we haven't come across a node that is
a goal node.
So, in that case, we can return failure.
There is no solution to the search
problem if we have explored all the nodes
in the graph, and have not come across a
goal node.
But initially, there will, of course, be
at least one node, namely the node we
created from the initial state.
So what we do in the next step, then, is
we, we take our set of fringe nodes, and
we select one node from the fringe, and
we use the strategy to decide which node
we will select first.
So this node is the next one we will
explore in our search.
And by explore, I mean two things.
The first thing is, we apply the goal
test to the state that corresponds to
this node.
If this node is a goal node, that means
we found a solution to our planning
problem, to our search problem.
And we can stop the search here.
Note that this catches the case where out
initial state was actually a goal state,
because the first thing we do is we apply
the goal test before we do anything else
to this node.
If the gold task test has succeeded, we
can simply return the path to this node,
as this must be a solution to our search
problem.
If our current node we are looking at is
not a goal node, then what we have to do
is we generate all the successors and we
use the function expand here to do this.
So what we do is, we take the problem,
and we take the node, and we apply the
successor function that is defined as
part of the problem to this node which
gives us a set of actions and new states.
And each of these states can be turned
into a new node.
Together with the action that led to that
state.
And we expand the fringe so we add these
new nodes to the fringe.
And this gives us our new fringe.
And, at that point, we go back to the
beginning of the loop, and start again.
We look at the fringe, whether it's
empty.
If it's not empty, we select a node from
the fringe.
So this will be now a, a node at depth
one.
Then we apply the goal test to that node.
If it's not a solution, then we have to
do the same for that node, expand it,
generate its successors, and so on, until
we finally come to the point where either
we've explored the whole graph,
which means the fringe is empty, or we
come to the point where a node is a goal
node and passes the goal test and in that
case our search is done.
Now there are a few subtleties, with this
algorithm that I briefly want to go into.
The first one is that a tree
corresponding to a finite search graph
may be infinite.
Look at this very simple tree.
We have two nodes here.
And we can go from one to the other.
And then we can go back.
If neither of those two nodes is a goal
node, that would give us an infinite
loop.
We can always start here.
Then we add its successor to the fringe,
which is this node.
Then we have only one node on the fringe.
But then we go back to this node, add
this to the fringe.
We go here and here.
And our search tree will be infinite.
So, that means that this loop here.
May never terminate even if the search
graph is finite.
And the second subtlety has to do with
the strategy and that's what we will look
at next.
The search control strategy is an
effective method for scheduling the
application of the successor function.
We have seen this in the algorithm.
The strategy tells us which node from the
fringe we will select next to apply the
successive function to, and generates its
successors.
Now, the first thing to note here is that
it's got to be an effective method.
So what we mean by that here is that the
strategy must not take up too much time
to decide which node from the fringe to
expand next.
Ideally, it would take constant time.
What the strategy then does is determine
the order in which we expand nodes, or
the order in which we explore nodes in
our tree, the order in which we go
through our tree to look for a gold
state.
Our aim, of course, is to produce a gold
state as quickly as possible, so we want
to descend down our tree to a gold state
that is relatively close, and we come
across that quite quickly.
So a perfect strategy would know where
that gold state is an r tree.
But then, if we knew where the gold state
is, we wouldn't have to search for it in
the first place.
In general, a strategy that produces a
gold state quicker than another is
considered a better strategy.
And the way we have described the
previous algorithm in the previous slide,
with the strategy as an argument to the
node selection.
This makes it a deterministic algorithm,
as long as the strategy is deterministic.
Otherwise, without the strategy, you can
read this as a non-deterministic
algorithm.
The way a strategy can be implemented is
by keeping the fringe nodes in a specific
data structure.
A queue could be either a last in first
out queue, or a first in first out queue,
and that results in different search
algorithms.
For example, the LIFO queue, is
effectively a stack,
which means our search proceeds by always
exploring the node that has, that has
been last been added to the queue,
which means it does a depth first search.
It goes deeper into the tree before it
examines the neighbors of a given node.
Feefo would give you a breadth first
search by going to one level of the tree
before it goes to the next.
But there are many, many more ways you
can think of how to search and we will
look at something called a heuristic in
the next week.
just another example, you could also take
an alphabetical ordering of the nodes, if
you can't find some ordering relation
between the nodes.
Another thing that is quite important is
that in many search problems the complete
tree is far too large to fit into a
computer's memory, even with the kind of
memory we have today.
So the search strategy determines which
part of the search tree will be explored
and will be in memory, and therefore it
may determine whether we are successful
at all.
Because if the search tree is too large
for memory, we may not come across a goal
node at all.
Now for those of you who are not familiar
with search I recommend that you either
go to the Russel and Norvik textbook that
is mentioned on the website and have a
look at the corresponding chapters or you
should go through the programming
exercise and implement the missionaries
and cannibals problem as a search
problem.
You can use either of those two queueing
strategies mentioned there.
Lost and first out, or first and first
out,
and just see what happens when you apply
these two strategies.
Also, a hint regarding repeated states.
To turn the tree search into a graph
search,
you have to remember all the nodes you've
seen so far.
And the most effective way to do this is
to add them to a hash table.
And before you add a note to the fringe
again you check whether it is already in
that hash table.
You should be able to do this in the
programming language of your choice. the
missionaries and cannibals search space,
as you have seen is very small, so the
search should be instantaneous whatever
you use.
So, have fun with that.