So far, we have laid a lot of groundwork
before we can describe our first planner.
We have seen how a planning domain has
described a states space.
We have seen how to define a planning
problem, what constitutes a solution to
the problem, and previously, we have seen
how to search through a search space.
If we put all this together, we end up
with a forward state-space search planner
and that is what we will look at next.
So here is the basic idea how state space
search works,
namely, we want to apply standard search
algorithms that we've seen before like
breadth-first search, depth-first search,
or A*, you may remember, to a planning
problem.
And to do this, we need to define the
search space which may be different from
the state space.
But in this case, our search space is
simply a subset of the state-space that
we define for the planning problem.
The nodes in our search space correspond
simply to world states.
So the states that we have in our
planning problem are nodes in our search
tree.
The arcs in the search space correspond
to state transitions as defined by the
operators and the actions that we execute
as part of the plan.
And a path in the search space
corresponds to a plan, which is the
solution we are looking for.
More specifically, here is how we can
define a planning problem as a search
problem.
So we are given a planning problem as a
set of operators which implicitly define
a state transition system.
We are given an initial state and a goal
description.
These three components make up our
planning problem,
then we can define the search problem as
follows.
For the search problem, we need an
initial state and we simply take the
initial state from our planning problem.
Then, we need a go for our search problem
and we define a goal test here naming the
test that s satisfies g,
so the state that we're curently
searching must satisfy the goal.
Then we can define a path cost function
for our search and that is simply the
length of the plan we're currently
looking at.
Implicitly, this means that all actions
have equal cost here and that is why the
path cost function as the length of the
plan works.
And the final component we need is a
successor function and the successor
function, denoted gamma of s here, is
what we will define next.
The successor function gamma of s for
single state is defined here.
It is the set of all states gamma s,a for
all actions a that are applicable in the
state s.
So this set consist of all those states
that can be reached by an applicable
action from our state s.
If I wanted to compute this, I would have
to, I have to go through all the
operators and find all the ground
instances of these operators that are
applicable in the state,
then I could apply those actions in the
state and I would get all the successor
states here.
This is how gamma of s is defined.
We can extend this definition slightly.
Suppose we are not in one state but we
are in a set of states.
We know that we are in one of these
states and we, we want to define what
states are reachable from any of these
states.
Then, this is simply the union over any
of these states of gamma sk.
So we compute the successors for each of
the individual states and build the set
union, which is the result of gamma s, s1
through sn.
This gives us the states that are
reachable from any of those states that
are the input to the function in one
step.
We can make this definition yet more
general by naming the number of steps we
want to allow.
In the simplest case, we have gamma zero
which means we allow zero steps.
So if we're in any of these states, s1
through sn, and want to compute the
states that we can be in after zero
steps.
Well, that's exactly the states we start
in. If we don't do anything, we can't go
to any other states.
But, in general, we want to allow m steps
here and we want to say, initially, we
are in one of these states s1 through sn.
And then we can apply a recursive
definition of the function gamma by
saying we apply this to gamma m minus
one, so we take the set of states we
start from.
We can go m minus one steps from these
states,
that this, that is the input to this
here,
and then, we can go one more step here.
And that is then the set of all states
that are reachable from s1 through sn in
m steps.
So that is what we've defined here, we've
defined the function gamma m, which maps
a set of states to another set of states.
Mainly, exactly those states which are
reachable in m steps from anyone of the
states given in the input.
The transitive closure of this function,
then simply defines the set of all
reachable states,
so this is defined here.
All the reachable states are simply the
union of k from zero to infinity of gamma
k of s.
So we start in our initial state and we
apply k steps from there.
This is this set and we can apply zero,
one, two, three, and so on, up to
infinity steps.
And if we take the union of all that,
that is all the states that are reachable
from our initial state s.
And that is the function gamma forward of
s.
And here is why I've given you such a
complex definition,
because, with this definition, I can very
simply state when a planning problem has
a solution.
So we can state that a STRIPS planning
problem defined by a state transition
system initial stating goal or a
statement defined by the operators and
the initial state in the goal, has a
solution if and only if the following
holds.
Namely, if we take the set of all goal
states and we take the set of all
reachable states and we build the
intersection between these two sets,
then, this must not be the empty set or
you can see it the other way around, too.
If this set actually contains an element,
let's say a state Sg, then this state is
in both these sets, which means it is a
goal state and it is reachable from the
initial state.
And if there's a reachable state from the
initial state that is a goal state, that
means we have a solution to our planning
problem.
Now, this is all great.
But you may wonder, when are we actually
going to see a planning algorithm?