Another implicit assumption we have made
so far, is that all the actions we execute
are instantaneous.
A more realistic approach is to assume
that our actions are durative, which means
they take time.
So every action we consider takes a known
amount of time and every action have a
start time point and a finish time point.
Now, we have already seen that the A*
algorithm takes the action cost into
account.
So it can search actions that have a given
cost and one approach is simply to assign
the time they take as the cost of the
action.
And in fact, the FF planner we have seen
last week has been extended in this way to
take time into account.
A different approach that is often used in
conjunction with partial plans, and
specifically, in conjunction with HTN
planning, is to use a temporal constraint
manager as a plug-in component to the
planner.
And there are two flavors of it that are
quire well-known.
The first one is called the time point
network.
A time point network simply associates all
the time points in a given plan.
So, we have a start and a finish time
point for each action and we can assert
relations that must hold between these
different time points.
What we get is a network like this one
here, where we have six time points, and
they are related by these different
relations that we see on the edges in this
network here.
The good news is that the consistency of
time point networks can be checked in
polynomial time.
A more complex approach that has been
proposed is an interval algebra.
So now, we're relating not time points to
each other, but the intervals that
correspond to the action execution.
So, if we have an interval i1 and an
interval i2, we can say that one interval
must be before the other and we use this
relation b here to express this.
What this means is that the end time point
of the first action must be genuinely
before the beginning of the next action.
Similarly, we have other relations like
meets where these need to be at the same
time point or overlaps where one comes
after the other and start during and
finish are three more relations we have
here.
As it turns out, the interval algebra is
more expressive than time point networks.
So there are constraints you can express
in the interval algebra that you can't
express in time point network.
But on the downside, checking consistency
in an interval network takes exponential
time.
One of the things that all the approaches
we've looked at so far have in common is
that they don't learn.
So, if we give them a planning problem to
solve, they search or use whatever
technique to solve this problem and come
up with a solution.
If we give them the same problem again,
it'll take exactly the same amount of time
and resources to solve this problem.
Or if we give it a similar problem, the
planner cannot take anything from that
similar problem to the new problem and try
to solve it better.
So one approach was to try to apply
learning to planning to somehow improve
the performance of the planner over time.
So the general idea is, we let the planner
solve a series of similar planning
problems, then, we somehow analyse what
the planner has been doing during the
problem solving process.
And the result of this analysis should be
something that we can feed back into the
planning process to make the plan more
efficient on similar problems.
That is the general idea and that is what
you would expect from human planners when
they start solving similar planning
problems, they would get better over time.
And there are a number of ways in which
this learning can be done.
Here are two of them.
One is the learning of macro-operations.
So, our planning problem contains already
a set of operators that we can use to
solve that problem, but we can increase
that set with macro-operations that
perform larger steps in our search space.
Of course, this is somehow similar to HTN
planning where we also had more abstract
methods that summarize what needs to be
done at a lower level.
Another approach that has been tried is
learning search control knowledge.
So, during the search, we often encounter
states that have the same f values, so the
heuristic doesn't help us to distinguish
the states from each other.
And, search control knowledge helps us to
decide which path to explore next in our
search space.
Another assumption we have made so far is
that we're dealing with a single planner
that has control over all the agents that
are executing the plan.
So in our dock-worker robot domain, when
we were planning, we assumed that the
robots on the cranes during plan execution
would do as they are told by the single
planner.
However, in multi-agent planning, this is
not the case.
So we no longer assume that we have a
single agent that is control of all the
other agents.
Of course, this complicates the problem
significantly and there are a number of
flavors in which this problem can be
developed.
For example, if the agents we're dealing
with have different beliefs about the
worlds state they are in, then, this
becomes a quite different type of
planning.
Or, we can have planning problems where
all the agents have all the capabilities
can execute all the operators that are
available.
Or, agents have different capabilities.
So, some operators can only be executed by
certain agents.
Again, we have seen this in the
dock-worker robot domain, where the robots
can transport the containers and the
cranes can load the containers.
And of course, cranes at different
locations can only loan the containers
that are at their locations.
Another aspect of multi-agent planning are
the goals.
So we can have agents with joint goals,so
that all the agents want to achieve the
same goal or they can have individual
goals.
And, this becomes worse when the
individual goals are actually conflicting
or contradictory.
In this case, the agents can be
adversaries, like in a game of chess.
So you can see, there is a whole range of
multi-agent planning problems And another
aspect that is somehow different is the
problem of joint actions.
So, suppose you have a table with some
objects on top of it, and if you lift just
one side of the table, the objects will
fall off.
But if there are two agents that lift both
sides of the table at the same time, then,
the objects will stay on the table because
the table stays level.
This is an example of what is called a
joint action and requires multiple agents
to coordinate to execute that action.
And a single agent alone cannot achieve
the outcome of that joint action alone.