Lesson 7 is A Culturally Important
Integral.
So the first time I saw this integral, the
professor who taught
me how to evaluate this called it an A
Culturally Important Integral.
I think it's taken probably ten years but
now I, I fully agree with him.
So, hopefully if it doesn't seem all that
culturally important to
you after a few years of experience and
I'll improve a bit.
So, I'm going to look at a function called
the standard normal density.
This is the little phi that's been showing
up in the, in the Black-Scholes Pricing
Formula.
And it's defined to be 1 over the square
root
of 2 pi e to the minus x squared over two.
And we also, oops, so little phi is not
actually in the Black-Scholes Pricing
Formula, it's this capital phi that's in
the Black-Scholes Pricing Formula.
I guess this showed up in the in the
homework when we were looking at the
derivatives of the
Black-Scholes Pricing Formula.
The capital phi is
defined as the integral from minus
infinity up to x of little phi of t dt.
And so when I saw this the first
time, now a few questions immediately
popped into mind.
So I, I called this 2 and a half.
So where does the 1 over the square roots
of 2 pi come from, that
just seem sort of like a strange thing to
stick in front of a function here.
Two, why not use a closed-form expression
for this capital phi?
And so it turns out
this is a function that somebody actually
proved does not have,
so this function here, someone has proved
this does not have antiderivative.
So there is no way to write down
a closed-form expression for this function
capital phi,
by closed form, I just mean, you know,
like 1 minus the square root of something
else.
They gives you the value of this capital
phi function.
If you wanted to write down the
function, you would have to keep just
writing and writing.
You need an infinite number of terms in
order to write it down.
And so then, the 2 and a half question was
where did this 1 over 2 pi come
from because the whole reason it's here is
that
I want this to be a probability density
function?
So the different, part of one of the
conditions,
but there are two conditions, it has to be
greater
than zero, greater than or equal to zero
for all real numbers.
So this satisfies that.
It's actually greater than zero for all
real numbers.
And it has to integrate to one when
I integrate it from minus infinity to
infinity.
And so the reason this 1 over the square
root of 2 pi is
here is because this function here
integrates to the square root of 2 pi.
So, if I wanted to integrate to one, I
need to divide by 1
over the square root of 2 pi, so those
will cancel each other out.
And when I do this integral, I'll have 1.
But, yeah?
>> I know this is a weird question
but if I don't have a closed-form
expression for big phi how do we know
when we integrate it from negative
infinity to infinity that it's equal to 1?
>> Well, big phi doesn't have that
property.
The little one, the little one does.
And so that's actually what this whole
lesson will be about.
So, kind of, in particular, I need to know
exactly what you just asked.
If I knew the, the capital phi if I could
write
down that function and just take the limit
as it goes to
negative infinity and the limit as it goes
to positive infinity,
then I would be able to evaluate the area
under that curve.
And I would be able to tell you
you know, I'd be able to tell you what it
is, I'd
be able to tell you that's the square root
of 2 pi.
Then I would say well if that is the
square root of 2 pi, if
I divide by the square root of 2 pi,
that'll make it equal to 1.
And so the rest of this lesson is to find
out where this square root of 2 pi comes
from.
So, since phi is a probability density
function, the
integral of phi over the real line, so I
don't
know why I put it twice here but it still
integrates to 1 even if you do it twice.
And this implies that e to the minus x
squared over
2 dx has to equal the square root of 2 pi.
And you can make a change of variables to
just have a, a slightly simpler version of
the
function without the squared minus x
squared divided by
2 just to have e to the minus x squared.
And so this is actually what I'm going to
try and show.
That the integral of e to the minus x
squared from
minus infinity to infinity is equal to the
square root of pi.
And like I said before if e to the minus
x squared over 2 doesn't have an
antiderivative, then this
isn't going to either because I was able
to get
this with just a simple change of just a
simple substitution.
So this is actually going to use a trick
very similar to what we used in
the very first lesson, when I was trying
to come up with the value of an annuity.
I'm going to pretend like I know what the
answer
is and say that it's equal to the value of
this
definite integral on the right-hand side
and that I'm going
to mess around with this m as well as the
integral.
So I want to show that m is equal to the
square root of 2 pi.
And I could also write m as the integral
from minus
infinity to infinity of e to the minus y
squared dy.
So it doesn't matter what I call my
variable.
The value of this integral is going to be
the same.
So I'm going to have m defined in terms of
x and m
defined in terms of y but they're going to
be the same number.
And now what I'd like to do is to show
that M squared is equal to pi.
So if I can show that M squared is equal
to pi then that is
the same thing as showing that M is equal
to the square root of pi.
And if you recall the Separable Integral
Lesson, so this now looks
like what I would want to get from a
function that's separable.
But I can use that result backwards as
well, so I, I'm going
to start out by just trying to unseparate
this and see what happens.
So that's just the double integral of a
separable function.
And I'll start unseparating the integral.
So there's M squared again and
then I'll take the, let's see, so I've
taken the y integral and
kind of plucked it into here, which I can
do because it's a constant.
And then I'll get rid of my, my brackets.
And now, notice that e to the minus x,
oops, e to the minus
x squared, that's also a constant with
respect to this integral on the right-hand
side.
And it looks like my dx disappeared from
this line, but it showed up again here.
So, everything is okay.
And so what I'm going to end up with is e
to
the minus x squared times e to the minus y
squared.
And by the properties of the exponential
function, I can write
that as e to the minus quantity x squared
plus y squared.
And then when you see x squared plus y
squared, that's usually a pretty good
hint that this might be something that
would be simplified by switching to polar
coordinates.
So, let's see what happens when I try and
switch this into polar coordinates.
so all I have to do to switch to
polar coordinates, I replace the
x by r cosine theta and the y by r sin
theta.
And then, my dx dy becomes r dr d theta.
So, the r was the Jacobian.
If I use the same transformation, if I use
the same change of variables
over and over and over again, the Jacobian
is always going to be the same.
So for the change to polar coordinates,
the dy dx or dx dy is always going to
become r dr d theta.
So now, I can write my M squared as the
integral from zero to 2 pi integral from
zero to infinity of, well, this guy is
going to get easier in just a second.
So, let's,
so all I've done here is I've factored out
the r squares the negative r squared.
And what's left inside the square brackets
here
is cosine squared theta plus sin squared
theta.
This is equal to 1.
So I have e to the minus r squared.
And then luckily, this little r that
showed up, thanks to the Jacobian, is
exactly what I need to be able to do a
substitution, to be able to integrate e to
the minus r squared.
And again, this is separable, so I can
also
take advantage of the fact that there's no
theta
in this part of the function so I can
move the integral with respect to theta
out in front.
And then, I have minus 1 half that I'm
going to introduce here just
so I can introduce some minus 2 here, so
minus 2 will cancel out the minus 1
half.
If I make the substitution, u equals minus
r squared then du is going to be
minus 2r dr.
So, I've made this, put this in,
in brackets here.
So, I have e to the u after I make my u
substitution.
This bit in the, in the parentheses is
going to be du.
And then if u is equal to minus r squared,
the limits on
u, they're going to start at 0 because
negative 0 squared is still 0.
And it will go to u equals negative
infinity.
The first first integral is trivial so
that just becomes theta
integrate evaluated at two pi so this will
just be two pi.
This is, oops, this is e to the u du.
So that's a special function that it's a,
it's its own derivative.
So I end up with minus 1 half e to the u
evaluated at minus infinity and at 0.
And so,
I have to be a little bit careful here.
I can't just plug infinity in.
But what I end up having is minus 1 half
so
e to the, I'm going to replace u with t so
this
is just e to the u evaluated at t and then
take the limit as that go, as t goes to
minus infinity.
And then, I have to subtract the lower
endpoint.
So that's just going to be e to the u with
u equals zero substituted in.
That will be e to the 0, and anything to
the zero
power is equal to 1.
Or anything not 0 to the 0 power is equal
to 1.
So then I have minus 1 half
times this, the limit as, of e to the t as
t goes to negative infinity.
This is if I, it gets smaller and smaller.
So in the limit that's just going to be 0.
So I end up with 0 minus 1, so negative
1 times negative 1 half, and that gives me
a half.
This first bit is 2 pi so 1 half times 2
pi gives me pi.
And I've been writing all of these equal
signs here.
So the whole long string of e qualities is
showing me that M squared is eventually
equal to pi.
And this is the thing that I set out to
prove in the first place.
So, in summary, I started out with M equal
to this integral
that I couldn't find an antiderivative of.
So it was difficult to evaluate.
I was showed I was able to show that M
squared was
equal to pi so M is equal to the square
root of pi.
And that gives us the result that we
wanted, that this integral from minus
infinity to
infinity of e to the minus x squared dx is
equal to the square root of pi.