So we'll get started with functions of
several variables.
So there's two types roughly that
we can talk about, and it just has to do
with what the output of the function is.
So I'm going to start out with the
simplest one which is the scalar valued
function.
Under a Scalar Valued Function just takes
values in the real numbers.
So you put in if it's of several variables
two or
more inputs and you get one number out
and some would call that a Scalar Valued
Function.
And the notation I'm going to use for that
is
f', that's the name of my function from rn
into r.
So rn just means that there are n real
numbers that are taken as input, so
this is a function of n variables.
And output is a real number so it's a,
a single variable output, a scalar
function.
And so you can think of that just as this.
So I have inputs x1, x2, up to xn.
Each one of the x's is a real number.
And then the output y is a real number.
And so the example I'm going to use, for,
for this week's
lectures is, Black Scholes pricing formula
for a European call option.
And so hopefully when we look at this with
all of its
pieces finally, it's going to, sort of,
become more apparent why we
had to spend so much time learning how to
take derivatives of
little indefinite integrals, things like
that, product rule, chain rule and so on.
So the inputs for this formula.
Are going to be s, which is the price of
the stock.
Sigma which is the volatility of the
stock.
K is the strike price, so this is, you
know, what
I'm going to be able to get for my if I
decide to exercise my option in the future
R is the
risk-free interest rate, so that's
risk-free interest rate just on money.
T is the maturity, and this is, the way to
think about
capital T, and there, there'll be a little
t somewhere here, too.
they're both dates,
so.
You know, this could be next Tuesday and
little
t, generally we're going to think of that
as today.
And then q is continuous dividend rate.
If the, if the asset pays dividends then
you want to
take those dividends and figure out what
the continuous rate would be.
And q is going to represent that number.
And then this is the formula so, generally
the, the inputs
you think of it as a function with two
main inputs.
So the, the price of the asset s, and then
the current time t.
And, generally, you can almost think of
this as one
input because at a certain time, like
right now, I can
look at the market and see what the price
of
the asset is so these, these are, sort of,
tied together
in, in a certain sense.
And, so, the formula then is s times e to
the minus q capital T minus little t.
And so this is where it becomes important
to think of the t's as dates.
So, if I say next Tuesday is capital t and
right now is little t.
So, that would be eight days in the
future.
So, when I do capital t next Tuesday minus
today that's going to give me eight.
So, This quantity, capital T minus little
T, you can think about that as the time
left in chill maturity, and as time moves
forward, that's actually getting shorter.
And then you can see that this formula is
going to simplify a bit
if you have a non-dividend paying asset,
this q is just going to be zero.
And so you'll have e to the zero.
And this whole piece that I have
highlighted will disappear.
It'll just become one.
[COUGH].
So I'm
going to multiply that times Fi.
And remember, Fi was this function we
defined as the integral
of the standard normal density from minus
infinity up to its argument.
So this value here.
So Fi of d1 of st.
So d1 is going to be another function that
we have to evaluate.
And then I'm going to subtract k times, so
here r is the interest rate, the risk free
interest rate times the time left until
maturity times Fi.
Again and now we have another function d 2
of st
and the, the form of d1 and d2 are down
here.
Again and now we have another function d2
of st.
And the form of d1 and d2 are down here so
I'll
have to wait until my slide disappears so
they're not exactly simple.
So the, the reason we want to write this
as Fi of d1 And fi of d2 is just if,
if I start plugging this whole expression
into these parenthesis the, the thing gets
quite unwildy.
And then d2 is just
equal to d1 minus sigma times the square
root of capital T minus little t.
And if you write down what that looks
like, if you plug in
this formula on the left for d1, all that
ends up changing is,
this plus here becomes a minus.
So that quite often, derivatives of d1 and
d2 are very similar to each other, they
differ
by a sign or not at all, depending on
what What you're taking the derivative
with respect to.
So in order to take a derivative of a
function of several
variables we, we have to define a new
concept called a partial derivative.
So I have a function from Rn into R.
And the partial derivative of F with
respect to the Jth, input, I'm going to
denote that as partial of F with respect
to Xj.
And that's
also going to be a function of N
variables.
[INAUDIBLE]
.
And we're going to define the partial
derivative, then, just
to be this limit on the right hand side.
And if you look closely, all I'm doing is
I'm treating
everything except for x sub j as if it
were a constant.
So, I am leaving those the same, and then
I am using
just on the one variable I am interested
in so x of j.
I am going to use the definition of the
derivative
on that one particular p.
So, add h to that and then add then I will
subtract r, local our, our initial points.
So, this is the point where I am trying to
find the derivative.
And then I'm going to divide by h.
And then take the limit as h goes to zero.
And then we say that this has a derivative
if this limit exists, and is finite.
And in practice, the way we're going to
compute these.
we're just going to fix xk for every x
that's not equal to j.
So remember, I'm trying to compute the,
the jth partial derivative.
So I'm just going to treat xk, any other
variable, as if it's a constant.
And then just to differentiate f as if it
were a
function of one variable, and that one
var, variable being xj.
So, for example, if I let my function, so
I'm going to choose a function of two
variables and I have x squared y plus e to
the minus xy cubed.
And I want to take the derivative of this
function now.
I guess I should mention a little bit here
about notations so, when we are taking
a complete derivative with a function of
one
variable and I take its derivative I've
just
been using 'd by dx' And when I'm taking a
partial derivative, I use this funnier
symbol that it looks kind of like a twisty
D that' I'm just going to read as partial.
And so, because this is a sum of
two functions, I still have a linearity
property.
So, I can.
The, the derivative of a sum is the sum of
the derivative.
So this is going to be equal to the
derivative of
the first term plus the derivative of the
second term.
And then to take the derivative of this
piece
here with respect to x, I'm going to make
a substitution.
So I'm going to say minus xy cubed.
I'm going to call that U, I think that's
what I decided to do.
Yep.
So I can rewrite this like this.
So if I look at what happened in the first
term, since I'm taking the
partial derivative with respect to X, my
rule was treat Y like it's a constant.
So if Y is a constant, I can use my
formula that says.
C times x squared.
The derivative of that is equal to c times
the derivative of x squared.
So in this case, now, y is my constant.
So I can just say that's equal to y times
the derivative.
Sorry, y times the partial with respect to
x, of x squared.
And then, for the term on the right.
I'm taking the partial derivative of a
function of u, so partial derivative with
respect
to x of a function of x, so I have to use
the chain rule here.
And so the chain rule says that the
derivative of this is going to be the
derivative of my function of u times the
derivative of u with respect to x.
[INAUDIBLE]
.
So the derivative of e to the u is just e
to the u.
And then I still have to calculate this
partial u, partial x.
And I'll do that just by taking the
derivative of my substitution here with
respect to x.
And then, for the, for the first term,
that was pretty easy.
I just used the power rule to say
that the derivative, derivative of x
squared was 2x.
So I end up with 2xy.
So the
partial derivative of my substitution with
respect to
x is just going to be minus y cubed.
So that's just minus y cubed times x and
using the power rule,
and then I just have to reverse my
substitution.
So I am going to replace this u.
Right here with minus x y cubed
and I end up with 2 xy minus y cubed times
e to the minus xy cubed.
[COUGH]
So that was the derivative with respect to
x.
We can repeat now for the derivative with
respect to y.
So I'm going to set this up exactly the
same way.
Use the linearity property to write.
This is two, the sum of two derivatives.
Make the same substitution.
But this time, when I look at the, the
first
term, now I'm taking the derivative with
respect to y.
So it's the x squared I can bring out.
So I have x squared times the partial with
respect to y of just y.
And then on the right hand term I have
partial with respect to y of e to the u.
So by the change rule I'm going to have to
multiply the
derivative of e to the u, times partial u
partial y
And again I am just going to take the
derivative,
but this time with respect to y of my
substitution.
So that gives me my chain rule derivative,
so I have du dy equals minus 3 xy
squared, so that's here just treating x as
a
constant and taking the derivative of
minus y cubed.
Using the power rule.
And then I just have to plug everything
back in and I
get the partial derivative of F of X with
respect to Y.
And so essentially what we're going to
have to do to get a full idea of
what the derivative of F of X Looks like
is where we need every partial derivative
and so if f is a function of n variables
with one output.
So the output is a real number then I
am going to define something called the
gradient of a F.
Which is denoted sometimes by capital d
times f of x.
So here we think of capital d kind of the
same way I think of d by dx.
It's a operator, so it means take
the gradient of the function f of x.
And the gradient is just going to be an
array of the partial derivatives of f of
x.
So each one of these terms, so each one of
these elements
of the array df Dx 1, or partial F partial
X one, that's a function of N variables.
Partial F partial X two, that's also a
function of N variables.
And
then one last thing that we might have to
deal with is a function of one
or more variables That takes values in a
multidimensional space is called a vector
value function.
And so in this case what I'm after is, I
have, say, two inputs, and my function
gives me two outputs.
And so in this case, I'm going to use the
function, sorry, the notation, F from Rn
into Rm.
And so this just means that f is the
function that takes n arguments.
So there are n inputs to this function.
And then there are m outputs to this
function.
And the way to think about this is, you
have f of my n inputs
I can have m a different sort of
sub-functions, each one of them returns
the well, element one, two, three up to m
of the vector of outputs.
And so in this case, when we try and make
the gradient.
We're going to have, instead of just an
array that only has one row, we're
going to have,
one row with n columns for each for each
element of the output.
So now my gradient is going to end up
being an array with m rows and n columns.
So there are N times N first order partial
derivatives, which is a lot to work with.