Here is the four one state space search
algorithm.
This algorithm is defined as a function
forward search that takes three arguments
namely the three components that make up
a planning problem.
The first component is the set of
operators defined for the planning
problem.
Then we have an initial state and a goal
description.
The algorithm works by starting from the
initial state and searching from here.
And it also builds up a solution plan why
we go through this loop.
As for the previous search algorithms,
the first thing in the loop we do is test
whether we have reached a goal state.
The goal test, now, is whether the state
that we're currently looking at,
initially the initial state, is a goal
state.
We test this by testing whether it
satisfies the goal.
If this is the case, then we can return
our plan, initially, the empty plan.
So, if our initial state was the goal
state, then we return the empty plan, and
we are done.
If not, then we have to continue.
And what we have to do next is compute
the state transition function.
We do this as described earlier by
computing all the ground instances from
all the operators defined in our planning
problem that are applicable in our state.
So this gives us the set of applicable
actions in our current state.
Now if this set was empty, if there are
no applicable actions in the current
state, then we can return failure.
That means we, we have exhausted our
search space and haven't come across a
solution.
The next step is simply choose one of the
applicable actions that we have just
computed.
What I've done here is simply made my
life a little simpler by describing the
algorithm as a non-deterministic
algorithm.
This is a non-deterministic choice point.
What this means, in the actual
implementation, would have to do search
here.
It would have to back track to this
point, to try out the different action.
If the one we've chosen previously fails.
So this would build up a search tree,
branching at exactly this point.
In a non-deterministic algorithm we can,
of course, assume that we have chosen the
right action here.
Then what we do is we simply update our
current state by applying the state
transition function of the previous
state, this is the previous state, and
the action that we apply in this state.
And of course we have to add this action
to the plan, so we concatenate new plan
consisting of just one action to our old
plan, and get the new plan as a result
and that's it.
We simply go through our loop again until
we either come to this point where we can
return a plan to a solution state.
Or we come to this point where we return
failure meaning we have exhausted the
search space and didn't find a solution.
And here is a very simple example to
illustrate this algorithm.
We start off in a initial state, which is
the trivial problem we've seen earlier.
And we have defined the goal also from
the example we've seen earlier to give us
just one state as a goal state.
But the algorithm doesn't know that
there's only one goal state, or where it
is.
So we will remove this, here.
So, the first thing the algorithm does is
test whether this is a goal state.
And I can assure you it is not.
So the algorithm will continue by
computing the applicable actions.
And then selecting one of these
applicable actions.
And in this case, what the algorithm does
is select this action, here.
We're taking, with the crane, there's
only one, at location one, the container,
which is on this pile here.
from the pallet in the pile.
That is the action that the algorithm
chooses.
Then what happens is it applies the state
transition function to get a new state,
which is the state we see here.
And it also updates its plan, which is
what we have here.
And it continues like this through the
loops so it checks whether this is a goal
state.
It isn't a goal state, it computes the
applicable actions, picks one of those,
in this case that's the move action, and
accordingly has to compute a new state,
that's the new state we generate with
this move action.
And so on we continue through the loop
and see this is not a goal state, so we
compute the applicable actions again, now
we try to load the container with the
crane at the location.
And, we get a new state.
As a result, now you can see the
container is on the robot.
And, this is not a goal state so we go
through the loop.
And we find there's a final action that
we need to execute.
We need to move the robot to the other
location.
And then we get a new state.
And this is now our goal state so at the
beginning of the loop, the algorithm will
terminate.
And it will return at this stage this
plan here consisting of those four
actions that, gave us the path through
this state space.
So you have seen that the algorithm was
only a very small step given all the
definitions we had before.
But now we want to say a little bit more
about the algorithm and what we want to
say is that the algorithm possesses two
properties that are very important.
Forward search is sound and forward
search is complete.
Soundness means that if the function
returns a plan as a solution, then this
plan is indeed a solution.
This is, of course, a very useful
property of such an algorithm.
If the algorithm was not sound, that
means it could return a plan that isn't a
solution.
So we would still not know what the
solution is but the algorithm is sound.
And the proof of this is very simple.
We can show this by induction.
And we show that, at the beginning of the
loop, this statement here always holds.
So we have the two loop variables, state
and plan.
And we show that the state is always
equals to gamma of si, and the plan we're
currently looking at.
This is true, initially, of course
because the initial value of state is the
initial state.
And the initial plan is empty.
So gamma applied to SI with the empty
plan means we still are in the initial
state.
And those two are equal.
And then we can show that this condition
is maintained through the loop.
Each iteration of the loop keeps this
condition true.
Which means that it is also true for the
final iteration before we return the
plan.
And that means the state is the result of
applying the state transition function,
NSI, with the plan.
And we return from the function when
state satisfies the goal.
So, therefore, this plan must reach the
state.
And our algorithm is sound.
The second property that the algorithm is
complete means that if there is a
solution to our problem, the algorithm
can find the solution.
And since this is a non-deterministic
algorithm, we talk about an execution
trace.
So there is a set of choices that we can
make at the non-deterministic choice
points, such that the algorithm will
return the solution plan.
And again, the proof can be done by
induction.
And this time, we show that our plan is
always a prefix of the plan we're looking
for.
What you need to remember is only that
our algorithm is sound and complete.