The next section is higher derivatives.
I'm going to start out with just a little
motivation
of the type of problem we're, we're trying
to solve.
So, a utility function and this is a
special type of
function that shows up in economics Is a
real value function, u of x.
So I'm just going to call it u, because
it's a utility, defined for real numbers.
And the idea is, it's going to help us
compare wealth levels.
And so basically, if If U of x is greater
than u of y, so x and y
are some sort of wealth, so you could
think
of that as maybe income, maybe a payment
from something.
Then u of x is preferred.
And so it's basically kind of telling me
Let's see.
Well, I have some pictures and that, that
will hopefully make it a bit
more clear.
So, some common utility functions are
exponential utility.
So, it has a parameter A is greater than
0.
Logarithmic utility, so it's just the log
of my wealth level.
power rule, so that it's b times x to the
b.
So it's sort of a, like a polynomial
function.
And quadratic, which is defined to be x
minus bx for some number b greater than 0.
And just to sort of help visualize, this
is what they look like.
So the, the actual value of the utility
isn't important.
But what's, what is important is just how
I'm
going to compare things that are on this
curve.
So if I look, for instance, at this
logarithmic utility here.
And if I'm over on the left side, just a
small increase
in, in the x variable is going to give me
a pretty big increase in utility.
Whereas if I looked at say the
right side of this power rule
You know, the same size increase in x is
going to give me a much smaller increase
in my utility.
So where these things pop up is if
you're trying to do something like
planning for retirement.
You know, having enough money just to
survive every
year in retirement that gets you the most
utility.
You have to be able to pay for your house,
pay for
your food, pay your bills that's You know,
if you don't have
that, you're going to have a really bad
retirement.
You know, if you get up on the right hand
side where you start to have a lot of
wealth.
You know, you already have a boat, do you
really need an air strip too?
really need an Air strip too?
You know, you already have a boat, do you
really need an Airstream too?
And so, the particular utility function
that I'm going to, to
consider for the rest of this little
lesson, is the quadratic utility.
And so normally when you're looking at
utility
functions you want them to be non
decreasing.
So you don't ever want to get to a point
like I've drawn here.
Where if I was on this little bit of the
quadratic
utility function, I actually add more
wealth and I'm somehow worse off.
And so what you need to do is be able to
find the maximum of this function.
And I, I suppose, you know, maybe if
you know, maybe if I was at a restaurant
or
something and I was putting food on the x
axis.
There would be some point were I was
pretty happy.
And then if I continued to eat I probably
would be less happy.
maybe that would be a good example of this
quadratic function, but generally From
from just a purely economic point of view,
you want them to be non-decreasing.
So what you would want to do with this
quadratic one is
you would want to find out where it gets
to the very top.
And then, probably at that point, just say
beyond
that, the utility is just constant at that
level.
Oops.
So.
Oh, so what is the derivative telling us?
And that's what I was trying to get at a
little bit before when.
You know If this curve is steep.
So the derivative is telling us what is
the slope of this curve at a point.
So if the derivative is large it means the
curve is steep, it
means that a little bit more wealth gives
us a lot more utility.
Whereas, if I'm over here a little bit
more wealth, hardly gives me any utility.
So that's the, the derivatives is I'm
going to give me sort of
the relative change in utility for one
more dollar worth of wealth.
And so now if I go back to my,
my quadratic utility, I want to find a
point where I'm at the top of this thing.
And so, the way I'm going to know I'm at
the top, you know, if I'm walking
up a hill, I walk up the hill and as I get
closer to the top.
You know, it gets less steep,
less steep, until all of a sudden, I'm
going down the hill.
And so, at one point, I'm going up.
Later, I'm going down.
Somewhere in the middle, it must have been
flat.
And so where it's flat, the slope of that
tangent line is going to be equal to zero.
So that means I want to find a point a so
that the derivative,
the derivative is the slope of my tangent
line, is going to be zero.
And I'm going to call
that point a critical point.
And if my function has a local minimum.
So that means it either has a hump or a
trough out of point a, then a is always
going to be a critical point.
And so if I, if I sort of zoom in on my
quadratic utility, so my u of x here is
now the quadratic utility function.
I find this point a where it's flat here.
Well, I can also take the derivative of u
of x and
that's this descending line here that I've
called U prime of X.
And where that line crosses 0, that's
where this point is, where the critical
point is going to be.
That's where the tangent line's going to
be flat.
So, where this line is above 0, I have an
upward sloping curve.
When the derivative is less than 0, so
below
the X axis, I have a downward sloping
curve.
And then, you can do exactly the same
thing.
If it were this is just some arbitrary
function that now has a local minimum.
And so now where it's downward sloping I
have a derivative of less than zero.
Where it's upward sloping.
I have a derivative greater than zero,.
And where this derivative actually hits
the x axis,
that's where my critical point is going to
be.
And so the lesson we want to take away
from this is.
If f prime of x is decreasing at a, so
here
f prime of x is going down at the point a.
Then I have a local maximum.
So the funtion looks like the top of a
hill.
If it's increasing, so here, the
derivitive
is increasing when I hit the critical
point.
Then I have a local minimum.
And so most of the time what's going to
happen when you're taking derivatives.
You take a derivative of a function f of x
and
you get f prime of x and that's also a
function.
And most of the time f prime of x is also
going to be a differentiable function.
And so you could again take its
derivative.
And so we're going to denote that by f
double prime of
x, which is just the derivative of f prime
of x.
And f double prime is called the second
derivative of f of x.
And I can also write it in Liebniz
notation, so
Now I take the first derivative of f of x.
I think of this thing in the square
brackets as a function.
And I take that function's derivative one
more time with respect to x.
I can write, this d squared over dx
squared to
mean take the derivative, take the second
derivative in one step.
And I can also use this notation d squared
f over dx squared
to mean the function that is the second
derivative of f of x.
And sometimes you'll also see this so you,
you just use a
capital letter d, so df of x would be the
first derivative of f of x.
D squared f of x is the second derivative.
And then there's no reason to stop at two.
So you can have as many higher derivatives
as you want.
some notation that seems to be pretty
common as you have f
to the n but the n is in parentheses.
So that just means the nth derivative of
the function f of x.
just like we had d
squared dx here, we can have d to the n, d
x to the n of f of
x.
Or this capital letter D to the n of x.
But that's only going to work if the one
before that so f n minus
1 of x is a differentiable function.
So as long as the derivative is a
differentiable function itself,
you can then take the derivative again
and, and keep going.
And so if we go back to our local maximum
and local minimum
picture, if I plot the first derivative I
get this decreasing line.
If I plot the second derivative, that's
just
going to be the slope of the first
derivative.
But the derivative is already a line, so
its slope is going to be constant.
So I just get a constant value here, u
double prime of x.
And so, f of x equals 0, sorry f prime of
x equals 0, so I have a
critical point at a here.
And f double prime of x.
So th, these, I really ought to have put A
in here.
So if I evaluate f double prime at a as
well.
So if I look at a, and go down to f double
prime, that's less than zero.
Then that corresponds to a local maximum.
So allow, that allows me to classify this
critical point as a maximum.
Where if f prime of a were equal to 0, so
here
I have, now I'm talking about the graph on
the right hand side.
I have a critical point, because the
derivative is equal to zero.
But here f of x, f prime of x is upward
sloping.
So f double prime of x is going to be a
positive constant.
So f double prime of a,
in particular, is going to be greater than
0.
And that's going to correspond to a local
minimum.
So these are called first and second order
condition.
The first order condition says the
derivative has to be equal to zero.
Second order condition says second
derivative less than zero.
And that gives me a local minimum.
And then if the second derivative is
greater than zero,
sorry, second derivative less than zero
gives me a local maximum.
Second derivative greater than zero gives
me a local minimmum.
So for functions like this it's not too
bad, you
can just draw a picture and it's usually
pretty clear.
But things get you know can get a little
bit more
complicated and then especially if the
function has several critical points.
And you're looking for a maximum, you
might want to wait till we
[INAUDIBLE]
the local minimum.
So for a financial example of this suppose
I have a certain
amount of money, and I want to divide it
into two assets.
And my goal is to, so that, that is
something called a portfolio.
And I want to choose how much I'm going to
put into each asset to maximize my
expected return.
And so basically what I want to do is I am
suppose I'm not allowed to short sell
either one of those.
So short sell means to sell something that
I don't actually own.
If I'm not allowed to do that, I have to
put some amount
of money into asset A and some amount of
money into asset B.
And those two amounts have to both be
greater than 0.
And sum up to my total amount of money.
So the way I'm going to simplify that is
just say f
of x is going to be defined on the
interval 01.
And x is just going to be the ratio.
Or the, the fraction of money that goes
into asset 1.
So asset 1 get's x.
Asset 2 get's 1 minus x.
And if I only consider x on the interval
0 1, then both of those are going to be
positive.
more generally, you can do this on an
interval AB,
but 01 will work for what I want to show
off here.
So, if I want to find all of the minimum
and maximum values of this function on 01.
The approach I'm going to use is first
find all
of the critical points on the open
interval 0 1.
And
I'm just going to evaluate f of x there.
And I also need to evaluate f of x at a
and b.
so a and b are the end points.
So I need to evaluate f of 0 and f of 1.
And then the global maximum.
So I can say what the global maximum is
going to be because I
know all of the points where that could
occur on this interval 0 1.
It's just going to be the maximum of all
the points I find in steps 1 and 2.
And then the minimum is going to be The
minimum
of all the ones I find in steps one and
two.
And really it's step two that I'm trying
to to harp on here because
this is what could happen.
So suppose this little tick over here is
meant to be 1.
If I have an expected return that looks
something like this, I would find Just
by using calculus, maybe these two orange
points, which are the critical points.
And then I would see well this one's
positive, and this one's negative.
And, if I'm investing, I certainly don't
want to invest in something that has
a negative expected return, so I would
probably choose this point here.
But it turns out that in this particular
example, the best choice would just be to
put all of my money in asset one and none
of my money in asset two.
And so this is actually a pretty common
interview question.
They'll set up some sort of payment off
scheme like this where
if you don't check the end points, you're
going to get the wrong answer.
And then another step you can do is
calculate the second derivative of f of x.
And evaluate it at the two critical
points.
And that would allow you classify those as
local minimum or local maximum.