[BLANK_AUDIO]
In our last lesson, we saw various
approaches to incomplete search of game
trees.
In each appre, approach, the evaluation of
states
is based on local properties of those
states.
Now that means properties that do not
depend on the game tree as a whole.
In many games, there's no correlation
between these local properties
and the likelihood of success in
completing a game successfully.
So in this lesson, we're going to look at
some
alternative methods, based on statistical
analysis of game trees.
First examine a simple approach based on
what's called Monte Carlo game simulation.
And then we look at a more sophisticated
variation, called Monte Carlo Tree Search.
Or sometimes, UCT.
The basic idea of Monte Carlo search is
simple.
As with depth limited search, we explore
the game tree to some fixed depth.
In order to estimate the value of any
non-terminal state at this depth, we make
some
probes from that state to the end of
the game by selecting random moves for the
players.
To sum up the total rewards for all such
probes, and divide
by the number of probes to obtain an
estimated utility for that state.
And then we use these expected utilities
in comparing states and selecting actions.
So I was just mentioning the expansion
phase is the same
as depth-limited search that treats
explore to some fixed step, as before.
And then the pro, we enter a probe phase
where we have
an exploration from each of the fringe
states reached in this expansion process.
For each making random probes from there
to a terminal state.
The values produced from each of these
probes are then added up, and divided by
the number of possibilities number of
probes
for each state to obtain an expected
utility.
For example, in the case on the left, we
made four
probes, got 1 100th, the sum total of the
four probes
is 100, divide by 4 is 25 The second case,
100s, 2 zeros, total of 200 divide by 4,
we get 50.
so these utilities are then compared to
determine the relative utilities
of the fringe states produced at the end
of the expansion phase.
Much better than making an assumption of,
conservative assumption of zero utility
for non-terminal states.
Simple implementation of max score for
Monte Carlo search is shown here.
It's a method that's exactly the same as
ordinary fixed depth heuristic
search, except that the player uses the
Monte Carlo routine to evaluate states.
And Monte Carlo is definite, one
definition
of Monte Carlo shown here, takes a state
as argument, returns the average utility
obtained from
set of n probes, here called depth
charges.
Or ends the value of some global parameter
count.
Now, the depth charge subroutine, shown at
the bottom first checks at a state's
terminal.
If so, it returns that value, otherwise it
forms a
joint move by taking random legal actions
of all the players.
That simulates this joint move, and calls
itself recursively until
it gets to a terminal state, and returns
the result.
Well, one downside on the Monte
Carlo method is that it can be optimistic.
It seems all players are playing randomly.
When in fact, it's possible that they know
exactly what they are doing.
It doesn't help if most of the probes from
a position in chess lead to success, if
one
leads to a state in which one's player is
checkmated, and the other player sees how
to do that.
This issue is addressed
below to some extent in the UCT method
that we'll describe shortly.
Another drawback of Monte Carlo is it
doesn't
really take into account the structure of
a game.
For example it may not recognize
symmetries or
independences that could substantially
decrease the cost of search.
Now for that matter, it doesn't even
recognize boards, or pieces, or piece
count; or any other feature that might
form the basis of game specific
heuristics.
Still, even with these drawbacks, the
Monte Carlo method is quite powerful.
It's fast, and consumes very little space,
and it's surprisingly effective.
prior to its use, general game players
were at best interesting novelties.
But once players start using Monte Carlo,
the improvement in game play was dramatic.
Suddenly automatic general game players
began to perform at a very high level.
And using a variation of this technique,
Cadia Player won the International General
Game Playing Cos, Competition three times.
And almost every general game playing
program
today includes some version of Monte
Carlo's search.