This section of the course will look at
the very wide range of research and
development areas that have been explored
in AI Planning.
It'll put AI Planning techniques in the
context of domain modeling and plan
representation.
Consider engagement with users, task
assigners, and decision makers, who must
select between plan options.
And would include the important aspect of
plan execution for practical systems.
The cost logo shows a number of
applications of [INAUDIBLE] AI planners
over the years.
The [INAUDIBLE] planner was used in the
mid 1970s to generate project plans for
electricity to [INAUDIBLE] overhaul.
The project plans in this case were
prepared well in advance, because it's
costly to have these machines out for any
length of time.
But while the repair's taking place
typically problems are found,
extra maintenance operations need to be
injected.
so the plans had to be adjusted as you
went along.
And [INAUDIBLE] was able to do that.
In the late 1970's, Steve [INAUDIBLE] at
NASA's jet propulsion laboratory created
the divisor planner, which was used to
generate action sequences for the Voyager
spacecraft.
Though it wasn't used for uploading live
action sequences to voyages.
Divisor was based on the [INAUDIBLE]
design.
But added the ability to represent time
windows on the activities.
Which is important for this kind of
robotic application.
Nonlins hierarchical task network
approach was also used in some of the
earlier research on the robots in Japan.
Assembly, integration and tests of the
payload bay for the European Ariane
rockets was carried out using a planner
based on the O-Plan design.
O-Plan has also been used in a wide range
of applications in emergency response and
search and rescue.
Edinburgh, AI planners have also been
used in applications as diverse as help
desks, tanker delivery, and many others.
Even the earliest AI planners were used
in realistic and practical applications.
The STRIPS planner from the early 1970s
was used to control the shaky robot.
And, as you can see from this table,
there's a range of planners over the
decades which have been applied to a wide
range of application areas.
And we're going to cover some of those in
a later module of this course.
As part of this cause, we're going to
encorage you to look at a number of
readings.
In particular, there's two reviews of AI
planning, which we hope you'll find
useful. One is from the 1990's, so it's
quite dated, but it does include a lot of
the work on those early planners and some
of the formative techniques as used in
them and that you'll learn about in this
course. And that's the Hendler, Tate in
Drummond paper in AI magazine, on AI
planning, systems and techniques.
Is also a review, a decade later, by
Wilkins and desJardins, on a call for
knowledge-based planning, where
techniques of knowledge-based systems,
and planning were being brought together.
Full details of these readings and the
locations where you can find the PDF
copies of them will be available in the
cource wiki.
Then there's a number of readings,
some of them very short readings.
on specific planners and their
applications.
And we hope you might dip into these
during the course.
If you've got time to read just a couple
of these, these are the ones we'd
suggest.
The initial review of AI Planners to
1990.
And a very short paper on O-Plan one of
the Edinburgh planners,
which looks at a wide range of techniques
and applications that were in use in
that, in that system.
There's a diagram in the 1990 review
paper which tries to trace some of the
historical connections between the
different planners.
The techniques they drew on and how they
build on one another.
It's worth looking at that in detail.
Perhaps you could pause the video at this
point and take a good look at some of the
techniques and areas in there.
There's an online version of this diagram
also available at high resolution if you
can't see it in the video that you're
using.