>> Earlier, when we looked at the planning
graph, I already mentioned that there is
something missing in this graph.
There are certain nodes missing, and there
were certain edges missing.
And that's what I said earlier, that there
were no mutex relations included.
So what we will do now is look at these
missing nodes, and we will also look at
the missing edges, which define mutual
exclusivity between propositions and
actions.
So that's what we'll be looking at next,
the mutex relation between propositions
and actions.
Earlier we have looked at independence
between actions in the same action layer.
We have seen that 2 actions in the same
action layer that are dependent cannot be
included in our final layer plan.
Now we will have a look at how this effect
propagates through the planning graph.
And first we will look at dependent
propositions, and here is an example.
This is part of the planning graph we have
looked at earlier, and you will note that
in the proposition layer p1, we have the
propositions r2 and ar.
That is the robot r is at location 2, and
container a is loaded on to the robot r.
The proposition r2 is present in that
proposition layer, because it is a
positive effect of the action Mr12.
The proposition ar is in that layer,
because it is a positive effect of the
action Lar1.
Now you may remember these 2 actions from
an example we have looked at earlier and
that showed that Mr12 and Lar1 are not
independent.
So these are dependent actions, which
means they cannot be selected from this
action layer for our final plan.
But of course if these actions are the
only reason why these propositions are in
this proposition layer, and these actions
cannot possibly occur together, that
means, the 2 propositions also can't
possibly occur together, at least not in
this proposition layer.
So that means, r2 and ar are incompatible,
in proposition layer p1.
Another example would be to look at the
propositions r1 and r2 in proposition
layer b1.
Clearly these 2 propositions are a
positive and negative effect of the same
action.
So if we include this action in our plan
we can't have r1 and r2 both be true in
p1.
So again they are incompatible in this
proposition they are, r1, and r2 are
incompatible in proposition layer p1.
So we have seen 2 reasons here why 2
propositions in a proposition layer may be
incompatible.
The first one shown by this example was
that we have 2 dependent actions that are
the only producers of the 2 propositions.
Then the 2 propositions must also be
dependent.
And the second reason was, that we had an
action, that had the two propositions we
were looking at, has positive and negative
effects, and that again means, they are
incompatible in that proposition layer.
Now, we will look at how we can simplify
this, by dropping two of the two cases,
namely the second case.
And we can achieve this by looking at the
things that were currently missing from
the planning graph and those are the no-op
actions.
So introduced no-op operations for a
proposition P and we give those the name
AP and the purpose of these is that they
carry forward the proposition P from one
proposition there To the next, so they
have only one precondition.
Namely that the proposition P is true in
the first proposition there.
And then, they have one effect that makes
the proposition true in the next
proposition layer.
They are, that means in this example we
would actually need 6 additional actions
in the action layer A1, 1 for each of
these proposition symbols that we carry
forward.
So, we have a No-Op operation for each one
of those.
I want to look at only one specific No-Op
operation though, namely the one for Ar1
that carries the symbol r1 forward.
And now let's look at the same example we
just looked at, in the second case of the
previous slide, where we looked at the
propositions r1 and r2, that were
positive, and the negative effects of
Mr12.
Now, we can see that, r1 is also a
positive effect, of Ar1, and r2 is a
positive effect of Mr12.
But when you think about it for a second,
you will see that these two actions are
not independent so they cannot occur
together in our final plan.
And that of course means that the two
propositions are incompatible in layer p1,
but this time for a different reason.
Namely because the two actions that add
them are incompatible.
So the introduction of the No-Op
operations means we don't have to
explicitly carry for or what proposition
Limbels from one layer to the next,
because the No-Op actions do that for us.
And they simplify our incompatibility test
for propositions in the same proposition.
Layer.
Now that you've seen these examples, it
should be fairly easy to understand the
definition, of what it means for 2
propositions to be mutually exclusive.
So 2 propositions, p and q, that are in
the same proposition layer pj are, mutex,
which stands for mutually exclusive, if
the following two conditions hold.
Firstly, every action in the preceding
action layer, tha'st Aj, that has P as a
positive effect, including the noop
operations, is mutex with every action in
Aj, that has Q a positive effect.
So if we find a pair of actions.
In the action layer aj that have p and q
as a factor respectively and these two
actions are independent, then we know that
we can also have p and q as propositions
in the following proposition layer.
And the other way in which we can have p
and q compatible in the following
proposition layer is if there is a single
action in Aj, that has both p and q as
positive effects or the other way around.
If there's no such action, then the two
propositions may be mutually exclusive.
In other words p and q are not mutex if
they are produced by a pair of independent
actions or by a single action.
I hope you understood this so far because
now I am going to confuse matters
slightly.
So, when I talk, I talk about independent
actions, but what's actually written here
in the definition is that we require the
two actions and the same action layer to
be mutex with each other, and that we
haven't defined here, but we will get to
the mutex relation between actions
shortly.
Now before I continue here comes a little
bit of notation and I want to introduce
the symbol mu Pj for the set of all pairs
of propositions p and q, all those pairs
that are in proposition their Pj and that
are mutex.
So mu Pj are old mutex pairs in
proposition layer Pj.
And for those of you who prefer algorithms
to formal definitions, here's the
pseudocode that defines mutex for
proposition.
Here we define the function mutex that
takes 3 arguments.
The first 2 are the 2 prepositions in a
preposition layer that we're trying to
test for mutual exclusivity.
And the third component is something that
we haven't seen, but as before this is
something we will see shortly.
This is simply the set of all mutex
actions in action layer aj.
Then we simply go through two Nestas loops
here.
The outer loop tests all the producers of
proposition p1.
So there should be an action a one that
produces this proposition.
And the inner loop simply takes the
actions that produce proposition p2.
So we test all possible combinations of
producers for the two propositions.
And if we find a single pair, a1, a2 that
is not mutex, that is not in our given
mutex relation between the actions, then
we can return false because we know these
two propositions can't be mutex.
We found a pair of actions that can
produce them and these two actions are not
mutually exclusive.
Otherwise, if we can't find such a pair,
then we return true, and we know that
these 2 propositions in their proposition
layer must be mutually exclusive.
Now you may ask, what happened to the
second part in the definition where we can
have a single action that produces both?
Well, this is actually covered by this
algorithm, when you select a1 and a2 to be
the same action, then it produces both the
propositions we're looking at, and of
course an action is never mutually
exclusive to itself.
So this case is covered with this simple
algorithm.
Now a quick word about the time complexity
of this algorithm and we see here that we
have two loops over all possible actions.
So if we assume that we have a maximum of
m possible actions including the no-op
operations, then this algorithm will run
in o of m squared because we're going
through two loops over all possible
actions and those are of course limited to
all the actions we might have.
So, it's polynomial.