This concludes the course on AI Planning.
You have seen that there are wide variety
of methods and techniques,
but that the basic technology for
representation and reasoning about plans
has some core principles, which are
broadly useful.
Practical applications of AI Planning are
in every day use and suitable problems
can be addressed by the methods taught on
this course.
You have now learned about the basic
techniques underlying most AI Planners.
This should allow you to read state of
the art research papers on planning and
you should be able to understand their
potential for problems you are working
on.
We hope you enjoyed the course and that
you will find the techniques useful and
relevant for your future activity.
Goodbye.
Bye.