>> So now we have seen the base beta
structure that we maintain including the
Mutext relations, we have seen how Forward
Planning Graph Expansion works, and we
have seen how backwards search in the
planning graph works, which means we now
can put all this together and finally come
out with the Graphplan Algorithm.
And here is the function graphplan, that
takes a propositional planning problem
consisting of a set of actions, an initial
state, and a goal description.
And the high-level structure of this
algorithm is as follows: we first expand
the planning graph, until we get to a
graph that may contain a solution.That's
what happens here in this part, and then
we try to extract the solution which
happens here and again in this loop, and
see If this fails, we've got to expand the
planning graph again.
So this loop continues to expand the
planning graph.
Now, also doing the backwards search in
the planning graph.
And now in more detail.
So we start by initializing some
variables.
I is the layer we're currently looking at,
searching at.
Then we have the no good table.
We have our proposition layer p-zero which
is initially the initial state.
And we have our planning graph which
initially only contains the proposition
layer p-zero.
Then, in this loop, we increase our layer
and we simply expand the planning graph to
include the next action and proposition
layer as we've seen earlier in the
definition of the function expand.
And, we have to continue expanding the
planning graph until.
All the propositions in the goal are
contained in our proposition layer, in the
last proposition layer, and none of them
are Mutex that's what these last two
conditions are.
But we also need to stop this loop when
we've reached a fixed point in our graph.
Then this loop is followed by this if
statement here, which simply tests the
reason why we have stopped our algorithm.
If we stopped because we found a
proposition layer that contains all our
goals and none of them are mutually
exclusive.
Then we can continue.
Otherwise, we have to return failure.
That means we basically stopped our loop.
Because we found a fixed point, but not
our goal yet.
So now we have a planning graph that may
contain a solution plan.
And the first thing we do is we remember
the size of the no good table here.
And the reason why we do this is because
this tells us when we have determinate in
our algorithm as we will see shortly.
So now we have reached the point where we
can try to extract the plan from our
planning graph and we do this here.
Star is now variable big pi.
And if this was failure so we can't find
the plan in this planning graph, then of
course one option is to expand the
planning graph with another layer, set of
layers.
And then again we try to extract a plan
from this planning graph that now contains
an additional action proposition layer.
And again, we store this in our variable
big pi.Now, if the return value is an
actual plan, that means we have won we can
return this plan as a solution.
So we test this in the next step we test
whether this plan was failure, and if it's
not, then we go to this loop if it's still
not failure then we come to the point
where we will return our solution Plan,
but if it was failure and we have reached
a fixed point in the plan, so an expansion
of the plan will no longer give us more
propositions or more actions in our action
layers, then we have to test whether we
need to terminate.
And condition for termination is now this.
If the size of the no-good table did not
increase.
So we still found exactly the same nodes,
and failed at exactly the same nodes.
Then an expansion of the graph will not do
us any good.
And that means we can return failure.
Otherwise, we store the size of the
no-good table, and remember that for the
next iteration of the loop.
So that was the detailed graph plan
algorithm.
And here are a few final words about
properties of the graph plan algorithm.
And in short, these properties are that
the graph plan algorithm is sound,
complete, and always terminates.
So this means that the graph plan
algorithm returns failure if and only if
the given planning problem has no
solution.
Otherwise it will return a layered plan,
the structure we've described before, that
is a solution to the given planning
problem.
And this plan will consist of a minimal
number of layers but that does not mean it
will consist of a minimal number of
actions of course.
So in that sense, it's not guaranteed to
be optimal.
But we have seen that Graphplan works on
the propositional STRIPS representation.
But again, remember, the STRIPS
representation can always be translated
into the propositional representation, so
that is not really a restriction.
The important thing here is that
Graphplan, when it came out, was really a
lot faster than all the previous planning
algorithms we've described so far.
So it was really a step forward in
performance.
And a lot of that has to do with the basic
data structure it maintains, the planning
graph.
The backwards search itself is of course
rather inefficient.
And still requires exponential time.
But is the reachability analysis that is
performed by the planning graph that gives
the algorithm a lot of power.
So, that was the Graphplan Algorithm.
Graphplan solves the same planning problem
as states based search or plan based
search.
But it does so in a very different way.
Namely by first generating the planning
graph, the basic data structure that
underlies its search.
And we have seen here the algorithm that
can be used to generate the Planning
Graph, which is Forward Planning Graph
Expansion.
And most importantly, this can be done in
polynomial time, and tells us something
about reachability of nodes.
And this Forward Expansion, together with
the Backwards Search, make up the Planning
Graph Algorithm.