[SOUND] We're now going to look at a
couple practical planners in operation.
You'll find some excellent online
resources for some of the well-known
planners listed in our table.
The course readings have also been
designed to introduce some of these and
we provide screen captures of a number of
our own Edinburgh planners in operation.
Nonlin was created in the mid-1970s, and
as mentioned earlier was applied in a
project using mixture of A.I.
and Operation Research, O.R.
methods, to create project plans for
electricity turbine overhaul.
It allowed for user-driven modifications
to the plans as maintenance inspection
took place and plans up to be updated.
Nonlin brought together range of A.I.
planning techniques, which were novel at
the time.
In this slide, I'm using the terminology
now commonly applied to these techniques.
Nonlin was a hierarchical task network
planner.
It could generate plans in which the
activities were not fully ordered.
It had been common up until that time for
A.I.
planners to generate plans which were
fully linear in order.
Nonlin searches in the space of planned
descriptions rather than in the
application state base,
a subject which we're going to cover in
the later module.
Nonlin uses the goal structure of the
plan in considering the different
alternatives.
So it always looks at different
approaches based on that plan rationale.
Nonlin as a mechanism for answering the
question of whether a proposition has a
certain truth value at a certain point in
the plan.
We call that the QA module, question
answering module,
is more often, nowadays, called the Modal
Truth Criterion that use condition types
to limit search.
It allowed for multiple contributors to
condition achievement in order to achieve
plan robustness.
It included compute conditions for links
to external databases and systems because
it was built as a practical planning
system.
These are similar to attach procedures in
some other planners.
And as mentioned earlier, is a mixture of
A.I.
and operational research methods,
so OR algorithms were used for time and
resource constrained reasoning.
Nonlin has been used as a basis for
textbook descriptions of hierarchical
task network planning.
O-Plan followed on from Nonlin and used
some of the same techniques.
It included domain knowledge elicitation
and modeling tools and supported a rich
plan representation.
It also was a hierarchical task network
planner and had detailed constraint
management.
It allowed for plugging constraint
managers, so that that that aspect could
be extended.
Gold structure-based planned monitoring
during execution was supported and it
supported dynamic domains in which new
objectives or tasks could arise while
planning an execution was taking place.
Plan repair when time was available or
when the situation demanded rapid
response was supported.
Interfaces for users with different roles
were provided in order that several
different users could be refining the
plan simultaneously and sharing
information about the plan between them.
And explicit management of the planning
and execution workflow was supported,
so the planner itself could be used in,
in these aspects.
There is a simple example of O-Plan
acting as a Unix system administrator's
aid.
The aim is to create a shell script that
reliably removes a volume group.
This is an application which a lot of
people have found difficult and can lead
to loss of files.
Once the current mapping between logical
volumes and physical volumes are, are
given by the drop-down numeric boxes, you
can just hit the plan button and the
planner goes off, and produces the plan,
and it prints it out as the script ready
to cut, and paste, and use.
Here's a more comprehensive example of
O-Plan running on a military operations
in urban terrain and where task
description planning and execution
workflow are all able to be supported
with multiple users acting over the
internet and all sharing a common plan.
so typically, there will be a task
assigner who will set up the problem.
It would go in and define this with
simple web form with drop-down lists of
the kind of tasks that can be carried
out.
And then, a planner can be called to
generate specific operations and, and
make suggestions of how to respond to the
particular emergency,
the particular disaster that's occurring.
And the idea is, that between the planner
and the task assigner,
they can talk and look at these options,
refine them,
throw away some replan when things are
being added, and so on.
And all this is occurring through these
user interfaces talking to the planner
behind the scenes.
O-Plan was used as the basis for
Optimum-AIV,
a planner for assembly, integration, and
verification of the payload bay of
Europe's Ariane rocket launcher.
It was originally designed as plan ERS-1
for assembly integration test of the
European Space Agency's ERS-1 spacecraft
shown here, on the left.
Optimum-AIV also used the rich plan
representation, hierarchical test network
planning, detailed constraint management,
plan and user rationale recorded.
It could handle issues arising during
planned execution and deal with it, these
through plan repair using test failure
recovery plans.
It was integrated with European Space
Agency's Artemis Project Management
System.
Let me draw your attention to a number of
features which are typical of practical
A.I.
planners.
Often, these are based on hierarchical
task network planning at an outer layer.
They often also allow for partial order
of the resulting plans rather than
insisting the plans are fully ordered.
They often include a rich domain model
that can manage many types of constraints
and include links to simulations,
analyses to refine then restrict the
plans.
These planners often allow for
integration with other systems,
user interfaces, databases, spreadsheets,
project management,
corporate systems of various kinds.
And this is very typical of practical
planners and often, much of the effort
that goes into a practical planning
application can go into this kind of
integration.