So, the next thing we're going to learn
about
is how to change variables in double
integrals.
So changing variables, when we did this
in, in Week 2,
I just called this the substitution method
or integration by substitution.
And so I'm going to, just to do a, a quick
review of that.
So suppose that x is a continuous function
and then g of x is a continuously
differentiable and invertible function.
Differentiable, I think I even spelled it
right.
So continuously differential just mean I
can take its derivative and the derivative
is a continuous function.
Invertible means that if I say x
is equal to g of s, so I have an s, I use
g to get an x.
Then there's another function g inverse,
so that I can
take g inverse of x and get my s back.
And that has to give me the same s that I
started with.
So,
something like a linear function is
invertible, but if I
had a parabola, so if I had y equals x
squared.
If I gave you x is equal to negative 3,
then
my function would give you, so negative 3
squared would be 9.
B but then if I, if I looked at 9, I
couldn't tell you if you
started out with a negative 3 or a
positive 3, so that would be a
non-invertible function.
So the
key thing here for g of s is that I have
to be able to
go back to the, back to where I started
from, back to my original s.
So this implies that g of s
is either strictly increasing or strictly
decreasing.
Although I guess it could have a flat spot
but then it
would have to immediately pick up again
right after the flat spot.
and so what I'm going to use g of s to do
then
is to map an interval c, d into an
interval a, b.
So if I have a variable s that lives in an
interval c, d then
I can find x by evaluating g of s, and
that's going to give me a point in a, b.
And the way I want to set this up is x has
to be able to take every value in a,
b.
And for every value x in a, b, there's
g-inverse of x that gives me a value in
c,d.
And then the same property has to hold the
other direction.
So for every s in c, d, I have to be able
to get a g of s in a, b.
So that's a, sometimes you hear the phrase
one-to-one and onto.
So it means for every s, there's a unique
x and
everyone in this interval goes to one in
this interval.
So there's for every point in a, b, I can
find in s in c, d that gives me that
point.
And for every point in c, d, I can find an
x in a, b so that g-inverse gives me that
s.
So then, integration by substitution says
that I can then switch
switch variables here.
So, I started out having a function of x
and this gives me a rule for changing that
into a function of s so
that these two integrals, these two
definite
integrals are going to have the same
value.
And so now, change your variables in two
dimensions.
I'd want to do the same thing.
But now, I have functions that are in
well, functions of more than one variable.
So let's let f of x, y be a continuous
function.
And I want to compute the double integral
over some domain D of f of x, y.
And so, when I was doing this in the
single variable case, I had
an integral a b for my first inter
interval a, b for my first integral.
And then I had an interval c, d
for the second integral, for the
transformed integral.
Now, I'm going to start out with an, a
domain D for the original integral.
And a domain
omega for the transformed integral.
And now, I just have to have two
functions.
So, I have a, a function x of s, t.
So, given s and t, this gives me a value x
and a function y of s, t.
So, given s and t, this gives me value y.
So, basically what I'm trying to do, I
have a 2-variable problem in x and y.
And I want to change it to two
different variables, s and t that are
functions so
that x and y are functions of s and t.
And then again, I need this relationship
to be one-to-one and onto.
That means for every point in omega, there
has to be a point in
d so that this relationship gives me gives
me the point in omega.
And then for every point
in D, there has to be a point in omega
so that this change of variables gives me
that point.
So it has to go backwards and forwards
giving
me, so I can always get my one point back.
And there has to be a one-to-one
correspondent so
one point in each interval corresponding
to the other.
And we also need this x of s, t and y of
s, t to be continuously differentiable.
And so the,
the thing I just tried to describe so
every point
s, t, and omega has to correspond to a
point x, y and D and vice versa.
This is just a just a way of writing that
down.
So that's what this, that's what I mean by
this double arrow here.
And so now what I want to be able to do is
I want to be able to find a function h of
s, t.
So that if I integrate f of x, y dx dy
over the domain D, I get the same answer,
I get the same value as if I integrate h
of s, t ds dt over this new domain omega.
And so I want to think about this as fof
x, y is equal to f, oops,
of x of s, t, y of s, t.
So basically I mean, this seems like a
sensible thing to do.
If I can get y in terms of s and t and I
can
get x in terms of s and t and I'll just
make my new function.
I'll write my function f of x, y as a
function of s and
t by first calculating x and y and then
plugging them in to f of x, y.
But we know this isn't going to get us all
the way, because this function of x and
y could be just 0 times y, in which case
it would just be a function of x.
And we already know that this does,
doesn't quite work for just
a function of x, I need to multiply it by
a derivative.
And so, we'll have to do some sort of
rescaling so
that we, we get the same value.
So in the single variable case, so if I
had x is equal to g of s then when I took
the derivative of both sides, I got dx is
equal
to g prime of s times ds, by the Chain
Rule.
And in the 2-variable case, I need to do
something analogous and unfortunately,
it's it's a bit more complicated.
So, it's complicated enough for even two
variables.
and you can just imagine what it's
going to look
like if you were trying to do three or
four.
[COUGH]
So in the 2-variable case, I have each
point x, y is a point, so
x of s, t, y of s, t.
And it's a vector-valued function.
So it has two inputs, s and t and it has
two outputs, x and y.
And so the gradient of this
transformation, so this two valued,
vector-valued function is going to be a
two by two array.
So remember, we used the notation capital
D for for the gradient.
And it's just the partial derivative of
the
first function with respect to s and t so
that makes up the top row of the gradient
and then the partial derivative of the
second function.
So the partial derivative of y of s t with
respect to s and then with respect to t.
So that becomes the second row of my
gradient.
So it's a two by two array containing all
of the first order partial derivatives of
a vector-valued function.
So then, the two-variable equivalent of
this operation here
is going to be dx dy equals and I take the
sort of the diagonals of this matrix.
So, I'm going to take the main diagonal
which
is this direction and then subtract the
other diagonal.
So it's the product of the main diagonal
minus the
product of the other diagonal so that's
just dx ds
dy dt.
So, dx ds and dy dt so main diagonal
and then minus the product of the other
two terms.
So that's this thing in the, the square
brackets here.
And I'm going to take the absolute value
of that times ds dt.
And that's going to be, if I, if I
multiply, so when
I, when I make the change of variables so
I replace f of x, y with f of
x of s, t, y of s, t then I have to
replace the dx dy with
this thing on the right-hand side.
And then those two integrals are still
going to evaluate to the same real value.
And so then this quantity inside the
square brackets here, this is called
the Jacobian of the change of variables or
the Jacobian of the transformation.
And so that gives me this 2 dimensional
change of variables formula.
So my original integral was an integral
over a domain D, a double integral over a
domain d of f of x, y dx dy.
And then I can change that into a double
integral over a domain omega,
which is the, the same domain but
expressed in terms of s and
t rather than in terms of x and y.
Then, I'm going to evaluate my function at
x of s, t
and y of s, t multiplied by the absolute
value of the
Jacobian and then I can put ds dt here
rather than dx
dy I want to evaluate these two integrals,
I'll get the same number.
So, let's look at the example.
So here, I have my
domain is my diamond again so this is
absolute value of x
plus absolute value of y, it has to be
less than or equal to 1.
And I want to do the, the same integral
over again.
And so, this is what I did last time.
And so I'd, I'd integrated first with
respect to y and then with respect to x.
And so now, I'm going to consider changing
variables.
So instead of using x and y, I want to use
s and t and I'm going to define s
and t so that s is equal to x plus y and t
is equal to x minus y.
And then remember, I need to calculate
this Jacobian and also, well, in this
particular case, one doesn't depend too
much on the particular values of x and y.
But I'm going to need, in general, for a
function of x and y, I need to know what x
and are in terms of s and t so I have to
first solve for x and y.
So just a, a little bit of Algebra
and substitution will get you to these two
formulas.
Then I can compute the partial derivatives
of
all of these so everything is 1 half
except
for dy dt, which is going to be negative 1
half because it's a minus t here.
And
then I'll compute the Jacobian, so I have
the dx ds
dy dt so it's the product of the, the main
diagonal.
So that's 1 half times negative 1 half.
So dx ds is 1 half dy dt negative 1 half.
Then I'm going to subtract the product of
the other two terms so 1 half and 1 half.
So that gives me negative 1 4th minus
1 4th, which is equal to negative 1 half.
So the Jacobian of this particular
transformation s equals x plus y and t
equals x minus y is negative 1 half.
And then I can plug that into my original
integral.
So my original integral was f of x, y
equals 1 over the domain D.
Then I can rewrite that as double integral
over a domain omega of
1 times the absolute value of the Jacobian
times ds dt.
And so the Jacobian was equal to negative
1 half.
The absolute
value of the Jacobian will be positive 1
half.
So, this gives me the double integral over
omega of 1 half ds dt.
So that's the easy part.
The tricky part now is what is this new
domain omega.
So I'm looking for values of s and t that
describe this diamond.
And these are the two functions I have.
So I have t is equal to x minus y and I
have s is equal to x plus y.
And so if I just, right now I'm going to
pretend they're 0 so t is 0 and s is 0.
And that just gets me y equals x, which is
this line here through the origin.
And x plus y or y equals minus x,
so that's just this line here through the
origin again.
So I have a line through the origin with
slope
1 and a line through the origin with slope
minus 1.
And now let's look at s equals x plus y
first.
So what's going to happen is I take
different values of s.
So in this, in this picture,
s is just going to be the y-intercept.
So by using larger values of
s, I'm just going to move this line up.
But the slope will stay the same.
And if I take negative values of s, that's
just going to move this line down.
But the slope is still going to be the
same because nothing's
changing on the right-hand side, which is
where the slope is determined.
And so if I want to cover this entire
rectangle with
s equals x plus y, I would want to go from
sort
of the, the line here, the x plus y line
that
gives me this side of the rectangle up to
the x
plus y line that gives me this side of the
rectangle.
And so that's going to correspond to the
y-intercept of this line here
is negative 1 and the y- intercept of this
line here is positive 1.
So s can range between negative 1 and
positive 1, and that just shifts this line
here
from this lower left edge of the diamond
up to the upper right edge of the diamond.
And then the same thing is going to happen
with t equals x minus y.
I want to go from negative 1 which will be
this lower right side of the
diamond up to positive 1 which will be the
upper right side of the diamond.
So the limit on
s and t are going to be minus 1 and
positive 1 for both variables.
So that gives me my domain of integration.
So it's now, I have taken this diamond
shape
in the original, in the original integral
and turned it
into a rectangle, in this, in this case a
square so it'll be easier to to do the
integration.
And so this is what I had the first time
so I had to split the integral up into two
parts.
But if I decide to integrate in my, with
my change of variables now, I have an
integral over omega of just 1 half ds dt
but I can replace that.
So, I can use Fubini's Theorem again with
ds
and dt just like I could with dx and dy.
So, I could replace this dA with ds dt and
now it's going to be a lot easier because
the, the integrals for, sorry, limits for
s so the inside integral, they don't
depend anymore on, on t.
So here, I can just do this as a, a single
integration problem.
And so just conceptually, what I'm going
to do is integrate 1 half over
minus 1, 1, so that's a rectangle of width
2 and height 1 half.
So that's going to give me 1 dt.
And now I'm trying to integrate 1 over the
interval minus 1 to 1.
So that's a rectangle of width 2 and
height 1.
So that just gives me 2 again.
And so, well to me, doing it this way was
a lot easier than doing it this way.
And we got the same answer.
So that's the idea of changing variables.
So the, the reason, let me make sure I
don't have another slide there, yeah.
So the reason you would want to change
variables are a, it's going to make
the integrand something that's easier to
integrate
or it's going to make the domain
something.
So if you can turn a odd shaped domain
into
a rectangle, that's going to make the
integration problem easier.
Or if you can,
by this change of variables, use the
Jacobian to introduce something
that you could then use in a, in a
substitution method.
you know, if you, if you want to use the
Chain Rule backwards you need the
derivative of your transformation.
And so sometimes you can use the, the
Jacobian to introduce that derivative of
your transformation and give your, give
yourself
an integrand that's easier to work with.