The topic for week 4 is Multiple
integrals.
So again I'm going to sort of follow the
same design I used in week two.
I'll start off just by defining what a
multiple integral is.
And because I want to be able to visualize
this, I'm just going to talk about double
integrals.
The second section is something called
Fubini's theorem.
And this is sort of like the, the
fundamental theorem of calculus,
gave us a way to evaluate an integral, a
single variable integral.
Fubini's theorem allows
us to use something called an iterated
integral
to evaluate a double integral or a
multiple
integral In section three, I'll talk about
something
called the change of variables for double
integrals.
So this is if I want to substitute one of
my variables with an expression,
how I can modify my integral so that it's
still evaluates to the same number.
In section four, I'll just go through and
extend an example
of that.
And in section five, I will show you that
there
is a certain class of double integrals
that are called separable.
Where without actually doing anti, any
integration, you can separate them to two
single variable integrals, and that will
make the calculation a little bit easier.
In section six, I will talk about one
particular
type of change of variables, which is
re-expressing the problem
in polar coordinates.
So, if the normal, if the original problem
was described in terms
of x and y, that would describe a point in
the plane.
Polar coordinates allows me to describe a
point in the plane using r and theta.
So r is a distance from the origin and
theta is an angle from the positive x
axis.
In section seven, I'll do something called
a culturally important integral.
So if you look at the standard normal
density, you'll notice there's this
1 over the square root of 2 pi out in the
front of it.
And that's because I wanted to integrate
to one.
And so I want to go through the argument
for why the, the
normalization factor should be 1 over the
square root of 2 pi.
So that's what we'll,
that's what we'll cover in topic seven.
And then in topic eight, I want to work
through calculating
something called the marginal density of a
bi-variate normal distribution.
So this is actually just single partial
integration exercise,
but it's a very complicated integral to
look at.
But again, it has, there are some tricks
that makes it easier to evaluate, and so
I want to go through them once in class
just so you have the opportunity to see
them.