[SOUND] AI Planners, using a generation
of action sequences in robots such as the
Freddy 2, Hand/Eye Assembly Robot
displayed here in the National Museum of
Scotland in Edinburgh.
This version of Freddy from four decades
ago had a large, fixed mounted arm with
sophisticated touch sensitive grippers,
and a side mounted camera to look at its
world.
Instead of the robot moving to reach
objects, the platform underneath the
robot was shifted instead.
Freddy was demonstrated on flexible
assembly tasks involving simple toy,
cars, and boats.
The video playing is taken from a 16
millimeter film of a Freddy project
demonstration made in 1973.
Freddy had to identify jumbled up parts
via vision, unscrambled the parts, and
then assembled them to create the
required product.
Some parts in the area didn't belong to
the target assembly.
In one project, the Edinburgh, normally
an AI Planner, was used to generate
object construction and arm movement
sequences for Freddy.
In its time, Freddy was one of the most
sophisticated robots in the world.
The Stanford Research Institute Problem
Solver Strips is one of the best known a
most influential AI Planners, and you'll
learn about it on this course.
Despite of being created over 40 years
ago,
it was already news control the activity
of a robot called Shakey at the Stanford
Research Institute, which is now call SRI
International.
Strips had may interesting features
including use in theorem proving
techniques to reason about the state of
points in the plan.
Strips gave us a representation of
actions with preconditions and effects.
It's got a mechanism called macrobes, for
generalization of its operators.
It included execution support facilities
to deal with partial failures.
Shakey is now on display at the Computer
History Museum in Mountain View,
California.
As we saw, Freddy included an early robot
arm, but as you can see here, technology
has come a long way.
For example, this modern research robotic
arm has many more capabilities.
Obviously, there's a lot more to robotics
than just activity planning and there are
significant challenges in terms of
vision, mechanical issues, and spatial
reasoning including locating the robot,
and tracking other objects.
But planning is a key aspect of
intelligent behavior.
Not every robot has the kind of activity
plan that we are describing on this
course.
That is, one which can plan from first
principles.
But robots typically do have plans,
perhaps precompiled ones, that they use
to control their behavior.
AI Planners have been used in much more
recent robots also, of course, such as in
some humanoid robots and the robots used
in the Annual RoboCup Soccer League
Teams.
Here, planning may have to cover the
coordination of different robots with
different roles, and the robots
themselves can have planners on board
that adjust their behaviors dynamically.
The planners have been used in different
kind of robots, too.
For example, an on board planner and
reactive execution agent was used to
autonomously control the NASA Deep Space
1 spacecraft prepared in its flight
rounding over the comet.
AI Planners have been used to provide
adaptability and flexibility robots in
the past and in the present,
in the factory, in the home, and in the
outer space.
And it's nearing which to put good use
tomorrow.
We hope you'll be part in creating this
future.