This is description of the Coalition
Search and Rescue Task Support Project.
Which is funded by the DARPA DAML Program
And it's conducted by AIAI [UNKNOWN] and
IHMC at University of West Florida.
So we're initially showing you the CoABS
grid manager.
And you can see that there's a number of
services which are running.
in particular, there'll be a JINI lookup
service.
And a number of other services running
directly on the CoABS grid.
Using KAoS for my IHMC and this provides
a directer service.
And we're running a domain manager named
dm1.
We then have two IX process panels
running.
CoSAR TS for the coalition search and
rescue panel.
And US-SAR for the US search and rescue
panel.
And we have two services running for
information lookup, called hospitals and
resources.
Four agent guides are running, which help
us to maintain policy across the use of
these agents.
Now we have, KAoS policy administration
tool, which is helping us set up and
maintain these policies.
So we have one domain which is running,
mini coalition, within this is the four
agency or previously, CoSAR, US-SAR and
then the two services, hospitals and
resources.
We're interested in limiting the kinds of
search and rescue resources which can be
chosen, depending on the flights that
these resources would have to make.
The countries that they will overfly.
So we're going to establish a new KPAT
policy, which we're going to call
gao-flight-restriction.
This is going to be a negative
authorization policy.
We'll choose from one of the available
actions available to us, and select that.
And within this slighted action we have
an available roll of has on country.
In this case, we're interested in placing
a restriction on a country, which is Gao
And then we can add that as part of the
policy specification.
That we have, we have home country Gao.
Then there's going to be a second part of
this policy.
Which is the country that we won't permit
overflights of Gaoen search and rescue
resources too.
So we'll say has rescue destination in
this case a limitation will be on the
contrary so basically Gaoen search and
rescue resources can not overfly arbelo
so you can see that we've got two parts
policy specification there.
And then we commit that policy and then
we want to distribute it.
So, we'll just show you now the four
agents once more within the KPAT tool.
And we can show you that for the
resources, agent we have that policy in
place.
So we're now going to move over to show
you the two process panels which are
available.
The coalition search and rescue
coordinator is going to be where most of
the action in the demonstration takes
place.
And then we're going to use a US-SAR
officer panel to initiate the action,
because they would have taken the initial
report about the downed airman because
he's a US national.
So in this case the US-SAR officer is
told to send any reports of downed airman
up to the coalition search and rescue
coordinator for their activity.
So, we'll take a look at the actions
available to us at the process panel can
support.
And we see there that's there's a way to
expand the description of this activity
is a particular built in standard
operating procedure.
And we get the expansion, which is five
substeps here.
We now look, take a look at the first
part.
And we see a way to break that down even
further.
You can see the indented sub process.
And we're going to look at the first part
of that, which is to establish the
medical capability.
Now, in this case, we know that we've got
a burned Ammon So we're going to use burn
care as the medical facility capabilities
we're looking up.
And then we're able to indicate that
we've done that manually.
Then we're going to use a service
available to us.
This is one of the services which is
registered.
So we can invoke the hospital service to
establish medical care,
establish the hospitals we have that can
deal with burn capabilities.
We're just showing you here that we know
about hospitals and indeed resources as a
service.
This is in the ice base two which
described services and in relationships
in that particular panel.
So we're going to invoke the hospital
service agent and it's going to now be
acting.
You can see it there it's already going
off and looking for, downloading
information from the, SONAT database
about Arabello and Binni in this case.
And it's checked, finding hospitals, and
that it's filtering those by the ones
that can provide burdened care.
We can take a look at that.
We can look at the details, look at the
kinds of hospitals available, where they
are and so on.
Find out that some can deal with a burn
carriage can see.
GahwadEl looks like a likely candidate.
We're going to, be interested in exactly
where the hospital is in relationship to
the downed hammond.
So we can perhaps best do that by looking
at a map of the facility.
This would be loaded from the information
known to the IX process panel.
You can see the pilot down in the sea
there.
And his condition report is in burns.
And you can also see the GahwardEl
Hospital.
which, as we noted before is, is, has
burned care facilities available.
So we're going to go ahead and slight
that hospital by binding the variable
appropriately.
And we can just tick that off as done.
And then we're going to look at the next
entry, which has established the country
that, that hospital is in.
You can imagine this being done more
automatically in future.
In this case we're going to indicate that
it's Arabello because that's what was
indicated in the information that came
back in the look up.
So now, that we've got our hospital
available, we're interested in selecting
the search and rescue results appropriate
to the task.
And we have a built in standard operating
procedure to remind us how to do this.
And in particular the first one is to,
look up the SAR resources available which
is going to invoke a resources agent.
This will use a soap connection over to a
CMU matchmaker, which finds these
appropriate search and rescue resources.
And we're finding some resources coming
back, and in fact only resources that are
allowed for all flights of arabello are
going to come back so chaos has already
been filtering the number of resources
found.
This case there are two that are
permitted and seem well to do the job and
we're going to choose the U.S.
Marine helicopter that's convenient.
It's in the right sort of location and
it's also helps us deal with the fact
this is a U.S.
Airman down.
So we're going to indicate that we
selected that resource.
By.
Oh.
We, we'll look at the map first just to
show you where that U.S.
Marine helicopter is.
So we're now going to show you we can.
Bind the variable for the SAR results
selected.
The US Marine helicopter.
And again we'll indicate we've done that.
Again you can imagine in the future much
of this could be done in a more automated
way.
And then we're going to notify the SAR
resource itself, this would best be done
by talking with the U.S.
SAR officer who would control that
resource so that it goes back onto the
process panel and when they themselves
have notified the helicopter pilot they
would indicate it's done and you would
see that the,
the, there's a cascade of done
information done to excess information
flying back up turning lue if we have not
find the hospital and we just going to
check what the outstanding issue was that
we're ask to just check it, as we went
along, and yes the country and SAR
resource chose nar allowed to get the,
and that was in fact constrained by the
KPAT policy.
So that concludes are demonstration.
Further information is available at some
of the URL's now being shown.
Thank you for watching the demonstration
of the course RTX project.