Previously we have seen how the general
tree search algorithm uses a strategy to
determine which node on the fringe to
explore next.
An example of such a strategy was a first
in first out queue.
We call this an uninformed source
strategy because it does not use any
information about the state itself, it
only uses information about when the
state was queued but nothing that is
internal to the state.
We will now look at heuristic search
strategies which use information about
the state on the fringe to determine
which note to explore next.
Information about a state that can be
used in a search strategy can be encoded
using a heuristic function.
In general, a heuristic function H, maps
a node in the search space to a real
number, R.
Or sometimes, you also find it maps it to
a natural number.
What a heuristic function encodes is the
estimated cost of the cheapest path from
the given node to a goal node.
So the heuristic function tells us how
close is the nearest goal node.
Obviously if the node N given to the
heuristic function is a goal node, then
the value must be zero.
That is, we are already had a goal node
so that nearest goal node is in distance
zero.
As you can see, a heuristic function
encodes problem specific knowledge in a
problem independent way.
For each problem we are looking at, we
can define a different heuristic
function.
Which is why the heuristic function is
problem specific.
But whatever search space we're looking
at, whatever problem we're looking at,
the heuristic function will always give
us a numeric value for each state.
And the fact that it is a number is
problem independent.
A perfect heuristic function would always
give us the correct distance to the goal
node.
But if we had such a function the search
wouldn't be very hard in fact it would be
trivial.
Unfortunately perfect heuristic functions
are very hard to find for most of the
problems we'll be looking at.
Best-First search is an instance of the
general tree search algorithm, where we
use the knowledge provided by the
heuristic function to decide which of the
nodes on the fringe looks best for
expansion.
In fact, Best-First search is a whole
group of algorithms, as we can use the
heuristic in various ways to decide which
node looks best.
And Best-first search can be used as a
tree search or graph search or algorithm,
depending on whether we use the test for
repeated nodes, or not.
In Best-First search, we use the
strategy, that uses an evaluation
function F, to decide which node in the
state space to explore next.
and again, the evaluation function maps a
node in the states space, to real number
R.
In general we will choose that node from
the fringe which has the lowest value F.
So the evaluation function determines the
search strategy in Best-First search.
Again, if we had a perfect evaluation
function we could use the search to lead
us straight to the goal node.
Note that the evaluate function is not
problem specific.
It is specific to the algorithm.
But the evaluation function may use the
heuristic function, which is problem
specific.
What we mean by best in Best-First search
is simply defined by the evaluation
function.
The node that is best has the lowest F
value.
Now, a quick word about the
implementation.
There are really two operations that we
need to support, when we look at our
fringe.
When we generate the successors of a
node, we need to add those to the fringe.
And when we select a node from the fringe
for expansion, we need to select the node
with the lowest F value.
Since we will do both of these operations
quite often during the search it is
important that these are cheap
operations.
The good way to implement this is by
means of a priority queue.
A priority queue maintains all the nodes
in the fringe, in ascending order of
their F values.
A priority queue can be implemented as a
binary tree, which means O adding a node
and retreading the node with a lowest F
value has a algorithmic time complexity.
The simplest Best-First search algorithm
is probably Greedy Best-First Search.
This algorithm simply uses the heuristic
function defined for the problem as the
evaluation function used by the
algorithm.
Remember that the heuristic function is
problem specific and encodes the distance
to the nearest goal node. Whereas the
evaluation function is not problem
specific and is used by the algorithm to
determine which node to expand next.
So the meaning of these two functions is
really completely different.
But Greedy Best-First search simply
equates the two and uses the heuristic
function to give us a search strategy
immediately.
The result is an algorithm that always
expands the node that is closest to the
goal node next.
The algorithm is called greedy because it
always tries to take the largest chunk
out of the remaining distance to the
nearest goal node.
It tries to get to the goal node in as
few steps as possible, but since the
number of steps isn't necessarily the
cost of a path, this is not necessarily
the optimal strategy.
In fact, Greedy Best-First search often
gives us solutions that are far longer
than the optimal path, and also far more
costly.
So let's look at our touring Romania
problem to see how Greedy Best-First
search works.
To remind you, the initial state was that
we are in Arad.
Now suppose our goal state is to be in
Bucharest, the capital.
The actions we have available are to
drive along the arcs shown in this graph.
And each arc has an associated cost, and
that is shown as a number next to the
arc.
So from Arad, I could drive to these
three towns and the costs would be
respectively this, this.
And this number.
What we also need for greedy best first
search is a heuristic.
And that's what we've got here.
The heuristic needs to estimate the
distance to the nearest goal node.
And our goal node is to be in Bucharest.
So we only have one goal node.
And on a map, we can use the straight
line distance to estimate the distance to
the, to a different point on the map.
So we will use the Euclidean distance
between two points on a two dimensional
map.
The table you are looking at simply gives
us the values of our heuristic function
for different nodes N.
So, if the node N is Arad, the distance
would be 366 rounded.
and so on.
For each city in our map, we have a
straight line distance in this table.
And this is the value we will use as our
heuristic value.
As is to be expected, the heuristic value
for the goal note is zero.
Another feature of this heuristic is that
it always underestimates the distance to
the goal.
Let's look at a simple example here.
For example, we have figure S.
Which, according to the heuristic, is 176
from the nearest goal node, Bucharest.
But, going back to the map.
You can see that from Arad, it really 211
from the goal node.
That is because roads don't tend to be
straight lines.
In reality, it is probably something like
this.
And that's a longer distance than what
the heuristic gives us.
So the real distance is 211.
But, going to the next slide again.
The estimated distance according to the,
the heuristic, is 176, which is lower.
Another important observation here is
that the heuristic presents us with
additional information to what we had in
the original problem description given by
the map.
There is no way you can compute the
values in this table from the information
given in the map.
And of course this table presents
problem-specific information.
Now, let us have a look at greedy first
search in action.
What we see here is the initial state of
the algorithm.
All the nodes you see are the fringe
nodes, and there's only one node, of
course initially.
Fringe nodes are shown in blue here.
That's the legend.
And the node we select to expand next is
shown in red.
So currently, there is no node selected.
Within each node, you see the name of the
city, plus the heuristic value for that
node.
Also, on the right hand side, you see
information about the depth of the
different nodes in the search tree.
So the first thing the algorithm does is
select a node from the fringe.
And since there is only one node, this is
the one that's going to be selected.
Then the algorithm performs the goal test
on this node.
Which will fail in this case, because
this is not goal node.The next step then
is to generate the successors of this
node.
So now, our initial state, Arad is no
longer on the fringe.
But its three successors are now the new
fringe.
This means we have to go through another
iteration of our loop.
And the first step is to select a node
from the fringe.
We do this according to the strategy.
Which tells us we've got to select the
node with the lowest f value.
So here, we have three nodes.
And the lowest f value is this one.
So this is the one we will select next.
Again, there's no, it doesn't not pass
the goal test, so we have to continue.
We generate the successors, and add these
to the fringe.
You can see what we are doing here is
tree search.
Because we've generated Arad again.
So this node is the original node.
And we could go back there immediately.
For most search problems, applying an
action, and then the reverse action
immediately afterwards is not a good
idea.
But let's continue with the algorithm.
So the next thing we have to do is select
another node.
And we select the node with the lowest f
value.
And here, that is Fagaras.
Again this is not a goal node so we have
to expand it and add its two successors
to the fringe.
Now we select a node from the fringe and
the node with the lowest F value is
Bucharest and this time the goal test
will toss so we finished with our search.
We can now extract the path to the goal
node simply by going up from our goal
node, the one that we found through the
tree, to the initial state and this is
our solution path.
That's it, that's how a greedy best first
search works.