In general game planning, a player may
choose to make
assumptions about the actions of the other
players or not.
For example, a player might assume that
the other players are behaving rationally.
By eliminating irrational actions on the
part of other players a
player can decrease the number of
possibilities it needs to consider.
Unfortunately, in general game playing, at
least as currently constituted, no
player knows the identity of the other
players or their characteristics.
The other players might be irrational, or
they
might behave the same as the player
itself.
Players might even be down, not
functioning correctly.
Since there's no information about the
other players,
many general game players take a
pessimistic approach.
They assume that the other players will
perform the worst possible actions.
This pessimistic approach is the basis for
a game playing technique called minimax.
Basic idea of minimax is to select moves
that are guaranteed
to produce the highest possible return, no
matter what the opponents do.
Player tries to maximize its own value and
assumes that the
opponents are trying to minimize its
value, hence the name minimax.
In
the case of a one step game, minimax
chooses
an action such that the value of the
resulting state
for any opponent is greater than or equal
to
the value of the resulting state for any
other action.
In the case of a multi-step game, minimax
goes
to the end of the game, and backs up
values.
Generally, we can think about minimax as a
search of a
bipartite tree, consisting of alternating
max nodes, shown here as gray squares.
And min nodes, show her as beige circles.
The max nodes represent the choices of the
player, while
the min nodes represent the choices of the
other players.
Now, in the case of games with more than
two players, it
can be multiple layers of min nodes
between each layer of max nodes.
One layer for each opponent.
now, also in looking at this tree, note
that although
we've separated the choices of the player
and its opponents.
This does not mean that the play
alternates between
the opponents or that the opponents know
the player's action.
Player and opponents make their choices
and then simultaneously, with knowledge of
each others, and, and simultaneously
without
the knowledge of each others' choices.
Okay, the value of a max node for a player
is the utility the
goal, the value, the reward at the
corresponding state, if that state is
terminal.
Otherwise, it's the maximum of the values
of
the min nodes that result from its legal
actions.
The value of a min node is the
minimum that results for any legal
opponent action.
Let's see how this works.
Following game tree illustrates it.
The nodes at the bottom of the tree are
terminal states
and the values are the player's gold
values for those states.
The values shown in the other nodes are
computed according to the rules we just
went over.
For example, the value of the min node at
the lower left is one because that's
the minimum of the two values of the max
nodes below it, namely one and two.
The value of the min
node next to that min node is three
because that's the minimum of the
value of the, values of the two max nodes
below it, namely three and four.
The value of the max node above these two
min nodes is
three because that's the maximum of the
values of the two min nodes.
And so forth.
Here's an implementation of a minimax
player.
It's identical to the implementations of
the compulsive deliberation for
single player games, except that it has a
different bestmove procedure.
The main difference between the bestmove
subroutine for single player games, and
the bestmove for multiple player games, is
the way the scores are computed.
Rather than comparing subsequent states,
it
compares the min nodes, as described
previously.
The minscore subroutine for minimax takes
an action and
a state as arguments, and produces the
minimum values for
the given role associated with the given
player for
any of the opponents legal actions in the
given state.
The maxscore subroutine, which is called
by minscore, takes state as argument,
and conducts a recursive exploration of
the game tree below that state.
If the state's terminal, the output is
just the roles reward for that state.
Otherwise, the output
is the maximum of the utilities of the min
nodes
corresponding to the player's legal
actions in the given state.
Now, one disadvantage to the minimax
procedure is that
it examines the entire game tree in all
cases.
While this is sometimes necessary, there
are cases where it's possible
to get the same result without examining
the entire game tree.
For example, if in processing a state the
max score subroutine finds an action that
produces
100 points.
It doesn't need to look at any additional
actions as it cannot do better.
Similarly if the minscore subroutine finds
an action
that produces zero points for the player
it
does not need to look at any additional
actions, as it cannot get the score any
lower.
Bounded minimax is just the minimax
procedure
we just saw with two minor changes.
Rather than processing all actions on
every node,
maxscore and minscore, first check for
these bounds.
And if they occur in any node, they
terminate their search, and return the
corresponding values.
So here's an example.
The nodes in this tree with are, are those
examined by bounded minimax.
The ones that have numbers on them, are
The other nodes are not examined at all,
and they don't need to be examined.
In this case notice that more than half of
the tree is pruned from consideration.
Note that 100 and zero are not the only
values that can be used here.
For example, if a player is in a so-called
satsificing game where it just needs
to get a certain minimum score, then it
can use that threshhold rather than 100.
For example, the player simply wants to
win and it's a
fixed sum game, then he can use 51 as the
threshold.
Knowing that if he gets this amount it has
won the game.