>> I've mentioned earlier that the
backwards search is actually a graph
search.
And here is how that works.
Suppose we are given our planning graph
with the ultimate goal in proposition
layer pk.
Then we go backwards through the graph and
somehow find some sub goals in this layer
pj.
And then we continue the search and this
may lead to a different set of sub goals
in our proposition layer pi.
Now suppose somewhere between pi and p0
the search fails.
So we come across and action layer where
we try to identify actions that achieve
all the sub goals.
But these actions are mutex, and therefore
we cannot find an appropriate set of
actions.
So the search has failed.
Then what we can do is, we remember that
in layer pi, we had these 3 nodes here
that together were not achievable.
So we continue with our backtracking
process, and we go back to layer pj, but
then from there we need to find different
actions, we go through different
combinations and we may end in our layer,
p i, again, choosing in a different way
the same combinations of preconditions or
sub-goals in this layer.
But since have seen the combination of
sub-goals in this layer before, and it was
previously not achievable in the planning
graph, we know that it still can't be
achievable so we don't need to do the
search again.
So effectively, what we do is remember the
search states we have encountered and
where we have failed.
That is, each search state is a set of
sub-goals in a specific proposition layer,
and by remembering these search nodes we
effectively do a graph search.
And we could just throw all these nodes
that we want to remember into a big hash
table.
But here's a more efficient data structure
that helps us remember what we've seen
before, the so-called nogood table.
The nogood table denoted by this symbol
here that looks like an upside down
triangle or as the Greek letter nebula is
For a planning graph up to layer k
consisting of an array of k sets of sets
of goal propositions.
So, we have k layers in our planning graph
and our array also have length k which
means each of the elements of the array is
for a specific layer, and then In each
layer we have a set of set of goal
propositions.
The inner set is one combination of
propositions that cannot be achieved.
So that effectively is a sub goal.
One surge node that we've looked at
before.
The outer set are all the combinations
that cannot be achieved at that specific
layer.
And there are really only two types of
operations we need to do on this data
structure.
Namely, before we are searching for
sub-goal, g, in our proposition layer, pj.
What we do is look in our no good table to
see whether we've encountered the sub-goal
before.
And remember we only star those sub-goals
where we have failed.
So we have to check whether our new
sub-goal, the sub-goal that we're
currently looking for is enabler of j, so
whether it Is in the jth layer and we
failed here before.
If it wasn't in that layer then we have to
search for the set g in this layer Pj and
this will either succeed in which case we
have found the plan, or it will fail and
then we have to add our sub goal to nabla
of j.
Remembering that this is a sub-goal at
which we have failed before in the j
proposition layer.
So, the mutex relation for each
proposition there, gives us pairs of
propositions that cannot be achieved
together.
The nogood table goes farther, as it gives
us sets of propositions that cannot be
achieved together in this proposition
layer.
Okay, now it's time to put all this into
pseudo code.
And this is the first of 2 functions that
we will define to perform the backward
search.
The function extract takes three
parameters.
The first parameter, capital G, is the
planning graph that we've generated
through our forward expansion mechanism.
The second parameter is the goal that
we're currently looking for.
This is originally the overall goal of the
planning problem.
And finally, the parameter I tells us
where in the planning graph we're looking
for this goal.
And we're looking for it in the I
proposition later.
Then the first thing we do is we check
whether the layer we're looking at is our
proposition layer P0, Because that means
we have reached pour goal so to speak, and
we can return the empty plan If this is
not the case, then we have to use the no
good table and we check whether our
current sub-goal is in the no good table
at layer I.
If this is the case, we failed here
before, and we can return failure again.
If we haven't seen this sub-goal g in
layer i before, then we call our function
gpSearch, that I'll explain to you in a
minute, which extracts a plan up to layer
i from our planning graph, and returns
that plan.
So this can be either a layered plan, or
it can be failure.
If it's unequal to failure.
So if we found a plan, then we simply pass
this plan through, we return this plan.
Otherwise, this is the case where we've
seen our sub-goal g for the first time.
We've tried to search for it, and we've
failed.
So that means, we need to update our noga
table, and we add our subgoal, g.
To the no good table at layer i.
And then, we simply return failure,
because we haven't found a plan at this
point.
So, as you can see, most of the work is
done in this function gpSearch, and that's
what we will look at now.
The function gpSearch takes four
arguments, the first argument is the
planning graph, the second argument is the
goal we are trying to achieve in layer pi.
So i identifies the layer in which we try
to achieve the set of goals, and Pi, are
the actions from layer AI, the action
layer AI, that we have chosen to add to
the plan.
And as we have just seen, in the
definition of the function extract, what
we actually pass in here are, the planning
graph, then the original set of goals in
that layer.
So that's all the goals in that layer.
The empty set, so we start with no chosen
actions.
And of course the layer I in which we're
doing all this.
Then the first thing we do in this
function is test whether the set g was
empty.
That is the trivial case and we will deal
with that later.
First I will look at the case where g
contains subgoals that we need to achieve
in layer pi.
And if this is the case then we select one
of those goals and this is denoted by the
proposition p here.
And then the next step is we use the
positive effect links to choose a provider
for this proposition.
And a provider must be as I just said a
positive effect, but it also cannot be
mutually exclusive with an action that
we've already chosen in our set, pi.
So this says there must not exist an
action a-prime in our set, pi such that a
and a-prime are mutually exclusive in
action layer a,i.
So this is the set of all actions in Ai
that we could use to achieve P, and we
call this set the providers.
Now, if the set of providers is empty,
then we can return failure.
So that means all the actions we found in
the action layer Ai were mutually
exclusive with action we already selected,
so we can't choose an additional actions
that would give us the proposition p.
In that case, we return failure.
But, if we have one or more actions that
can provide p, we need to choose one of
them and this is actually the choice point
where our search branches that means we
may need to come back here later when we
do backtracking and try out a different
action to provide.
So this is our backtrack point, but now we
have chosen a and that means we can
recursively call gpSearch.
We keep the same planning graph of course
but now all the positive effects of our
chosen action are no longer goals that we
need to achieve.
Of course, p will be one of them, but
there may be multiple positive effects
that can now be removed from our goal.
Then, we add the chosen action a to our
currently chosen actions in the set pi.
And we continue to search in layer i.
That means, every time we go through this
part of the algorithm, we reduce the set
g.
And eventually, we will come to the point
where this jet.
G is empty.
We have no more sub-goals to satisfy in
this layer, and we have chosen some
actions accumulated in the variable pi.
Then what we can do is what we call
Extract, as shown here.
So we give it the same planning graph, and
as the same sub-goal, we give it the union
over all the preconditions of the actions
in our set, pi, and we search for those in
layer i minus one, in the preceding
proposition layer, and this will return
either a plan or a failure.
If it did return failure, then we simply
pass this through.
And if it returned a plan, then we need to
concatenate this new layer, this new
action layer, the chosen actions in this
action layer To this plan, and return this
as the result of the function.
And that concludes the backwards search
through our planning graph.