So now I want to start talking about
something called the limit.
So in the, in the previous section we, we
came up with this
formula for, for a perpetuity which I'm
receiving an infinite stream of payments.
But that has a, a finite value, so you
know
that, value of this thing it's approaching
something called a limit.
but I want to sort of give you another
example where that's not going to work to
motivate
why we need to have a rigorous
mathematical definition
for what's going on here for, for our
limit.
So suppose, instead you know, I receive a
dollar in year one,
I pay a dollar in year two, receive a
dollar in year three and so on.
And I want to say what's the, what's the
present value of this sort of future
stream of payments.
So that's, that's kind of trying to couch
it
in the same terms I was using before, but
let's
just think of this as calculating the sum
of
one minus one plus one minus one, and so
on.
And so one way you could approach this is,
you could just draw parentheses around
every one minus one, and there would still
be an infinite number of these groups.
So I'm going to have plus one minus one.
So each one of these quantities is
going to be zero.
so then I'm just summing from k equals one
to infinity, the number zero.
And so, hopefully that would be equal to
zero but I, I've put, question marks about
some
of these equality signs because I want to
say that doing this might be kind of
dubious.
So if I could re-write it this way, then I
could.
So, this way I mean that.
So if I re-write it as plus one, minus one
as a quantity and then take the
sum of that.
If I could use the, the normal rules for
addition I could just split this sum up as
an infinite sum of positive ones
and an infinite sum of negative ones, and
rewrite it like this.
And so then again, you would think that,
you know, if you agree that this thing
up here is equal to zero, you should
probably agree that this here is equal to
zero.
But
now I can do something a bit tricky, so I
want to
use this same idea of you know, sort of
popping a few
terms off of my sum that I used last time
to, to
figure out what the value of an annuity or
a perpetuity is.
So in if I write this infinite sum of ones
well I'm just going to pop off the first
three say.
So I have one plus one plus one.
Plus the sum from k equals four to
infinity of one.
But it doesn't really matter what I use as
my index here.
It's just an infinite stream of ones.
So I'm going to replace this k with j.
But it's just going to be, you know, it's
a different name for the same thing.
It's a different index but it's just
going to start at one again.
So I have one plus one plus one and an
infinite stream of ones.
And so if I plug that in, I'm just trying
to
do the same trick that I did last time, of
subtraction.
So, I'll plug that in for the first one,
so my sum of positive ones
becomes this guy here and then I still
have my infinite stream of negative ones.
And now I have my sum of positive ones
minus
oops, sum of positive ones minus my sum of
negative ones.
So that should be zero but I've got these
three extra ones sticking out in front.
So now I get the value of this thing is
equal to three.
And so by using this trick I can make it
equal to anything I want to.
So you're not going to be able to do any
sort of arithmetic trick like I did last
time that's going to help you out trying
to
figure out what this thing is equal to
here.
Oops,
[INAUDIBLE]
, there we go.
So like I said I can make v equal to any
integer value by just choosing how many
ones I want to pop
off or if I want to to be negative I just
pop
off some of the negative ones from, from
this part right here.
And so, we want to try and think a little
bit about
[UNKNOWN]
what's different.
So, if we go back my, my formula for
the annuity or for the perpetuity, you
know, those
are in all sorts of investment science
textbooks, Econ
101 textbooks, so clearly they're probably
the right thing.
so what's different about that, then what
I've done here, when I've used exactly
the same trick to try and figure out what
this stream is equal to.
So first I'm going to start out with a
little
bit of notation.
So this is the notation that gets used
in the the textbook we Dan's Definica
textbook.
So, oops, r here is, set to real numbers.
So, real numbers
are just every single number that you can
write down using a decimal expansion.
This z with a funny little, type setting
is the set of integers.
So that's just whole numbers, but also
zero and, and negative numbers.
This symbol means in, so when I, when I
talk about
the real numbers and the integers, I'm
thinking of them as sets.
And a set is kind of a special
construction with one operation.
So something can be either in a set or not
in a set.
And that's all there is to sets.
And so this is the symbol I'm going to use
to say something is in a set.
[COUGH]
.
This upside down a is for all.
So if I want to say, you know, this result
holds for all combinations of the inputs.
This is the symbol I'm going to use.
backwards e means there exists
and arrow means goes to.
So, here we, we see the arrow.
This notation means a function g that
takes an argument that's a real number
and gives you an answer that's also a real
number, so g takes r to r.
So the, the notation here are these things
on the left and right of the x.
And they mean the floor.
So we think of x as a real number.
And then the floor is just going to be the
largest integer that's less than or equal
to x.
You know if x was three point five, then
the floor of three point five would just
be three.
And then you know hopefully this should be
pretty self explanatory after that.
If I turn these guys around we get
something called the ceiling so
that's just going to be the smallest
integer that's greater than or equal to x.
So again if I had three point three, the
ceiling of three point five is going to be
four.
And
then if I use this slash that's just
going to be not.
So if I wanted to say that x is not
in the set of intergers I would just write
this here.
So the z is the set of integers, the
kind of funny looking epsilon thing means
in, the
slash through it means not in and then x
is the number that I'm making a statement
about.
So x could be three point five, three
point five is not in the integers.
Okay, so for our definition of a limit, so
g is a function
that takes a real number and gives me a
real value to answer.
And that this notation just means that the
input can be
any real number, and the output is also a
real number.
It doesn't mean that I can get every real
number as an output of that function.
So even if I took, my function being x
squared, I'm not going to be able to get a
negative numbers out of that.
But its still every real number can go in
and
every number that comes out is also a real
number.
So that's what I'm giving up with this
notation here.
Okay.
So this is the definition of a limit from
from the textbook.
So the limit of g of x.
As x goes to x zero so when I say x goes
to x zero I'm thinking of x zero as one
particular point
and then I'm thinking of x as another as a
variable
and I'm moving that variable closer and
closer to this fixed point x zero.
So the limit of g of x as x goes to x zero
exists and
is finite and equal to, that's a l, kind
of in my strange projector font.
So it's equal to l if and only if for any
epsilon greater than zero, so
you generally in mathematics, when you use
the
letter epsilon you're talking about a very
small number.
But I want to say for any epsilon greater
than zero, but think of
this as small, there exists a delta also
greater than zero
so that the absolute difference between
the function value at x
and this limit, is less than epsilon, so
this is just
saying I can make my function very close
to this limit.
For
every value of x that's going to fall in
this
interval, x not minus delta, and x not
plus delta.
So that means there's a point, x not,
there' s a little interval around that x
not.
And for every x in that interval, my
function, is going to be
within epsilon of the limit value.
And so basically,
what, if I can find for any given epsilon,
so really what I want
to able to do, is find this number delta
as a function of epsilon.
And if I can say, then, for any epsilon
greater than zero, I can tell you the
delta, that makes the function, you know,
arbitrarily
close to the limit when it's within this
interval.
Then we're going to say that that value,
l, is
the limit of the function as I go to this
point x zero.
And then here is exactly the same
definition, sort of using all
of the short hand that, that shows up in
the text book.
So we have the limit.
So this lim is the abbreviation for limit
as x goes to x zero of g of x
equals l, this iff means if and only if,
so it's just an abbreviation for, oops,
this thing up here.
If and only if, for, so a,
upside-down a, for all, if and only if,
for epsilon
greater than zero, there exists a delta
greater than
zero, st is such that, and the
distance between g of x and l is
less than epsilon for all x that's
within delta
of x zero.
And then
similarly we're going to say, so here
we're talking about limits in
the first definition that are finite so
that means they go
to something else than infinity.
You know, if the limit is 100 the limit is
one, something like that.
There's some thing like if I say, what's
the limit of x as
x goes to infinity, obviously that's just
going to keep getting bigger and bigger.
So we also want to have a limit, a
definition,
for what we mean if, if a limit diverges.
So I'm going to set the limit as x goes to
x zero of g of x
is infinite if and only if, and now we're
just going to kind of flip this around.
So what I, what I was trying to say for
the first definition of
a limit, for when it's getting close to
something finite, is I want to get.
You know, within a certain neighborhood,
so that when
I'm in that neighborhood I'm within
epsolon of my limit.
I'm just going to flip that around and say
now
there has to be some c greater than zero.
And now
this c is supposed to be a really, really
big number.
Then I'm going to say there exists some
delta greater than zero.
Such that g of x is greater than c.
So c is a big number.
You know, any big number, so as big as you
want.
And I'm going to say now there's some
neighbourhood around x zero.
So a neighbourhood, so it's x zero minus
delta to x zero plus delta.
And if I'm in that neighbourhood, every
single point in that neighbourhood when
I evaluate g of x, I'm going to get a
number bigger than c.
And, what's going to happen is suppose I
find a c and I find a delta and now I say,
no I want it bigger, so I just take an
even bigger value for c, so say two c.
And my neighbourhood's going to get a
little bit smaller.
But there's still going to be a
neighbourhood that gives me values
greater than c.
And if I can find a function that has that
property, then I'm going to say that
g of x, the limit of g of x as x goes to x
zero, is infinite.
That means I can make g of x bigger than
any real number
that you choose just by choosing a value
close enough to x zero.
And this is, oops, this is exactly the
same statement but with some of the
things turned around, so now we have for
all
c less than zero and it's going to
negative infinity.
It's exactly the same thing I can now make
my function
value smaller than any real number, so you
give me any
real number, and I tell you, you choose a
neighbourhood of
this width and it will be less than that
real number.
If I can do that then we're going to say
that the limit as x goes to x zero of
g of x is equal to minus infinity.
And so the, this notation also tends to
give
some people trouble when you say exists,
and is finite.
So exists means you get something, well,
okay.
It's kind of circular, but that exists.
So infinity and minus infinity, these
still count as exists.
If you have something, and it tends to
show up more when you have a fraction.
But if you have something that's going to
zero divided by zero, or infinity divided
by infinity.
Those are things that don't exist.
So, that's the difference why you need to
say exists and is finite.
Most of the time, when people say exists,
they also mean it's finite.
So it's just something to be aware of if
you're
reading, reading a paper, and it doesn't
really make sense.
the exists probably also means
the limit is finite.
And then we also need to be able to
make sense of limits when x is going to
infinity.
So this is kind of what we had to do with
with calculating the perpetuity.
We wanted to say as n is getting bigger
and bigger,
you know, I can't say as x is going to x
not.
When, because I can't make this
neighbourhood of with delta around
infinity.
So we have to
have a slightly different definition for
this.
And basically, the way I'm going to, I'm
going to define this.
So the limit of g of x as x goes to
infinity is equal to l.
If and only if, for every epsilon greater
than zero,
there exists some number b.
So this is the same condition on sort of
the range of my function.
You know, the, the value of my function
has to be within epsilon of l.
And that's going to hold for every x
greater than b.
So basically what I'm going to do is just
keep
looking at bigger and bigger and bigger
numbers b.
Until I finally get to a number b where I
can say,
for every number greater than b, this
condition here is going to be true.
If I can do that, then I say that this
limit exists and is equal to l.
And so, we can use our pricing formula as
a little exercise to see how this is
going to work.
So we had for an annuity that had a fixed
number of payments.
We had a pricing formula I'm going to call
it v sub n.
So it's a value of annuity based on n
payments.
And we're just looking at what happens to
this as n gets bigger and bigger.
And kind of intuitively, you should think
that, well
if I just look at the, the limit as
n goes to infinity, we probably should get
the same thing, that we got for the
perpetuity.
And so that's the question I'm going to
try and answer.
And so the way I'm going to set this
up, is I want to say, for some number,
epsilon.
So this is the way you start out every one
of these arguments.
You say given epsilon greater than zero.
That'll be worth one point on the homework
assignment.
Find N such that the difference between
the
annuity and the perpetuity is less than
epsilon.
Whenever little n is
bigger than this value big n.
So what I want to do is find a value big n
say
its 1,000 then I know that if you know
little n is 1,001,
1,002, 1,003 this v sub n minus v is going
to be
the absolute value of that difference is
going to be less than epsilon.
So I just start out by writing down the
difference.
And so v sub n Is given by, I can't
highlight this whole thing I guess, well
the first term here.
And then the v is just the, the minus a
over r here.
And then if you look at this, you're
going to see that
you have a over r times one minus a over
r.
Or so, I guess I, I did the math here.
And you end up with just this thing in the
middle.
But we're taking the absolute value of
that
so the minus sign is going to go away.
And so this is an expression for the
absolute value
of the difference between my annuity
formula and my perpetuity formula.
And now what I want to do is solve for a
big N.
And this big N has
to be an integer that has the property
that,
for any little n greater than that big N.
This condition holds, and basically the
only reason I'm dividing epsilon
by two is I need to have it strictly less
than epsilon.
And so the easiest way to do that is to
say, if I can make
it less than or equal to epsilon over
two, epsilon over two is certainly
strictly less.
Then epsilon, so that's just going to get
my definition you
know, without having to worry about these
kind of corner cases.
So now it just becomes an algebra
exercise, you know, I'm looking for n here
so I'll just move the a and the r over to
the right hand side.
Then I'm going to take the logarithm of
each side.
And we have this property of the logarithm
that the
log of something to a power is oops, that
power.
So in this case, n times the logarithm of
the base.
And then divide through by one plus r.
And then you have to be a little bit
careful here because, on
the left hand side, this n, I want that to
be an integer.
But on the right hand side, I think you're
going to be hard pressed to
find values of a, epsilon and r, that are
going to make this an integer.
and it needs to be true in general
anyways.
So, this is why we're going to use our
ceiling operator.
So I'm going to
choose my capital N.
Just to be the, the next biggest integer
after this things that we found here.
And then for any n greater than capital N.
Well I've chosen this n so that this thing
holds.
Oops, the middle part holds.
this less than or equals to I guess I was
just
being a little sloppy when I made this
slide, that's actually equality.
We've shown, you know, that the only way
that we could have the equality here is
on the off chance that I did pick a, r and
epsilon, so, this exactly an integer.
so I've used epsilon over two here to
solve for n.
And that's going to be strictly less than
epsilon, so I'm able to show
that regardless of what value of epsilon
you tell me, I can tell you a value
of n that's going to make my annuity
formula and my perpetuity formula less
than epsilon apart.
And so in that case, we're going to say
that the
limit of the annuity formula as n goes to
infinity
is equal to capital N, or sorry, is equal
to the perpetuity formula, is equal to
capital V.
Okay, so summary for our limits, thing.
Our limits section.
So, given epsilon greater than zero, we
can find we can find
capital N such that this difference is
always, the absolute value
of this difference is always less than
epsilon for any epsilon that you tell me.
So that way I can say, that the limit of V
sub n as n goes to
infinite, is equal to V.
And then, again, this is, our definition
of the limit, so the limit as x
goes to x zero of g of x is equal to l if
and only if.
For every epsilon greater than zero, there
exists a delta greater than zero, such
that the absolute value of the difference
of g of x and the, the limit
is less than or, is less than epsilon
whenever x is within delta of x zero.