In the previous segment, we have seen how
the planning problem can be solved by
searching for solutions but we've set up
two completely different types of search
spaces.
One was the state space and one was the
plan space, but both approaches really
solved exactly the same problem.
In the next segment, we will modify the
problem itself so the approaches we've
seen so far are no longer applicable.
Previously, a planning problem contained
a goal, and a goal was a condition on a
world state that we want to achieve.
Now, we will look at tasks.
Tasks are things we want to do.
You may remember the example from the
introduction going on a holiday,
that would be a task, and I've already
mentioned then that this would be
difficult to describe as a goal because
we want to end up in the same state in
which we started.
So, we will now look at tasks and task
networks, which are the essential
components we're dealing with in
hierarchical task network planning.
So, we will start by defining simple task
networks.
Simple task networks are really a
simplification of the more general
approach which is called hierarchical
task networks or short, HTN.
You've already heard about HTN planning
in week 1 when my colleague, Austin Tade
was talking about planning in context.
But let's start from scratch here.
A lot of what we've seen so far carries
over into task network planning.
For example, we have terms that can be
either variables or constants to describe
the objects in our domain that we're
dealing with and we have literals that
express propositions that are either true
or false.
We also have operators that describe
types of actions that we can execute in
our domain.
And, of course, we have their instances,
which are actions which we want to
execute.
The semantics is still based on state
transition systems so we also have a
state transition function that describes
how the world evolves when we execute our
plan.
And, of course, we still have plans which
are the solutions to our planning
problems.
But there are a number of new components
that we need to consider in task network
planning.
And the first component are, of course,
the tasks themselves, the things that we
want to do in our domain, like going on a
holiday or fixing a car or learning
something on this course.
Simple tasks corresponding to actions
directly but, of course, we often deal
with tasks that are more complex, like
going on a holiday is rarely a task that
we can consider as directly executable.
The next new component of the methods
that describe ways in which we can do our
tasks.
And this description usually consists of
a number of subtasks that, together,
achieve some more complex task.
And these subtasks, in itself, can be
organized.
They can be ordered with respect to each
other, for example,
and thus, form a task network.
So, what we will do now is formalize
tasks, methods, and task networks, and
then define planning problems based on
these concepts and what solutions look
like and finally, algorithms that solve
this type of problem.
Let me illustrate all these with another
example taken from our Dock Worker Robots
domain.
As you can see in this picture here, this
is a very simple problem.
We have a single location at which we
have one crane and we have three piles
and three containers.
Currently, all three containers are in
the first pile and we want to move these
containers to the third pile.
So, our task is to move a stack of
containers from pallet p1 to pallet p3.
And we want to do this in such a way that
the order of the containers is preserved.
Clearly, this is a task that we cannot
achieve with any of the actions we've
previously described.
It is a more complex task.
We could, of course, describe this as a
planning problem that we've seen so far,
but here is a set of informal methods
that we can use this type of problem in
general.
And I will start at the bottom here.
So, the first method we can have is to
move a container from one pile to another
pile and, of course, we can only ever
move the topmost container.
So, we have a method for moving the
topmost container and we say this method
is simply a take action followed by a put
action.
So, we have two actions that are ordered
with respect to each other that make up
this method of moving the topmost
container.
So, this is a very simple method that
simply groups two actions together.
A more complex method is to move the
whole stack and we can do that by
repeatedly moving the top most container
from one stack to other.
We must do this until the stack is empty
and if we do this, of course, a side
effect is that we reverse the order of
the containers in our new pile.
And we can fix that last problem by
having a third method which says we move
via some intermediate stack so we first
move our stack to an intermediate stack
and that reverses the order of the stack.
And then we move it to the final
destination and we reverse the order
again.
So, these three methods taken together,
describe a way in which we can move a
pile of containers from one pallet to
another pallet, respecting the order of
those containers.
I hope you can see that this approach is
much more akin to the way humans solve
problems, and this is by hierarchical
decomposition and identifying abstract
concepts.
Here, we've identified the more abstract
concept of a stack that didn't exist in
our previous domain description.
And now, we can formally define what we
mean by a task.
And the first thing we need is a set of
symbols that we can use to give unique
names to our task.
And these are the task symbols given by
the set Ts, consisting of t1 through tn.
Now, our operator names, which are the
name of the operators we are using, must
be a subset of our set of task symbols.
And if, for a given task symbol, we also
have an operator name that corresponds to
this task symbol.
We call this task symbol a primitive
task.
And then, we have the non-primitive task
symbols which are simply those task
symbols for which we don't have
corresponding operator names.
A task then is simply a syntactic
expression of this form.
It consists of a task symbol ti, which
can be either a primitive task symbol or
a non-primitive task symbol.
And it consists of a series of arguments,
r1 through rk which are the terms
representing objects that are manipulated
by this task.
This is, of course,
very similar to the way we've defined
operator names and that is not a
coincidence.
And similarly, we will define ground
tasks as all those tasks for which all
the parameters are ground, which means
they are actual objects and not
variables.
A ground operator was called an action,
but we don't have a special name for
ground tasks here.
This means we have four types of tasks
here.
Tasks can be primitive or non-primitive,
and they can be ground or unground.
And to relate tasks to actions, we can
make the following definition.
Suppose we are given an action a which is
described by the name op c1 through ck
where op is an operator name and c1
through ck are constants representing the
parameters of this action.
Remember, it's an action, so it's fully
ground.
So, these must be constants and not
variables.
We can say that this action accomplishes
a ground primitive task described by the
expression, ti r1 through rk, in a state
s, if the following two conditions halt.
The first condition states that the
syntactic expression that describes the
action and the syntactic expression that
describe the task must be the same so the
must have is that the name of the action,
as given here by op must be the same as
the task symbol and, of course, it's
primitive tasks so we have an operator
name that corresponds to it.
And we must have that all the arguments
must be the same.
So, the first constant must be equal to
r1 and so on.
And, of course, because these are all
constants, r1 through r k must also be
constants otherwise they couldn't be
equal.
So, the first condition is that the
syntactic expressions for the two, action
and task, must be the same.
And the second is that the action a must
also be applicable in the state s.
So, what this gives us is a way of
accomplishing very simple tasks, namely
those tasks that are ground and
primitive.
But we can't accomplish unground or
non-primitive tasks yet.