>> The problem with the planning graph
heuristics we have looked at is that they
are not very accurate.
Especially where the goal consists of
multiple conditions.
Pattern databases can result in very
accurate heuristics, but there's a lot of
overhead involved in computing the
database and they're usually only for one
specific goal so if the goal changes we
need a new database.
Now we will take a closer look a the
heuristic used by the FF planner.
Ff was developed by Jor Kauffman who
presented this week's feature, and the
heuristic it uses is quite remarkable,
because it is both efficient and accurate.
So, let's have a look at the FF Planner.
Planner.
The first thing to note about FF is that
it performs a forward state-space search.
Which is the technique we've described in
the second week of this course.
That means that planner starts from the
initial state and generates more states
going forward into the search space until
it encounters a gold state.
And.
The basic search strategy can be a star in
f, f, but there is a second strategy
implemented, and that is called enforced
hill climbing.
Enforced hill climbing is a kind of best
first search, where we commit to the first
state that looks better than all the
previous states we have looked at.
One advantage of this technique is that it
copes well with search spaces that have
large plateaus.
That is, large sets of states that all
have the same evaluation function value.
And this is quite often the case in
forward states based search.
However, the early commitment, taken by
enforced hill climbing can lead to degrees
of sub-optimality.
And in the worst case, it can not give us
solutions at all.
Namely, if the search space contains dead
ends.
But this segment is about advanced
euristics, so let's take a look at the
relaxed problem heuristic, which is the
heuristic used by f, f.
So, the first step is to construct a
relaxed problem that we need to solve as
part of our computation of the heuristic.
And, the relaxed problem used by FF is one
where we ignore the delete lists of all
the operators.
So we take our original problem, and
remove the delete lists, the negative
effects from all the operators.
And this is our new problem that we use to
compute the heuristic.
And the important thing here is, to solve
this relaxed problem, we only need
polynomial time.
That means the heuristic ids efficient to
compute.
And the solving of the relaxed problem
works in two steps.
The first step is a forward chaining step
where we build something that is similar
to the planning graph we've seen earlier.
But this time it's a planning graph for
the relaxed problem, that contains way
fewer edges and information.
Then in the second step we chain backward
from the last layer on this graph to
extract out relaxed plan from this graph.
And while the forward chaining is quite
similar to what graph plan does, the
backward chaining is actually quite
different.
The result of backward chaining is a
relaxed plan.
And then to compute the heuristic, we
simply take the length of the relaxed
plan, that is the number of actions in
that plan as our heuristic value.
That is the relaxed problem heuristic or
ignoring delete list heuristic used by FF.
Another improvement implemented by FF is
that it prunes its search using helpful
actions, and in that way it uses
information gained during the computation
of the heuristic to improve the search.
Another important technique, but not
related to advanced heuristics, so we
won't go into details here.
And here is the idea of the relaxed
planning problem applied to its, the
example we have used earlier.
What we see here are the 3 operators from
our simplified dock worker robot domain,
where the robots had cranes to load and
unload.
Containers and to compute the relaxed
prime problem we simple remove all the
delete list that is the negative effects
from all the operators.
So, we remove the not A (r,l) from first
operator then not in (c,l) and not
unloaded (r) from load and not loaded from
the final operator.
It's that simple.
What this gives us is a planning problem
that contains some magical objects, for
example looking at the first operator when
we move the robot r from location l to l
prime, the precondition is that the robot
is at location l.
And as a result of this operator we will
have the robot at location l prime.
But because we've removed the negative
effect, the robot would still be at
location l.
So it's now in both places.
And the same goes for the containers in
the other actions.
The containers, after a load or an unload
action, remain the place where they used
to be but they are also in the new place
where we just put them with this operator.
And that's the problem we need to solve to
compute the relaxed problem heuristic.
And here is the pseudocode that performs
the forward chaining, and computes the
relaxed planning graph.
And this is defined by a function
computeRPG for a relaxed planning graph,
takes as input, a planning problem, and
this is already the relaxed planning
problem.
Then the first thing we do is some
initialization.
And we start off with a set of fluents.
These are state propositions that hold in
the initial state.
And we have an index t that tells us where
in our planning graph we are.
And this is followed by a loop, that
extends our planning graph with one action
layer, and one proposition layer at a
time.
This is this loop.
Loop here.
And the first thing we do in this loop is
increase the index of the layer we're
currently working on, that's here.
Then we compute the next action layer,
which consists of all the actions that
have their preconditions satisfied in the
preceeding proposition layer or layer of
fluence[INAUDIBLE].
F.
So that gives us the next action layer A
t.
And we need to compute the next
proposition layer F t.
And we start by initializing that with the
propositions that were true in the
previous proposition layer, F t minus.
And then we go through all the actions in
our preceding action layer, and add the
positive effects that come with these
actions to our layer of propositions,
giving us an extended layer of
propositions.
Then there are two ways in which this can
terminate.
The first one is given the condition in
the while loop up here.
And that says, we terminate when all the
goal conditions are part of our last
proposition layer that we generate here.
And the other condition is down here.
That says when our proposition layer is no
longer increasing then we can return
failure.
Because that means we're still in the loop
so, our goal conditions are not part of
the last proposition layer and we don't
increase that layer and therefore we can
return failure.
But, if we terminate this loop normally,
which is here, then we go to the next
statement after the loop which simply
returns the relaxed planning graph we have
generated here.
While this is somewhat similar to the
expansion of the planning graph, you will
have noticed that we are not computing any
mutex relations here And that also means
that our relaxed planning graph will be
smaller than the planning graph generated
by graph plan, because this condition for
termination is actually much simpler, and
we terminate sooner.
Now that you've seen how to compute the
relaxed planning graph, here is the
function that extracts a plan from this
graph, and returns its size as the
heuristic value.
And the first input to this function then,
is the planning graph, all the layers
including proposition layers and action
layers, and the goal that we're trying to
achieve in this planning graph.
And the first thing we do in this function
is test whether our goal is contained in
the final proposition layer.
If it isn't, then of course, we can return
failure because there can be no plan in
this graph that achieves the goal.
Otherwise, we continue by computing the
last layer in this planning graph that we
still need to consider, and that's what
the variable M has.
And the way we compute this is that we use
a new function, first level, which we
haven't introduced that.
So, this function takes here, a goal and
the layers in the planning graph, and
tells us in which layer this goal first
appears in the planning graph.
So it gives us the index of the first
layer.
Of this goal in the planning graph.
And M, is then simply the maximum of all
the values for all the goals.
Then we can start with the backward
chaining.
And the way this function works, we don't
simply start at the last layer but we
start in different layers and we don't
just move one layer at a time towards the
initial state but we can actually skip
several layers.
And here is how that, That works.
We use the variable Gt to hold all the
goals that need to be achieved in
proposition layer t.
And we initialize the different sets Gt
with all the original goals that were
given to the function.
And we do this by going forward through
the planning graph, which is what this
loop here does.
And we add the goal component to GI to the
set GT.
If it appears in the layer T for the first
time.
So if the first level in which GI appears
is, indeed, T.
And now that we've assigned all the goals
to the different sets, GT.
We can go backwards through the graph,
starting from layer M to 1.
And search for actions that achieve these
goals in the corresponding layers.
And if we are in layer t, then the goals
we need to achieve are stored in the
variable Gt, and what we have to do is,
find actions for each component of that
layer Gt.
So, for each Gt, we need to select an
action that achieves that goal component,
and that means Gt has to be a positive
effect of that action, of course.
But, we have a further restriction on the
set of actions we can choose from.
Namely that the action also must appear
for the first time in this level T.
So this is what this function computes.
The first level of A in all the action
levels must be T.
And then once we have chosen an action of
course we need to add all its
pre-conditions as sub-goals to our
structure G.
And, what we do is we don't just add the
pre-conditions to the preceding layer
which would be T minus 1 as new goals but
we may skip several levels.
And the level where we add this
precondition P, is simply the level in
which P first appears in our planning
graph.
So this is the minimal index such that P
is in the proposition layer.
That is the index where we add P as a new
goal condition to our set G.
And of course this loop terminates when
we've reached T equals 1 because F0 of
course responds to our initial state.
And then after we've finished with this
loop all that remains is the final step
and that is to count all the actions in
our extracted plan and return that as the
heuristic value.
Now, you have seen the heuristic computed
by the FF planner and used for it's
search.
Here is a summary of the result.
The heuristic that we've computed is of
course, not admissable.
That means FF is not guaranteed to return
a minimal plan, but this heuristic is
quite accurate.
And that means, FF finds the plan
reasonably fast because it has to explore
a smaller portion of the search space than
planners that use a less accurate
heuristic.
And also, the heuristic is efficient to
compute.
Because, as you will have noticed, both
the functions I've just introduced can be
computed in polynomial time.
The overall result can be summarized quite
nicely with the following statement that
I've taken from Urich's slides, that he's
using at his home university.
And this reads almost all current
successful satisficing planners use
variations of some of these ideas
introduced in FF.
And here is a quick summary of what we've
learned about advanced heuristics, the
first heuristics we've looked at are
simple planning graphs heuristics but can
be extracted more or less directly from
the planning graph but are not very
accurate.
Then we've looked at pattern database
heuristics which are very accurate but
have significant overhead in their
computation which can be done before the
search for a plan.
But they're also not very flexible, in
that the database needs to be recomputed
for different goals or different objects
in the domain.
Then, we've had a look at the FF Planner,
and specifically, at the heuristic it
uses, which is based on the idea that we
solve a relaxed problem in which all the
delete lists have been removed from all
the operators.
And this is really one of the state of the
art heuristics that is used in planning
today.