What you have just seen is the overview
of a generic plan space search planner.
The reason why we've looked for the
overview first is so that you can
recognize the generic search structure
that underlies this algorithm.
Now, we will look at some of the
implementation details that come with
this algorithm and that were hidden and
the function used by the generic
algorithm.
The first function used by the plan space
planner is the function that extracts the
Opengoals from a given plan.
And instead of computing these open
goals, afresh every time we go through
the loop, we will do this incrementally.
We start off with out initial plan pi 0,
that has just the 2 dummy actions in it
and goal.
And the question now is, what are the
unachieved sub goals in this initial
plan? And the answer is simply that these
are the gold conditions that are the
pre-conditions of the goal dummy act.
So our goal conditions from our planning
problem are our initial unachieved
sub-goals.
Then we have to modify the set when we do
one of two things.
When we add an action to the plan we have
add all the action's preconditions as
unachieved sub-goals to our set.
So we increase the set of unachieved
sub-goals every time we add an action to
our partial plan.
And when we add a causal link we decrease
the set of unachieved sub-goals.
And we decrease it by the preposition
that is now protected in this causal link
and is no longer unachieved.
This precondition of an action is not
supported by a casual link and is no
longer an unachieved sub goal.Next we
have to complete the threats that exist
in our current partial plan and again
we'll do this incrementally rather than
compute them every time we go Through the
loop.
And we start with our initial plan pi 0
that simply contains no threat.
So that is very easy to compute.
The other cases are a little more
complex.
New threats can be introduced into our
plan every time we add an action to our
plan.
So suppose we're adding our action A new
to our plan consisting of the usual
things.
Then what we have to do is follow this
procedure to check whether.
A new threat has been introduced with
this action.
The way we do this is we go through every
causal link that is currently in our
plan, and we have a loop variable here
that represents this causal link as going
from AI to AJ, protecting proposition P,
and for every such link we have to check
the following.
The first one is, we check whether our
new action is already ordered, before ai,
or after aj.
So if the new action, is before the
provider, or after the consumer, that
means it cannot be imparital, to our
causal link.
Which means, it cannot threaten that
causal link, and we can just simply,
continue with the loop, go to the next
link.
Otherwise that means the action can be in
parallel to our link.
It need necessarily but it can be.
And then we have to check every effect q
of our new action.
And if there is such an effect q that can
be unified with p such that q and ~p are
equal.
q and p are complimentary then and only
then is q of anew a threat for our causal
link.
Of course, this only applies if the
substitution is actually consistent with
out binding constraints.
So this was the case where a newly
introduced action may threaten an
existing causal link in our partial plan.
The other way where we can add new
threats to our partial plan is when we
add a causal link, from ai, to aj,
protecting proposition p, to our current
partial plan.
And when we add this new causal link to
the plan,
this may be threatened by any action that
is already in the plan.
So what we've got to do is, we've got to
loop over all the old actions in our plan
that already existed in our plan.
And check whether they pose of threat.
Again, if this existing action is either
before the provider or after the
consumer, then this action cannot be a
threat.
And there's a third condition here,
namely that our existing action is the
consumer in our causal link.
Of course, the consumer of a causal link
cannot threaten that causal link.
So, if one of these three conditions
hold, we can go on to the next action
because this Existing action we're
currently observing cannot possibly be a
threat to the newly introduced causal
link.
Otherwise, we have to observe all the
effects of our existing action, and do
what we did before.
We've got to see whether this is
unifiable with our protected proposition,
and if this is the case, if these two can
be made complimentary by some
substitution that is consistent with our
binding constraints, then we have the
case where we effect q of our existing
action a old threatens are newly
introduced causal link from ai to aj
protecting proposition p.
In summary, we have no threats initially
but every time we add an action to the
plan that means we can threaten an
existing causal link with this new action
and every time we add a causal link to
this plan to the partial plan then this
may be threatened by an existing action
that is already in the plan.
Now that we have detected the two types
of potential flaws that can exist in a
partial plan we need to look at the
function that can remove these flaws and
this is this function here getResolvers,
the Resolver is a way of removing a flaw
from a plan.
And we will first look at the flaw that
is an unachieved precondition in our
partial plan.
And we will consider the precondition p
of action ag.
And there are two principal ways in which
this type of flaw can be removed from the
plan and in which way can be resolved
namely by adding a causal link and by
adding a new action and a causal link.
Let's start with the causal link along.
This is a causal link to an existing
action so what we going to do is see
whether there is an existing action in
our plan , so we go through all our
existing actions in the plan to check
whether there can be a provider for this
unsupported pre-condition.
The first condition then is that we have
to make sure that our existing action can
be ordered before the consumer, and the
consumer, of course, is ag in this case.
So, if our existing action is the
consumer, or it is already ordered after
the consumer, then we cannot use it as a
provider, because it cannot come before
the consumer, so we can just consider the
next action.
Otherwise, if it may come before the
consumer, then we've got to check every
effect q, of our existing action, to see
whether this can be used as a provider.
And again, what we do, is we try to find
the substitution, consistent with our
variable binding constraints such that p
and q are equal.
If we can find such a substitution, then
adding a causal link to our plan, is a
resolver for this thread.
And the causal link we need to add is,
from our currently existing action, to
our consumer, protecting the link sigma
of p.
So we instantiate our proposition with
the substitution we just found.
This was the case where we used an
existing action in our plan to provide
support for an unachieved precondition.
The alternative is, of course, that we
introduce a new action into our plan that
supports our unachieved precondition.
And to check whether this is possible,
we've got to loop over all the operators
in our planning domain and check every
effect q of every operator to see whether
this can be used as a provider The first
step is, that we look for a substitution
sigma, that makes p and q equal.
Note that we don't have to worry about
the variable binding constraints in this
case, because all the variables in q,
that we've just introduced with the new
operator, are of course new variables,
and have no bindings yet.
If we find such an operator, then we use
an instance of this operator as a new
action in our plan.
So this is the new action we need to add
to the plan.
And we also need to add a causal link to
the plan and this causal link consists
of.
The link from a new, the provider, the
action we just introduced, to our
consumer, ag.
And again we protect the condition sigma
of p, the instantiated proposition, that
is an unachieved pre-condition of a g.
And these two things together, provide
our result for.
So if our flaw is an unachieved
precondition.
we can remove this flaw by either adding
a cause link from an existing action or
we add a new action and a causal link
from that new action to our unachieved
precondition.
Now lets look at the case, where we have
an action at, that is threatening a
causal link ai to aj, protecting
proposition p.
And lets see how we can getResolvers,
that remove this type of flaw from our
partial plan.
For an action to be a threat to a cause
link it must be at least potentially in
parallel to that cause link so one way to
remove this type of flaw is to simply
order the action either before or after
the cause link, And we can order the
action before the threatened link under 2
conditions.
The 1st 1 is that the threat must not be
the provider and the 2nd is that it must
not be already after the consumer.
If neither of these 2 holds, then we can
add an ordering at before ai and that is
a resolver for our threat.
The other ordering that resolves this
threat, is to have the action come after
the causal link or the causal link before
the action.
However, if our threatening action is the
provider in our causal link, then we
cannot use it.
Or similarly, if the action is already
ordered before the provider, then we
cannot order it after the causal link.
In all other cases,
ordering or threatening action after the
consumer is a resolver for this type of
flaw.
The other way in which this type of flaw
can be resolved is to add variable
bindings such that the unifications that
we computed earlier will fail.
And here is how we can do that.
Remember it is the effect q that
threatens our proposition p here, so what
we do is we go through every variable v
that occurs in p or q and try to make the
unification fail on that variable.
So if we computed earlier our
substitution of v must be a specific
value, sigma of v, then.
Asserting that our variable v must not
have this value is, of course, a
potential resolver, but it is only a
resolver if this is consistent with the
variable bindings currently in our
partial plan.
If it is consistent, then this is a
resolver.
Adding this variable binding constraint
is a resolver for our flaw.
In summary threads can be removed from a
plan by either ordering the threatening
action before or after the cause of the
link or extending the variable bindings
such such that unification of the
offending effect and the protected
proposition fail.