So, now we'll look at higher order partial
derivatives.
So, remember for a function of a single
variable I could say d squared by dx
squared of f of x when I wanted to talk
about the second derivative of f of x.
And what I meant, what I mean by this
notation is take the
derivative of f of x with respect to x one
time, the thing
in the square brackets here, that's going
to be another function of x
and then I'm going to take the derivative
of that, again with respect to x.
And then I can also use the notation.
So, the derivative of x with respect to x
I can call, sorry.
Yeah.
Derivative of x with respect to x.
So, I'll call that f prime.
And if I take the derivative of that
again, we use the notation f double prime.
So for a function of several variables,
I'm going to do
pretty much the same thing, except just
with partial derivatives.
So for instance, if I wanted to take the
derivative with respect to x so the
second derivative with respect to x,
second partial
derivative with respect to x of a
function.
E to the xy.
So, maybe highlight that part at least.
What I mean is take the derivative take
the partial
with respect to x of e to the xy.
That's going to give me another function
of x and y.
And then take the partial derivative of
that function with respect to x again.
And so if I just go ahead and evaluate
that, I'm going to end up with y
times e to the xy, by taking the
derivative of this with respect to x once.
And then another y will pop out when I
take the second derivative,
so I end up with y squared e to the xy So
there's a bad
example of how not to do the chain rule,
by just doing it all explicitly.
Hm-mmm.
And then similarly if I want to take the
second partial,
second partial derivative of e to the xy
with respect to y.
I'm going to do exactly the same thing,
except I'm just
going to have partial y's in the
denominator And in this
case, this is such a simple function I
could just
relabel the x and y, so we can kind of
skip
the computation and just see that the
output is going to
be, in this case, x squared times e to the
xy.
But for functions of several variables
there's now also
the The possibility of something called a
mixed partial derivative.
So I'm going to keep the same idea as I,
as I had in middle
section of the slide where I take the
derivative with respect say the partial
derivative of my function with respect to
one of the variables and repeat except
when I repeat I can take the partial
derivative With respect to a different
one of the variables.
So in this case, I'm going to take the
partial derivative,
first with respect to y, and then with
respect to x.
So you can kind of think of this thing
here as an operator.
And so, it's going to do something to this
function.
And the part that's closest to the
function that's going to happen first.
[INAUDIBLE]
.
So if I were to write this out using
slightly longer form.
When I say partial squared, partial x,
partial y.
I mean, first take the partial derivative
with respect to y of my function.
That's going to give me another function
of x and y.
And I'm going to take the partial
derivative
with respect to x of that function.
So, here, I've just evaluated the first
partial with respect to y.
So we got the same thing we got up here.
But now, this time, it's going to be
slightly more complicated.
Because I'm going to take the derivative
of this now with respect to x.
So now this is a product of two functions
of x.
So.
X is the first function, and then e to the
x y
is my second function, so I have to use
the product rule.
And so again just to make this all fit
on one slide, I've skipped, probably some
essential work.
But I hope it's, I hope it's correct.
So I have the derivative of the first
function times the second function.
So the derivative of x is going to just be
one.
So the first term in the product rule is
going to to be e to the xy.
And plus the first funtion times the
derivative of the second.
So I'm going to take X times the partial
with respect
to x, of e to the x y.
We already worked that out above, too.
So I have e to the x y plus x y e to the x
y.
Oops, going to write down here.
Okay, my arrow's not working anymore.
There it goes.
And somehow this is going to probably
bring up the question what
is the relationship between, so here I'm
doing the mixed partial.
Taking the partial derivative with respect
to y
and then the partial derivative with
respect to x.
X.
And here it's just the other way around.
First, with respect to x and then with
respect to y.
So we already saw that if I did it y first
then x, this is the function that I got.
[INAUDIBLE]
.
And
now let's look at what happens when I do
it with respect to x first.
And then with respect to y.
So first, I'm going to take the partial
derivative
with respect to x of e to the xy.
And that's just going to give me y times e
to the xy.
And now again I have to use the product
rule to take the derivative of this.
So it's, the derivative of the first
function,
so the derivative of y with respect to y,
is just one, times the second function, so
that's where this e to the xy comes from.
Plus, the first function, so that's my y
here.
Times the derivative of the second
function.
And we've already worked this out, this
was just x times e to the xy.
So I end up with e to the xy plus xye to
the xy, which is what
we got for the first one.
And so when I have this.
Sort of, very symmetric with respect to
differentiation function.
I find that the mixed partials are equal.
So, it doesn't matter if I do dx dy, or dy
dx, I get the same, same result.
So, but this function that I chose, it was
easy to work with in terms of taking its
derivatives.
But, because of this symmetry, maybe we
should try it with a, a little
bit more complicated function to see what
happens.
So I think I chose this function from the,
from the text book.
it was not fun to take the derivatives of
this.
So to get the second partial with respect
to y and then respect to
x, first I'll start out by taking the
derivative of this with respect to y.
So let's see.
So the first thing I'm going to do is make
my
u substitution, just to avoid making
mistakes with the chain rule.
Usually what, what gets me is the minus
sign up here, because
that's, if there's a minus sign here and a
minus sign here,
for some reason I tend to have about a 50%
chance of missing one of those.
We're getting it wrong I suppose.
[SOUND]
So,
I also did the partial derivative with
respect to y
of the first term here just because it was
easy.
So by the power rule the y is just y to
the zero.
So I have x squared.
Plus the partial derivative with respect
to y of e to the u.
So that begs for the chain rule.
And so that's just going to be the
derivative of e
to the u with respect to u, which luckily
is ease,
e to the u, times the partial derivative
of u with respect to y, which
I'm going to get just exactly like the
first
example by taking the derivative of my
substitution.
So let's see what I end up with here.
So I have x squared minus 3 xy squared e
to the minus xy cubed.
And in fact since we've already taken the
derivative of this
a few slides ago, I didn't have to do this
bit.
I could've just used the derivative I'd
already computed.
And so now I want to take the derivative
of this guy, the partial derivative with
respect to x.
So again I'll do the, the first term,
just because the derivative of x squared
is easy.
By the power rule I just get two x.
And then this minus is going to appear
here.
And then I'll take the derivative of this
term by treating it as two functions.
3 x y squared, and e to the minus x y
cubed.
And so I'm taking the derivative now with
respect to x.
So, the derivative of the first term,
that's easy.
That just got x to the 1 so the x is going
to go away so I end up with 3y squared
times the second function.
And plus the first function so there's my
3xy squared times the derivative of the
second function
[SOUND]
And so, just, plugging all of this in and
distributing this minus sign,
gives me this, and now all I have to do is
plug in, what
u is, and what partial derivative of u
with respect to x is, which I got just
Again, by taking the derivative with
respect to x this time.
And so, I end up with this somewhat
unhappy looking formula here.
But, at least it's something that doesn't
look
like it's going to have a lot of symmetry.
Like if I changed the x and y, they
shouldn't be the same.
And so now we'll repeat the same
calculation,
but here I'm going to use x first.
So this time the last time I did y first,
and now this time I'll do x first.
So again the first term's going to be
pretty easy to do, so we'll just do that.
Second term I'm going to make my u
substitution,
so I can see myself using the chain rule.
So I'll let u equal minus x y cubed,
again.
So the first part, I'm treating y as a
constant, and then
taking the derivative of x squared, so the
power rule just says
that's going to be 2x, and then times y,
and then I need
to take the derivative with respect to x
of e to the u.
So by the chain rule, that's going to be e
to
the u, times the partial derivative of u
with respect to x.
Which again, I get just by taking the
derivative of my substitution.
And
now I need to take the partial derivative
of this with respect to y.
So again the first term is going to be
easy, that's
just y to the one, so that's going to be
two x.
And the second term I'm going to need to
use the product rule,
so the functions will be y cubed and e to
the u.
So, the product rule says it's derivative
of the first function,
so this is the derivative of Y cubed by
the power rule.
Times the second function, plus the first
function times the derivative of the
second function.
And so we've done this several times
already, so
just skip this line and just plug in the
results.
Oops, two times.
And so we get another Sort of unhappy
looking formula.
But I think on the next slide I put them
together, and those were actually the same
formulas both ways.
So that sort of gives us some hope that,
probably these
things are equal, regardless of what order
you take the derivative.
And.
If you take a more serious math class, you
can actually prove this.
I'm just going to give the, the statement
of
the theorem.
So, if all of the partial derivatives of
order k.
So, order k means how many times I've
taken a derivative.
So, if if I take the second
partial derivative, that's a derivative of
order two.
Of the function f of x exist and are
continuous.
Then the order in which the partial
derivatives of f of x of order at most k.
So, as long as I don't try to go beyond k.
Then the order that I do those derivatives
doesn't matter.
I'm going to get the same mixed partial.
And so, just like I made an array to hold,
the first
derivatives, I need to make an array now
to hold, the second derivatives.
And this array is going to be called the
Hessian
of f of x, and we can use the notation.
D squared so that two just
means essentially just take the derivative
twice.
But in this case because we're talking
about
functions, you know, so the first one has
n inputs, then I end up with the gradient
which
has n outputs, so that's a, a function
that has n
When I evaluate the gradient at one point
I get n results.
And then I'm going to take the derivative
of that again so
I'm going to get an n by n array of mixed
partial derivatives.
And so down the, the diagonal of the
array, so the diagonal for
some reason, when people say that, they
mean top left to bottom right.
this going up bottom left to top right.
It's also a diagonal but nobody means that
when they say diagonal.
So the diagonal elements are just going to
be taking the derivative,
the partial derivative of the function
with respect to the same variable twice.
So In that case, I can kind of compact
this notation.
This means partial x one, partial x one.
But it's the same thing, so I just write
it as squared.
And then in the off-diagonal elements
[COUGH],
the, the first row, I take the derivative
with respect to x one.
The partial derivative with respect to x
one first.
So the x one is going on the right side,
here.
And then I take the partial derivative
with respect to x whatever column I'm in.
So if I'm in the second column, I take the
partial derivative with respect to x two.
If it's the nth column, I take the partial
derivative with respect to x n.
And,
remember, because of the theorem that I
had on
the last slide, this function here and
this function here,
so this is x1x2 and this is x2x1, so
if this function is well behaved, then
these two terms will be
equal.