So far in this course we have looked at a
number of ways of solving planning
problems efficiently.
That is, we have assumed that we were
giving a planning problem.
But a planning problem is a very specific
artifact.
And to get to this artifact requires a lot
of work.
So we have a lot of problems we need to
solve before we can start planning and
that's what we will look at now briefly.
The first problem that we need to solve
before we can do any planning is the
knowledge engineering problem.
One thing we have learned on this course
is what the planner takes as input, namely
a planning problem consisting of an
initial state, a goal, and a set of
operators that we can use to move through
the state space.
And for a planner to use this as input,
all this needs to be represented in a
formal language, such as PDDL.
Knowledge engineering is really everything
that we need to do to get from the first
informal problem description to this
formal representation that we can give to
a planner.
And this involves the problem of problem
formulation that I've already talked about
when I've introduced you to the
missionaries and cannibals problem.
And problem formulation is really vital
for the efficiency with which we can do
problem solving.
If the operators we choose to represent
contain too much detail then the state
space can explode exponentially and we
cannot solve problems anymore.
But that is only one of the concerns
during knowledge engineering.
There are others like how adequate is the
knowledge we have represented or how easy
will it be to maintain in the future?
There are now tools that we can use to
perform the knowledge engineering for
planning domains.
And these tools support one or more phases
of knowledge representation as shown here.
The first phase that we need to go through
is the requirements specification.
This is where we talk to domain experts
and try to find out what they expect from
the system that we will build as a result
of this process.
Then the second phase is knowledge
modelling where we take the knowledge that
we have extracted from the experts in the
first phase and built a formal model but a
fomal model that the experts can still
understand and critique.
So it needs to be fairly high level.
Then we can do a model analysis, which
involves verification and validation,
finding out whether the model is adequate
and captures all the knowledge that we
need.
Then we can deploy the model, which means
we have to export our domain specification
in a language and formalism that a planner
can understand.
This is then followed by plan synthesis
which is essentially what we've looked at
in this course.
And finally we can do plan analysis and
post design which is we look at the
generated plans, go back to the experts
and show them is this really what you
wanted.
Are these plans useful to you?
What criteria do we have to assess these
plans?
And overall this is an iterative process,
so that means we can go back to any phase
at any time and start over again to
improve the model.
As you can see, knowledge engineering for
planning domains is anything but trivial.
But there is an alternative approach to
doing all this manually, and that is to
try to learn planning domain model-[SOUND]
The basic idea here is, that you build a
system that can observe what is going on
in a specific domain.
And derive operator descriptions, that
describe how the state of the world as
changes, as the system sees it.
This has been done recently for the game
of Freecell, where a system observed the
game playing for a while and then came up
with a formal system of operators that
described how to play this game.
One of the problems that keeps coming up
during knowledge engineering for reasoning
about actions and change is The Frame
Problem.
An to explain this to you I need to go
back in time a little.
Back when people were first looking at
planing problems in the '60, a very
popular field in [UNKNOWN]AI and in which
a lot of progress was being made was
automated[UNKNOWN] imprving.
So one of the earliest approaches to
solving planning problems, then, was to
transform a planning problem into a theory
improving problem.
And doing that involves writing a set of
logical axioms that represent what changes
in the world when an action happens.
There were, of course, axioms expressing
the preconditions of an operator, and
there were axioms expressing the effects
of an operator.
But it turned out for a theorem improver
to work you also have to write down
explicitly what doesn't work when an
action is executed.
And in fact, the list of things that don't
change when an action is executed, is much
longer than the list of things that do
change.
So the problem was, that we needed to
represent a long list of facts that are
not changed by an action.
And the frame problem in general, then, is
to construct a formal framework for the
reasoning about actions and change in
which the non-effects of actions do not
have to be enumerated explicitly.
The formal framework that was used
originally was first order logic, and
using theorem proving as the problem
solving technique.
And the specific set of relations and
functions that were used to represent
operators in first order logic, are known
as the situation calculus.
Now, there are a number of ways in which
the frame problem can be approached and
the first one was to ask the question
whether we can use a different style of
representation so we don't use the
situation calculus but we use a different
way of encoding the same knowledge in
first-order logic so we keep the
formalism.
And while there has been some progress
with this approach.
The problem of enumerating non effective
actions explicitly did remain in some way
or other.
The second approach, then, was to use a
different logical formalism.
So, instead of first order logic.
We may be able to use a more complicated
formalism that can encode the knowledge
better.
And 1 good candidate was always non
monotonic logic.
And again there has been some progress in
that area.
But theory improves for non-monotonic
logic are not very efficient.
And the third approach was to simply write
a procedure that generates the right
conclusions, in our case plans, because
its solution is built into the procedure.
And that third approach is basically what
we've been following on this course.
But you should be aware of the frame
problem which has to do with the
representation of non-effects of actions.