What we still need to formally define is
when an action is applicable in a state,
and what the corresponding state
transition is.
To do this I will first introduce a
little notation.
Suppose we're given a set L of literals.
So, these are positive and negative
atoms.
Then I can use this here, this symbol L
plus to refer to those atoms that are
positive in L and I can use L L minus to
refer to those atoms whose negations are
in L.
So L plus and L minus are sets of atoms
namely those that are positive and
negative in L respectively.
Now, let A be an action, and S be a
state.
And when I say action here, I mean
action, a ground instance of an operator.
Then we can say that the action A is
applicable in the state S, if two
conditions hold.
Namely, all the positive preconditions of
A, preconditions plus, of A, must be a
subset of the state, S.
And we also want none of the negative
preconditions of A to be in S and this
can be expressed by this expression.
The intersection of the negative
preconditions and what is in the state S
must be empty.
In other words there can not be a
negative precondition that is also a true
in the state.
A is applicable in S if all the positive
preconditions hold in S and none of the
negative preconditions hold in S.
And now we can define the state
transition function gamma for a given
state.
That's the state in which we are
initially.
And the action A that we are applying in
this state.
And this can be defined as follows.
We start off with the state, and we
deduct all the negative effects.
As I told you earlier, this is the delete
list.
So we delete this from the state.
And then we add all the positive effects
so we add them to the state.
And again, I've already explained.
This is the add list.
So we start off with a set of ground
atoms.
We remove some ground atoms and we add
some ground atoms.
And this is the state that we get as a
result of applying the state transition
function, in state as using action A.
One minor point that is of quite a lot of
importance and some detail, is that we
first delete the negative effects and
then add the positive effects.
That means, if there is an atom that is a
negative effect and a positive effect.
It will be in the resulting state because
it is first removed and then added again.
You may wonder, why would you ever want
to have an action that has the same atom
as a negative and positive effect.
Well, maybe have look at the move action
that we've just introduced.
And see whether this would ever be
possible that an atom can occur as a
negative and a positive effect depending
on what values I choose for the
variables.
Finding the actions that are applicable
in a given state is actually a non
trivial problem.
You can see this quite easily when you
think about the number of possible
actions that may be applicable in a given
state.
Namely, all those operator instances
where you replace every parameter by
every possible value.
That would give you an exponential number
of actions.
In general there are way fewer actions
applicable in this state, though.
And here is an algorithm that you can use
to find the applicable instances of a
given operator in a given state.
This function, add applicables, takes
five parameters.
The first is A, the set of actions and
this is initially empty.
This is just the set in which we collect
the result of this functions for the
applicable actions.
Then we give it an operator of which we
seek instances that are applicable in our
state.
We have a set of remaining preconditions
of this operator so these are the
preconditions we still need to look at.
Initially these are all the preconditions
of the operator.
Then we have a substitution for the
variables that are parameters of the
operator.
Initially no variables are replaced by
values.
And then, of course, we have the state in
which we are trying to apply this
operator.
So, the algorithm will first deal with
all the positive pre-conditions.
So at first, tests whether there are
positive pre-conditions left.
And if there are none left, it goes to
the first part here.
And if there are positive pre-conditions
left, it will go to the second part here,
the second part of this if statement.
And the first thing we do is select the
next positive pre-condition that we are
trying to apply to restrict the actions
that we can apply in this state.
So PP is the positive precondition that
we look at next, and then we go through
all the propositions in our state here as
P, and try to match this against PB.
Of course,
if the predicate doesn't match it can
never be a match and therefore we can
ignore these.
We only look, need to look at those
propositions that have the same
predicate.
And then we extend the current
substitution that we were given as our
parameter such that the two SP and PP
match.
This gives us a new substitution and if
this substitution is valid it means we
were able to extend the substitution.
Then we can do a recursive call and the
recursive call goes as follows: We dont
change the set of actions in this case.
We simply use the same operator again.
We remove the precondition from the set
of preconditions that we've just dealt
with.
So PP is the one we've just exploited, we
no longer need to look at that.
We've changed the substitution by adding
more, values to variables.
And the state remains the same.
We go through this loop until there are
no more positive preconditions, and then
we end up in the first case of the if
statement.
So now we've dealt with all the positive
preconditions.
We now look at all the negative
So we loop over NP where NP is a negative
precondition and all we have to do is now
check whether our state falsifies this
negative precondition.
If this is the case then this cannot
result in an applicable action.
But if the state does not falsify the
negative preconditions then we have found
an instance of this operator up that we
were given that is an applicable action
in this state.
And that, what we have to do is simply
replace all the parameters of this
operator according to the substitution
that we've been building up.
Here is an example that should illustrate
this algorithm.
In this example, we are given our state
over here.
That's the set of ground atoms.
And we have our PDDL action defined here.
That is the move action we've seen
previously.
So these are the two parameters we've
seen in our algorithm.
that's the operator is the move action,
and s is the state we were just given.
The other parameters are an empty set.
The pre-conditions of the move operator.
And an empty substitution.
The algorithm then starts by testing
whether there are positive preconditions
left which is the case which means we
immediately go to the L parts of the
algorithm.
And the first thing there is we choose
the next positive precondition we want to
look at.
So let's go back to the example.
The first positive preconditions is
adjacent from two and this is the first
precondition we will pick here.
So that's PP, PP is this adjacency
relation.
Looking back at the algorithm we see that
the next step is to look for all those
state propositions that can match this
positive precondition.
So let's look at our state.
This is the adjacency relation and we
have two adjacency ground atoms in our
state, namely location one to location
two and location two to location one.
So these are the two cases here I've
listed for SP.
The loop will go through those two and
succeed there.
The next step in the algorithm, then, is
to extend the substitution, such that SP
and PP match.
And we can see that this has happened
here.
I'll go through the first case on the
left here.
we've extended the substitution, such
that the variable from, from our
precondition must be location one and
two, must be location two.
So that adjacent one or two matches what
we have here in our substitution.
The algorithm then continues with the
recursive call.
Because the substitution is still valid.
And it simply removes that positive
precondition from the preconditions that
we still need to do.
So again, we end up at the entry to the
algorithm.
See that there are positive preconditions
left.
End up in the else branch.
And select the next positive precondition
that we need to deal with in the
algorithm.
And as we can see here the next positive
preconditions at R from so that's the
next positive precondition we select and
we need to match that against the state,
let's look at the algorithm again.
So we're now here that we're going
through a loop over all of the
propositions in the state that match this
positive precondition.
And if we look at the at relations of the
state, there is only one option here.
So this loop is only one long.
And we choose this here.
So we try to extend the substitution such
that it matches this state proposition.
And what we see here is that we need to
match R to R1, and from to location two.
But in our substitution we have already
set that from must be location one.
So it can't be location one and location
two at the same time.
Which mean our substitution is not valid.
But if we go back to the algorithm.
We had a branch here previously in this
loop that we haven't explored yet.
And that is listed here.
Namely, where SP was adjacent, location
one to location two.
And again, what we do is extend our
substitution such that the state
proposition matches the positive
pre-condition.
And we can do that here.
So we have that our new substitution maps
from to location two, and two to location
one.
Again, this is followed by the recursive
call.
So we need to check whether there are
more positive preconditions, just like in
the other case.
And yes, there is another positive
precondition.
The same one we dealt with in the other
case, the at relation.
And again there is only one possible
instance in the state that can match
that.
And that's at r1, location two.
So, where are we now in our algorithm?
We are here.
We need to extend the substitution, such
that the state proposition matches the
positive precondition.
So let's go back to the example.
What we have here is we need to match R
to R1.
And again we can do that.
And we match from to location two.
And again, previously we have matched
from to location two.
So this is consistent with the way we
need to match from now.
Which means we can actually, in this
case, extend the substitution.
And have a new substitution in which
case, from.
Is location two, two is location one.
And R is R1.
So again this would be followed by the
recursive call here, and that means we
reach the algorithm with a set of empty.
Positive preconditions.
There are only negative preconditions
left.
Let's look at the example.
We've dealt with adjacent and we've dealt
with at.
So, there are only negative preconditions
we need to deal with.
And the negative preconditions, then,
that's this part here of the algorithm.
We go through every negative precondition
and check whether this is falsified in
the state.
Instantiated with our substitution sigma.
So, what does this look like in the
example?
So, there's only one negative
precondition in our example.
Namely, that.
We want the location we're moving to not
to be occupied.
And that is our MP now, which means it is
not occupied location one.
In the example the variable we are
instantiating is two and our substitution
tells us that two must be location one.
So this is the instantiated negative
precondition not occupied location one.
And as we can see in the state, the only
location that is occupied is location
two.
Which means, our negative precondition is
not falsified here.
So we can turn this into an action, that
we add to the set A.
That's the final step here.
So we add to A, the instance of this
operator, instantiated using our
substitution that we've defined here.
That was the last substitution that we
had.
And we get the operator, move R1, from
location two to location one.
And indeed this is the only applicable
action here, and that means we are done
with this algorithm.