Okay.
So, we'll do this one more time, looking
at the maximum expected returns portfolio.
[COUGH]
So, just a little bit of a reminder about
the problem I'm trying to solve.
I have a vector of portfolio weights W,
that I think
of as so I'm, I'm thinking of N assets in
my portfolio.
So, W1 is the amount of my portfolio
invested in asset one.
W2 is the amount of my portfolio invested
in asset two, and so on.
There's n assets in the portfolio.
And there's a constraint on this factor w,
that the
sum of the elements has to be equal to
one.
So I sort of have one chunk of money that
I'm going to use to buy my portfolio.
And so the, the sum of all the pieces I
put
together to make that portfolio will end
up equaling that one.
Then, for each of the n assets I'm going
to put in my
portfolio, I have a value mu 1 that's the
expected return of that asset.
I'm going to put all of those together in
a vector and call that mu.
And then I also have a covariance matrix
for
the returns of the asset that I'm going to
call sigma.
And so this has to be an n by n matrix,
because it's, needs to tell me the
variance of each asset.
So it has to have n diagonal elements.
And then all of the off-diagonal elements
are going to
tell me the co-variance between that
particular pair of assets.
So whatever asset corresponds to say,
row i and column j.
And this has some special properties, so
it's symmetric.
That means sigma is equal to sigma
transpose.
And it's positive definite.
So this means that if I the, take an
eigenvalue
decomposition of sigma, all of the
eigenvalues are greater than 0.
And
the problem I want to solve, I want to
maximize the expected return subject to
the constraint on risk.
So, the expected return for each asset is
mu sub i for asset i.
And so if I just multiply that by the
weight of each asset and sum that up,
so you can think of that as just the dot
product of mu and my weight vector w,
which I'll write in matrix notation as mu
transpose w.
I want to maximize that quantity.
So again, this is going to be a linear
quantity, because these mu's are given to
me.
And then the w's are just all to the first
power, so this is going to be mu
1 is a coefficient, times w 1, mu 2 is the
coefficient times w 2, and so on.
And then I have two constraints.
So there's the
linear constraint.
So e transposed w has to equal 1.
So remember e is a vector of ones.
So this is going to be on the final too, I
use e as a vector of ones.
So just keep that in mind so e transposed
turns
that into a row vector times a column
vector w.
That's the same thing as just the dot
product of e and w.
And since e is all ones, that's just the
same thing as the sum of the elements of
w.
And that has to equal 1.
So that's my constraint on the portfolio
weights.
And then the second constraint is w
transpose sigma w.
And so this is interpreted as the risk of
the portfolio.
And the optimization I'm trying to do is
subject
to my portfolio having a certain level of
risk.
I want to choose w to give me the maximum
possible expected return.
So that's what this, this optimization
problem is asking you to do.
So we say it has a linear objective.
So that means all of the, the w's are all
to the first power.
And it has linear and quadratic
constraints, so this is
the linear constraint and then this is a
quadratic constraint.
And I can write out the Lagrangian for
this, so
it's going to be a function of w and
lambda.
So here lambda, because I have two
constraints,
lambda is going to be a vector with two
elements.
So I've lambda 1 and lambda 2, the
Lagrange multipliers.
And then it's just equal to the, the
function
that I'm trying to find the optimal value
of.
So that's the objective function.
Plus lambda 1 times the first constraint,
plus lambda 2 times the second constraint.
Then I need to take the gradient of the
Lagrangian.
So this is the, this is what I want to set
equal to 0.
So I want to find the inputs w and lambda
that
are going to make the gradient of the
Lagrangian equal to 0.
That's going to give me the critical
points of the Lagrangian.
So this is actually a little bit prettier,
because we can assume some knowledge of
the problem.
So in the last problem, I had to write out
this huge matrix,
pretty much element by element.
Here, because I can write everything in
terms of this mu vector and the
co-variance matrix, I can, i, it saves me
a little bit of notation.
But you have to be careful about the
dimension
of things to make sure that they add up.
So, this is a, a gradient of a function.
So the Lagrangian is a function of, so
this
would be n plus 2 variables.
And it's a scalar valued function.
So when I take it's gradient, I'm going to
get a row with n plus 2 elements.
So you want to make sure there's n plus 2
elements over here.
So this will be the, the first portion of
the gradient, the second portion, and the
third portion.
So what is the dimension of this?
Well, mu is a vector of expected
returns, and there's one expected return
for each asset.
So mu transpose is just going to be a row
vector of n elements.
Then I have lambda 1 is the scaler value
to
e transpose, so e is a column vector of n
ones.
So e transpose will be a row vector of n
And when I multiply that by lambda
one, this thing that I have highlighted
here, that's going to be a row
vector that just contains the value lambda
1 n times in a row.
And so, since this is a row vector with n
elements, and this
is a row vector with n elements, I can go
ahead and add them.
And then I just need to make sure that the
last thing here is also a row vector with
n elements.
So, 2 lambda 2, that's going to be a
scalar
quantity, so I don't have to think about
that.
Then I have w transpose sigma.
So w is a column vector with n elements.
So if I take its transpose, it's a row
vector with n elements.
So its dimensions are 1 by n.
And sigma is an n by
n co-variance matrix.
So if I have a 1 times
x vector times and n by n matrix, that's
going to give me a 1 by n output,
which is again a row vector of n elements.
So I can sum up these three terms.
And that's going to give me a 1 row vector
with n elements.
Then here for the second part of the
gradient, I have e transpose w.
So that's just going to be a dot product.
This is a single row times a single
column, so that's a scalar quantity.
And then when I subtract 1, that's also a
scalar quantity.
So this is 1 by 1.
And
then w transpose w.
So, again, this is a bit tricky, but this
w transpose is 1 by n.
Sigma is n by n.
And w is n by 1.
So it's always the outer dimensions that
are
going to determine the dimension of the,
of the product.
So this starts with a 1, and this last w
ends with a 1.
So this quantity that I have highlighted
is
a 1 by 1 quantity.
So that's just a scalar value.
And then sigma squared p is the risk of my
portfolio that I'm stating.
So that's also a scalar value.
So this final part of the gradient is
a scalar value.
So my gradient is 1 by n plus 2, which
is exactly what I was shooting for,
because I have n plus 2 values as inputs
for my function.
So, I want to solve to find the critical
point again.
So I'm going to define my function G to be
a function of w and lambda.
It's just going to be the transpose of
this function of the gradient of the
Lagrangian.
And so I end up with this vector here that
I want to set equal to 0, but again, it's
got,
it's got this quadratic form in it.
So it's not going to be something that I
can just solve as a linear system.
So I need to, so it's going to be a
nonlinear problem that I need to solve.
So I'm going to have to approach this with
Newton's method again.
And so the first thing I'm going to need
is this function G.
And then the second piece to, to be able
to do
my Newton iterations is I need the
gradient of this function G.
And so again, this is quite a bit easier
to write down then the previous
example, because I, I know a little bit
more about the form going on here.
So I can just take, the gradient of,
of this function is going to be the
derivative of this with respect to w, then
mu 1, then mu 2, or sorry, w, and then
lambda
1, then lambda 2.
So if take the derivative,
mu is constant, so when I take this
derivative with respect to w, I get zero.
There's no w here, so that also becomes
zero.
But there is
a w here, and so it turns out that when
you
take the derivative of this, this is
actually a, a matrix product.
So this is
this is going to be so it has n pieces.
So it has n rows and one column.
So, when I take the derivative of that,
I'm going to end up getting a matrix.
So this quantity here is 2 times lambda 2
times sigma.
So this has the same dimension as the
matrix sigma,
so this upper left block is n by n matrix.
Then when I take the derivative of this
with
respect to lambda 1, I'm just going to get
e.
So that e is going to go here, except
remember e is this column vector of n
ones.
So at least the dimensions match up.
This has n rows.
And then, we've also talked about taking
the derivative of a quadratic form.
So the derivative of this is 2 times sigma
times w.
So this is also going to be a quantity
with n rows.
So this top row that I have written here,
if I were actually to write
out every single element by itself, this
would have n rows and n plus 2 columns.
So that when I take, oops, derivative of
the second
line with respect to w, I just gave e
transpose.
And since there's no lambdas anymore in
here, the
bottom right block is always going to be
zero.
And so then again at the bottom here, I
take the derivative of this quadratic form
and that's what's
going in here.
So, now I have
I now have the pieces I'm going to go
through the a, an example from the
textbook now.
So they used five asset example with
expected returns of 0.8
through 0.20, and the asset return
co-variance matrix of this.
So, remember that these things are sort of
on the order of mu squared.
So that's why these are going to be so
much smaller than what's going on here.
And then the target risk was 25%, so the
sigma squared p is going to be 0.25
squared, which is 0.0625.
So this was the definition of the function
G of w and lambda.
And so, I can write an R function to
compute this.
So again, I'm going to use this, vector x
is going
to be w, and then the last two elements
are going to be lambda 1 and lambda 2.
So x, if w has n elements, then x is going
to have n plus
2 elements.
And now, instead of hard-coating the
values for mu
and sigma into this function, I want to
also make
them arguments to my function, so that if
I
wanted to solve another problem with this
same function.
Instead of having to rewrite the entire
function, all I have to do is make
a new vector mu and a new matrix Sigma,
and then I can just pass
those in as arguments as well.
And then I also need this sigma p2, which
is, that just
this value here, which is the constraint
on the risk of the portfolio.
And all I'm going to do is just evaluate,
oops, I'm trying
to highlight the top line here, but it
doesn't seem to be working.
I'm going to just evaluate these three
pieces one at a
time and put them into a vector, and then
return that.
So that's all the, the function G is going
to
do, just return the vector value of this
function G.
And so the first is just mu plus, this is
just going to repeat lambda
1 n times, which is exactly what this
second term in the first row is doing.
And then 2 times lambda 2 plus
sigma times w, so that's just what the
third portion of the first line is doing.
E transpose
w, that just sums up the values of w.
So I'm just going to use R as sum function
to do the same thing.
And then w transpose sigma w minus sigma
squared p.
So there's w is the first n elements.
So I guess I was a little bit sloppy here.
The five, I should have used an n, but
because this is a
5 by 5 example, I had a 5 in here in the
first place.
So I have w times, sorry, w transpose, so
in R, this t function transposes.
So w transpose sigma w minus sigma squared
p.
And ag, and I'm going to use the C
function to
wrap all that up into a vector and return
it.
Then similarly for the gradient, so this
is again
going to be a little bit messier than the
last one.
I'm going to use pretty much the same
approach I used in the previous example.
So I'll make grad, which is a matrix of
zeroes, has dimension n plus 2
by n plus 2.
Then, in the top left n by n
block, I'm going to put 2 lambda 2 sigma.
So 2 lambda 2 is scalar.
Sigma is an n by n matrix, so that's why I
have to assign it into an n by n block of
this matrix grad.
And I just have 2 times lambda 2 times
sigma.
Another nice feature of R is, if I assign
a scalar value into a range in a vector.
So here I'm assigning the number 1 into
columns, or into
rows 1 through n of column n plus 1.
So that's referring to this e up here.
It's just going to repeat that 1 enough
times to fill up that range.
And so the same thing is going to happen
for this e here when I run this command.
And then for rows 1 through n in column n
plus 2, so that's describing this
portion over here.
I just need to put 2 times sigma times w.
So, remember w is the first five elements
of the input to this function.
And then again, I, I put mu, sigma, n, the
constraint in here,
just so that I can change this anytime I,
when want to use it to solve a different
problem.
So for a different mu and a different
sigma.
And I guess this is a little bit
overparameterized, since I
don't think mu and the constraint don't
show up in here.
But I just wanted to use the same
arguments as I had for the function G.
So then, the Newton, so once I'm the bulk
of the work was
getting these two functions to make the,
to compute the gradient of the function.
Once I've done that, I can just assign
myself a starting point.
So I'm going to use 1 half repeated 5
times, so this is going to
make a vector just 1 half, 1 half, 1 half,
1 half, 1 half.
Then I'm going to put a 1 and a 1 at the
end of it.
So my starting point is 1 half for
x, or for w1 through w5, which, I don't
know how much sense that makes, because
the one thing I do know about the w's is
that they should sum up to 1.
But at least it works.
and then I'm using values of 1 as
a starting point for the two Lagrange
multipliers.
So that looks like this.
My Newton iterations, again, it's, this
part's almost always going to be the same.
I just, I compute my gradient and I
compute my
function, and then I just need to solve
that linear system.
And then I use that to update x.
So I'm writing the updated x in the same
piece of memory as x had.
And I'm going to repeat that 25 times.
And that gives me this computed solution
here.
So I couldn't quite fit the whole w vector
on the
first line, so this first five parts
corresponds to w1 through w5.
The portfolio weights, or the asset
weights within the portfolio.
Then this is the first Lagrange multiplier
and the second Lagrange multiplier.
And then I'll do the same thing I did last
time
to try and classify this as a minimum or a
maximum.
So, one of the nice properties about the
minimum variance portfolio is because I
had to
solve a linear system to get the critical
point, I know there's only one critical
point.
Here, I'm not certain if,
what critical point I got.
If you know a little bit more about
the problem, there should actually be two
critical points.
And it turns out that one of them
corresponds to the portfolio you want, and
the other one corresponds to the absolute
worst
portfolio you can get according to your
constraint.
So it is important in this one to be able
to classify the point you found as the
actual maximum.
So, we'll go back and look at the, the
upper left n by n block
of the gradient of the function G.
So this is actually just going to be the
transpose of the Hessian of this function
of
the, of the Lagrangian, so F, except when
I plug in the computed values lambda c.
>>
[INAUDIBLE]
>> No, you can actually do that.
So what that corresponds to is something
called a short sale.
So what I do is, I pretend like I don't
have any shares of Starbucks.
But I borrow some shares of Starbucks from
some guy who does
and I give, I sell them to you, so you
give me money.
And then, yeah, so there's, a negative
weight means I owe that guy some
Starbucks.
Yeah,
and I have to buy that back in the future
to give it back to him.
So you can actually do that.
Yeah, the problem gets to be a bit more
complicated if you put,
if you start putting extra constraints on
it like w's have to be positive.
So, which can be solved, but not in the
very
first math class that looks at that sort
of thing.
[COUGH]
Whoops.
So this this is the matrix.
So last time, I, I set up the problem, or
not, not me, but Dan Stefanica, who is
the author of the course textbook, set up
the
problem so that this matrix was diagonal
no matter what.
So, he set up the Lagrange the Lagrange,
the Lagrangian,
so that the off diagonal element elements
were always going to be zero.
Here that's clearly not the case.
So, since the, the matrix isn't a diagonal
form,
you need to compute the eigenvalues of
this matrix.
And the computed points, so w sub c, it'll
correspond to a maximum if this matrix is
negative definite.
And it'll correspond to a minimum if this
matrix is positive definite.
And so, the way we can check that, because
this is just
a matrix, it's just numbers, I can just
compute the eigenvalues of that.
So I use eigen to calculate the
eigenvalues.
This is just the code to generate this
matrix here, and then the dollar sign says
it.
So the eigenfunction will also give me the
eigenvectors,
but I'm not really interested in that
right now.
So, if I take just the values out of this
function, I
get this vector of five values and they're
all less than zero.
So that tells me that this matrix is
negative definite.
And that tells me that the computed point,
x subs er,
in this case w sub c, corresponds
to a constrained maximum of the objective
function.
And then finally, I can find the computed
w.
So that's 0.199.
And so this is the maximum that I can make
the expected return for my portfolio,
subject to having a risk of 0.25 squared.
Okay.
So that's all I have.
Oh.
Okay.
Yeah.
>> How did you know.
You did 25 iterations, so how
do you know that you actually have a
typical value after 25 iterations?
>> Yeah, just to make this stuff fit on
the slide, I just, I did that.
Really, what you should do,
so remember, this was
in the section on
on doing Newton's method with vector
valued functions.
This is sort of my update.
And so what happens is the you know, if it
works, it's supposed to be converging to a
certain value.
So converging means that my current
estimate is
close to the thing that I'm trying to get.
And so when I'm in that situation, if I
update, I shouldn't move too much.
And so, what you can do, is you can
monitor the norm of this vector.
And when that gets below a certain
level, and usually you want to do it
relative to the size of x,
so you could the norm of this vector
divided by the norm of x.
When that's less than say one in a
million, then you just say
that this point is so close to x that I'm
going to stop.
So you need, you need to kind of think
about it a little bit.
But essentially you, you want to define a
value
somehow, of what it means to be close
enough
to the thing you're trying to get.
And then you just watch as you're going
along.
And when you hit that then you stop.
But, like I said, you know,
Newton's method isn't really guaranteed to
converge.
So, it's also good to have something like
this, like you go 50 times until you stop.
So you'll either stop or you'll hit 50.
But if you don't put a maximum number of
times and
it doesn't converge, you know, it's just
going to keep going and going and going.