Picking up where we left off last time,
we're
on lesson number five, double integrals of
separable functions.
This really was meant to follow up part
four,
where we had a function, I did a change
of variables, and then it wasn't that much
easier
to integrate after I did the change of
variables.
But there was a trick that we missed, and
so that's what this
section will, will cover.
So if we look back at what we did last
time.
We had this integral here, which this is
what the function was.
This was just x, and then we transformed
into s and t.
So this is what x got transformed into.
And then we had oops, the absolute value
of the Jacobian here, and then ds dt.
And then I'll rewrite that
in this more power rule slash anti-power
rule friendly
form of just each each variable to a
power.
And
now, if you look at where I've put the
square brackets here.
oops, so this is, this is the way we tried
to do it last time.
So I just pretended this is a function of
s and t.
I'm going to inter, I going to do the
partial integral of this with respect to
s first, evaluated at s equals 2 and
subtract it evaluated at s equals 1.
But, if we look at this a little
bit closer, any function of t, since we're
doing
a, a partial integral, any function of t
is going to be constant with respect to s.
So I can move, I have this integral
sign here corresponds to integration with
respect to s.
So the inside integral sign and the inside
variable here,
the, they correspond to one another.
And anything, and, and these are
corresponding to the variable s,
anything that's not an s is constant with
respect to this integral.
So I can move that across the integral
sign, and
I'll get what I have on the right-hand
side here.
So I, I get the t to the minus 3
halves, that's constant with respect to
this integral in here.
So I'm going to bring it out front.
And now I have something that only depends
on s here.
And so what this is going to allow me to
do is express this integral
as the product of two definite integrals
that are integrals of single variable
functions.
So I have here an integral, oops.
just of s alone.
And then multiplied by an integral on the,
on the right of t alone.
And so the reason I was able to do that
is, if I look at his function here, that I
can't
seem to highlight right now, just get a
little bit
or it so people can see where the mouse
pointer is.
Everything in this set of square brackets,
I can do
that integral and that's just going to be
a real number.
And so, I can just treat the whole thing,
whether I evaluate it and get the real
number.
Or I just keep it in these square
brackets.
It's constant, so I can bring that across
this integral sign here.
And now, this is going to be obviously,
quite a bit easier,
because I can do each one of these
integrals independently now.
So here I've just computed the
anti-derivative
of the first function, anti derivative of
the second function, then I'll have to
to evaluate them at their limits and
subtract.
so I'm just using the fundamental theorem
of calculus Independently now.
Once for this function of s and once for
this function of t.
And let's see.
So the rest of it is just a little bit of
algebra.
And I don't suppose anybody remembers the
thing I told you to remember on Monday.
But it was, so last time it was negative 6
plus 5 root 2 over 3.
This time it's 5 root 2 minus 6 over 3.
but because we're able to separate this
integral, I, well
at least for me I felt it was a lot for
me to evaluate it this way than it was to
evaluate it trying to integrate it twice
as an iterated integral.
And so, in general, this is going to work
only when we have a rectangular domain of
integration.
So this isn't going to work if the limits
of one of the integral depend on the
value in the other integral.
because then, I'm not, it's still going to
have
some dependence on the, the first partial
integral
will have some dependence, not in the
function,
not in the integrand, but in the limits.
So I won't be able to move that across the
other
I won't be able to remove that across the
other integral.
So I have to have a rectangular domain of
integration.
And
then I have to be able to take the
integrand, this is the function I'm trying
to integrate.
And I need to be able to write that as a
product of
a function of the first variable times a
function of the second variable.
And then I can express the double integral
of f
over r as the product of these two single
variable integrals.
So the double integral of f over r becomes
the integral.
So remember, this is f, but now I'm
going to use the fact that I
can separate it into a product of g of x
and h of y.
And then the ab limits correspond to
integration with respect to x.
And the cd limits correspond to
integration with respect to y.
And then because h of y, this is going
to be constant when I'm integrating with
respect to x.
So I can bring that out in front of the
integral sign.
The dx integral sign.
And now inside the square brackets, I have
something
that I could just integrate and replace
with a constant.
And so, since this quantity inside the
square brackets
is constant, I can move that out in front
of my dy integral.
And so what I'm left with is a product of
a definite integral
with resp g of x dx, and another definite
integral, h of y dy.
And so this was this was an
example of kind of the forward use of, of
this property.
So I had a function of s and t that I
could accept, it was a function of s times
the function
of t, so I was able to separate that.
It got easier when I did the change of
variables, because
I took my diamond, and I turned it into a
rectangle.
So that allowed me then to, to use this
property.
the other thing that will seem kind of
strange is that I can also use this
backwards.
So it, sometimes.
And in fact, we're going to have a lesson
on that in a little bit.
if I have two integrals of this form.
So an integral a
single variable function times the
integral of a
single variable function that I'm not able
to compute.
So each of these, this side and this side.
I'm not able to do When I multiply them
together, I am able to evaluate it.
So that'll give me a sort of a interesting
way to solve one particular problem.