And now, we finally get to Lagrange's
Method.
Hey guys.
I'm, I'm starting up again.
So now I get to Lagrange's Method.
So the problem I am trying to solve.
Remember when I go back to my
portfolio optimization, I want to maximize
a function.
So I'm going to call this my objective
subject to one or more constraints.
So I'm, I'm going to use n for the number
of variables of the function I am trying
to maximize.
And then I'm going to think about having n
con-, m constraints.
So g1 up to gm.
So there was a 18th century mathematician
named Joseph Louis Lagrange
who proposed the following method for, for
a solution for this problem.
And his solution was to make this function
It's now a function of the original n
variable so x one up to xn.
And then also these values lambda.
So you get one lambda for each of the
constraints you have.
So lambdas going to go there's, or the
subscript on lambda will go from one to m.
So there's Lambda 1 for g1, Lambda 2 for
g2, and so on.
And the way you make this function
is you just put the objective here, and
then you
add Lambda times each of these constraints
to that objective function.
So you have Lambda 1 times g1 plus Lambda
times g2 plus Lambda 3 times g3 and so on.
And also note that I've written the
constraints
so that they have to be equal to zero.
So this is zero isn't a variable that's
kind
of hard coded in that spot.
So if you have something like a condition
X squared plus Y squared equals 1,
you have to write that as X squared plus Y
squared and minus 1 equals 0.
And then it turns out the optimal value,
so, the
maximum value of f, the biggest or
smallest I can
make f, subject to these m constraints, is
going to
occur at one of the critical points for
this function here.
Suggest a little terminology to get us
started.
This function, capital F, so is a function
of n variables
and the m lambda values is called the
Lagrangian.
And the vector Lambda that has Lambda 1
through Lambda
m as it's components is called the
Lagrange multipliers vector.
So each one of these things is called a
Lagrange multiplier,
and then the whole vector is called the
Lagrange multipliers vector.
And then there's one necessary condition
for this meth-, method to work.
So if I rename the inputs to the
original function, to the objective
function, lowercase f.
I'm going to put those in a vector and
just call that x.
And then, if I let g of x just be this
vector valued function.
So remember, again, when I put parentheses
around a
row, what I really mean is a, a column
vector.
So this is a column vector that has G1 as
its first element.
G2 as it's second element, and so on,
so it's a vector-valued function of the
constraints.
Then the gradient, and now remember that,
so if I have
a vector-valued function, the gradient's
now going to be a matrix.
The gradient of this vector-valued
function, g(x).
Has to have full rank at any point where
the constraint g of x equals zero is
satisfied.
So that means you have to figure out what
this gradient matrix looks like.
Pick a point that satisfies the contraint.
So, pick a point that satisfies g of x
equals zero, then evaluate the gradient at
that point.
So that will give me a matrix now just of
numbers, because
it's sort of a matrix of functions,
evaluated at one particular point.
You can do elimination
on that matrix, and you'd end up with a
full set of pivots.
So if that condition holds, then I say
that the rank of
the gradient of this vector value function
g is equal to m, so
it's this matrix is going to have m rows,
and so in each
row, I'm able to find a pivot, that means
I have full rank.
And so I said oh you can do that for one
point but
actually for this condition to hold you
have to do it at every point.
So this this can sometimes be pretty
problematic to to do
Most of the time I don't bother checking
this, unless something really goes wrong.
And then you wonder, why is this not
working.
You know, oh, maybe it's the, the
condition isn't, isn't being held.
Okay.
So the Lagrangian is going to be a
function that has N plus M variables, so.
X is this is the argument for the, for the
objective function.
Little f.
Which was a function of n variables.
And then I'm also going to have m Lagrange
multipliers.
So, the Lagrangian has n plus m variables.
And I need to compute the gradient of this
thing.
Because.
I need to find the critical points,
because what I'm after is a critical
point of the Lagrangian will correspond to
an extreme value of, of my optimization
problem.
So I can think about doing this in two
steps,
and it turns out this, this step is pretty
easy.
So, I'll write d sub x of the lagrangian.
So, this will be
the gradient, but I'm only going to take
partial derivatives with respect to x.
And then, this will be the gradient
with the partial derivatives with respect
to lambda.
And since this should just be one long row
vector, so it's a row vector
because I'm using the square brackets
here, so
I mean I want everything to stay in
a row and the first n elements will be
these partial derivatives with respect to
the x variables.
And the last m elements will be the
partial derivatives with respect to the
Lagrange multipliers.
And now let's remember what the Lagrangian
looks like.
And now if I want to take the partial
derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to one of the x variables,
what I'll end up with.
Because the differentiation is a, is a
linear operation.
So the derivative of a sum is the sum of
the derivatives.
So I'll have one derivative.
So if I'm taking the,
the partial with respect to xj, I'll end
up with
the partial derivative of little f with
respect to xj.
So that's my first term here.
And then for lambda 1, I'm going to end up
with lambda 1 times the partial derivative
of g 1
with respect to x j, plus lambda 2 times
the
partial derivative of g 2 with respect to
x j.
So I can actually just move that
differentiation operation across the sum.
And what I'll end up with.
Partial derivative of f with respect to
xj, plus the sum from 1 to m.
So summing over each one of these
Lagrange multipliers terms, of the
Lagragne multiplier
so lambda i times the partial derivative
of constraint i with respect to xj.
And then on the right hand side, this
turns out to be quite a bit easier.
So when I'm taking the partial derivative
with respect to each
of the lambdas, the objective function
doesn't have a lambda in it,
so this the derivative of this, the
partial derivative of this
with respect to anyone of the lambdas is
going to be zero.
And also, the g doesn't have any lambdas
in it.
It's also a function
just of the, the x variables.
So the only place the Lagrange multipliers
are going
to show up are just lambda i to the 1.
And so when I'm taking the partial
derivative with respect to lamda i, every
one of these is going to be equal to zero,
except for lamda i.
And so what I end up with is just a gi of
x.
So the gradient of f is going to be these
partial derivatives with respect to x.
The gradient of g is going to be this, so
it's a little tricky to see.
But the, there, there's n columns so x1,
x2, all the way up to xn.
And then there's m rows.
So it's a m by n matrix.
And then, each row is just going to be the
gradient.
Of g, i of x.
So here, first row is
the gradient of g1, second row is the
gradient of g2 and so on.
And so I end up with this matrix being the
gradient of a vector valued function.
So now I can express the, the sum.
And the second term using matrix notation,
so I had this sum of lambda
i times the partial derivative of gi which
respect to xj and so if
I look at a column here, if I pick a
particular j, so suppose I pick j
equals 2, that's going to be the second
column of this matrix.
So, this sum is just going to be equal to
lambda times
the second column of this matrix.
So that's what I mean when I say.
Matrix sub j, I mean the jth column so if
I put a little two down
here, I'll be talking about the column
back
there, that's the second column of this
matrix.
And I can write this sum then as lambda
transposed times
dot specific so the jth column of this
matrix.
That's going to make my notation a little
bit easier to handle now.
I don't have to write out all of these
partial
derivatives, I can just write it out in
terms of gradients.
So it follows that my gradient for the
whole Lagrangian now.
This is going to be the gradient of f,
plus this
thing that I just worked out up here, and
so I'm
going to be able to do this plus operation
because the, the
gradient of f is going to be a row vector
with n elements.
And then lamba transpose.
That's also going to be a row vector with
n elements.
And I'm going to multiply that by an n by
n
matrix, so it's going to stay a row vector
with n elements.
So this term is a row vector with n
elements; this term is a row vector with n
elements.
And so I can do the sum just by doing the
summation element wise, and
I end up getting exactly what I had in the
sum formula in the previous slide.
And then the derivatives for
For the part of the Lagrangian that just
corresponds to taking derivatives with
respect to lambda, they
just end up being the constraints again,
so remember
g was a vector valued function of the
constraints.
So if I take g transpose, that's just
going
to be that same vector but put into a row.
And I have to do that because this whole
thing has to end up being a row.
So I end up with a row vector here of n
elements, and a row vector here
of m elements, and so when I put those two
next to each other, I end up with this
row vector with n plus m elements that's
the gradient of the Lagrangian.