We'll now look at a number of AI Planners
and the type of application in which
they've been used.
Earlier in the course we showed a table
with a number of practical planners
applied in realistic situations.
And we noted the long history of the
practical application of our planning
methods.
And during the course, we described some
the key techniques employed in search
planners.
We're going to now explore a number of
these systems, the features they include,
and their applications.
SIPE-2 System for Interactive Planning
and Execution was created in the 1980s
and has been developed since then to
provide a comprehensive approach to AI
planning.
It's been developed by David Wilkins and
his colleagues at SRI International in
California.
SIPE-2 is a domain independent planner
which supports interactive planning,
allowing humans and system to co-operate
in a mixed initiative planning fashion.
It can efficiently reason about actions
to generate the novel sequence of actions
that respond precisely, to the situation
at hand.
It supports the giving advice to the
planner.
It plans a hierarchical at different
levels of abstraction,
replans during exclusion,
can generate parallel plans, so it can
allow for multiple agent planning.
Post constraints and reasons about
resources within the plan and interacts
with users through a graphical interface.
SIPE-2 has been applied in applications
as diverse as, oil spill response,
military planning, and production line
planning in a brewery.
O-Plan was built by my own team at
University of Edinburgh through the 1980s
and 1990s.
It was based on the features in the
earlier nautaline hierarchical test
planner.
O-Plan supported the whole life cycle of
planning.
From domain modeling and knowledge of
list station tools.
Through planning, detail constraint
management, and plan execution.
He was able to repair plans, or replan as
necessary, when execution failures
occurred.
And O-Plan experimented with a wide range
of graphical user interfaces, including
support for multiple concurrent users
with different roles in the planning
process.
And the workflows involved in
coordinating between multiple users.
It supported a web interface to allow the
planner to be used as a web service.
O-Plan is being used in Edinburgh and
elsewhere for a wide range of
applications.
Some of which were introduced earlier in
the course.
And as noted previously,
O-Plan was used at the bases for the
design of the deployed optimum AIV
planner at the European Space Agency for
Ariane rocket launch and payload base,
sample integration and test.
Shop and it's successor Shop two were
created at University of Maryland by Dana
Now and his colleagues.
Shop two is hierarchical task network
planner.
But keeps the activities in the plan
fully ordered.
It selects activities to include in the
order they'll be executed from the start
of the plan.
Which eases reasoning about the state of
the world affected by the plan, at any
point.
Shop two does allow for interleaving of
the solutions more multiple goals and
subgoals in this ordered plan which is an
improvement over the original shop
planner.
Shop two can reason with a rich logical
model of the state, including quantifiers
and conditionals.
And can maintain and reason out temple
constraints as is required for most
practical planners.
And it allows for numeric computations
alongside the most symbolic will state
models.
Calls to external routines are possible
to incorporate constraints expressed in
program code.
And the rich domain model allows
preferences on choosing operators in
given situations, feature seen in other
practical planners, also.
Shop and Shop two have been applied to a
wide range of applications as diverse as
fighting forest fires, controlling
multiple unmanned autonomous vehicles,
UAVs, and creating business process
workflows.
The shop techniques have also been
incorporating some domains specific
planning applications embeded in
manufacturing automated systems and in
versions of the commercially available
Ridge Barren device which won the
Inaugural World Compute Bridge
Championships in 1997.
There are some common themes we can see
appearing in many of the practical
planners we've described.
The use of an outer hierarchical task
network approach which is friendly and
understandable to users.
An underlying detailed
constraint-handling layer to handle the
real needs of time and resource
constraints and plans.
Integration with simulation analysis
systems to prune or further constrain the
plans which about are useful.
Integration with plan execution and plan
monitoring to put plans into real use.
Rich knowledge modelling languages, and
ways to describe features of application
domains in ways which the planner can use
to constrain choices.
And availability of comprehensive and
useful user interfaces during planning
and execution.