So the next topic is, a Change of
Variables Example,
so a slightly more complicated version of
what we just did.
And this one I, I took from the textbook.
And I found it when I was reading the book
getting ready to do this class I found it.
I thought sort of too complicated, so I
thought it would be a good
thing to go through step by step just to
make sure everybody understands it.
So I want to evaluate the double integral
over
domain D of x dx dy, where this domain D
is going to
be points in the xy plane, where x is
greater than or equal
to zero, then the product x and y is in
between 1 and 2.
And then y divided by x is also between 1
and 2.
And so it turns out we can assume that x
is greater than zero.
I wrote assume here.
You don't really have to assume.
You can actually see that it's greater
than zero.
[COUGH]
So it's easier if you rewrite the domain
so solve for one of the variables.
So generally I like to see y as a function
of x.
That's what I'm most comfortable plotting.
So if I solve for y, if I can isolate y,
then I can just say y equals 1 over x.
That has to be kind of a lower bound in
some sense.
And y less than or equal
to 2 over x.
So y equals 2 over x.
That's going to be kind of an upper bound.
And then the same thing is going to happen
with the second set of limits.
So I have.
x less than or equal to y.
That's just the line y equals x, and the
function, the
domain has to be above that because it's y
greater than x.
And then there's also going to be a line y
equals 2x, and that has to
be kind of an upper bound, because it says
that y has to be below that.
And so once you've gotten this far, what
you want to do next.
Is, just draw a picture.
So, I tried my artistic skills here.
And, so, the second condition, y has to be
greater than x.
So, the bottom side of this blue region is
the line y equal x.
In the top side of the blue region is the
line y equals 2x.
And this just says y has to be in between
those two lines.
So to be in my domain I have to be in my
blue region.
And then 1 over x so y has to be greater
than 1 over x.
So this line, the bottom of the yellow
reason is this line 1 over x.
The top of this yellow regions is 2 over
x.
So this is 2 over x up here.
And so to be in the domain I also have to
be in the yellow region.
So I have to be in the blue region and I
have to be in the yellow region.
And if I remember my primary school
art class correctly, yellow and blue make
green.
So that tells me that this green shape is
the domain that they're talking about.
So this is, this description this set, if
I
want to draw a picture of it looks like
this.
[COUGH]
And so what do I have next?
So it
turns out that the points here's.
This
point at the bottom is, let's see, what
did I
do?
dx last, so this has this point at the
left most side of the green region in the
x coordinate is one, then I get this point
here, oh oops.
Not 1, it's
the square root of 2 over 2, then this
point is going to
be 1.
And so that makes sense, because y equals
x gives me the point 1 equals 1, and y
equals 1 over x also gives me the point
1 equals 1.
So this bottom point of the green
[COUGH]
green region is the point 1,1.
This point over here is root 2 over 2.
And so you just find those by figuring out
where each of these lines intersects the
other one.
And then on the right hand side I guess we
get root 2.
And, it turns out that we're pretty lucky.
That this point at the very top of
the green region, too, also has x
coordinate 1.
So, it's exactly above this bottom point.
And, so the reason that that's going to be
handy is that means that
instead of having to split this up into a
whole bunch of pieces.
I can just split it up into two pieces.
So I can go from the leftmost endpoint,
which was root 2 over 2, up to 1.
And I'm going to
kind of try and get this bit over here.
Oh, I could have used another color.
And then I want to go from 1.
So that's kind of this line dividing the
green region in half up to root 2.
And that's going to be my second integral,
but the point is
in the first integral, given x, I can find
an upper bound.
So, I can find an upper limit and a lower
limit as functions
g of x, so g one of x and g two of x.
So, the upper limit, given
x, will be 2x, and the lower limit will be
one over x.
Then, when I'm on the right hand side of
the x equals 1 line, the upper limit
will be 2 over x, so that's this line up
here, and the lower limit will just be
x.
So y equals x, and so those,
I guess, are the limits that
I've plugged in here and
here, and here, and here.
So, I think the rest, most of this slide,
you can tell it's going to be
bad because I didn't have enough space to
even put the, the title up at the top.
I needed, you know, more space to put the
calculations.
You can actually evaluate this it just
sort of
becomes an exercise in bookkeeping which I
did for you.
So, just to point out some good habits.
So, first I'm going to integrate with
respect to y.
So that means my limits have to be y
equals functions of x and so
then when I, once I find an anti
derivative.
So when I integrate x with respect to y
that's going to come from the function xy.
If I took the derivative of that, the
partial derivative of
xy with respect to y that would just give
me x.
And then just to remind myself which
direction
I'm going, I said I'm going to evaluate
that at y equals 2x and then 1 equals 1
over x and take the difference.
And then I'm going to do the same thing
for
my integral on the right hand side as
well.
And so at this first step I get the same
antiderivative.
I don't suppose I can make that go away.
Maybe if I click
on details and then quit.
We are going to have to edit this out of
the video I think.
Okay, good.
So hopefully I don't get some terrible
virus in the next 12 minutes.
So in the first step we're going to get
the first
anti-derivative, but once I evaluate this
at the limit, so
the, the limits in the y direction are
different in
the first integral than they are in the
second integral.
So I'm going to have a different integral
when I
come to doing the second step of my
interation.
And so this is what I end up with, an
integral
from root 2 over 2 to one of 2x square
minus 1.
And then the integral from 1 to root 2 of
2 minus x squared.
Now it's just a regular old single
variable problem, so you can
look through the slide on your own time if
you want to.
Just trust that I did it correctly.
Again, big exercise in bookkeeping, but if
you don't
make any sign mistakes you will eventually
arrive at
the correct answer, which is this minus 6
plus 5 times the square root of 2 over 3.
And so just let's keep that
in mind.
So minus 6 plus 5 root 2 over 3.
And now let's consider the change of
variables.
So s equals xy, and t equals y over x.
So, hopefully seems familiar.
This was my domain in, for the original
integral.
And it turns out, if I define these
variables this way, it's
actually pretty easy to figure out what
the, the transformed domain should be.
So here I have x y has to be in between 1
and 2.
So that's going to tell me that s has to
be in between 1
and 2, and then t is equal to y over x, so
this just tells
me that t also has to be in between 1 and
2.
So instead of having this funny shaped
green interval now,
I just have a square 1, 2 cross 1, 2.
So that's my new domain of integration,
omega.
And you can sort of use the same reasoning
that I used to, with the diamond.
So here if we look at t, is this y over x.
So if I were to solve this.
For x I would get y equals t times x.
So that's saying t is kind of the slope of
that line.
And if you think about what's happening in
this blue region,
t equals 1 corresponds to the bottom of
the blue region.
And t equals 2 corresponds to the top of
Just because here I have y equals 1 times
x.
Up to y equals 2 times x.
And in between 1 and 2 if I had t equals 3
over 2 times
x, that would just be a line that split
the blue region right down the middle.
So you can sort of think of it as this
bottom line swinging up to the top line.
So it's pivoting on the origin, just from.
y equals x up to y
equals two x and then the same thing for
this s equals xy.
I could think of that as y equals s over
x, and so again there's
this number 1 going up to 2, oops, going
up to 2, so s
equals one just corresponds to the bottom
of this yellow
region, the curve making the bottom of the
yellow region.
And that curve is just going to shift up
to the top as s goes from 1 to 2.
So that's sort of the geometric argument,
you know making this
sketch of the domain is usually what
you'll have to do.
It turned out this wasn't quite as hard as
I thought it
would be the first time I read it, just
because, I realize
now the reason that the, the textbook
defined
the, defined this domain in such a
complicated way.
Is because it makes it easy to see what
the limits
on s and t are going to be just because
this
is really telling you what the limit of s
is and
this is really telling you what the limit
of t is.
And so that means I can change my domain
from d, which is this funny shaped
green thing, to just t equals 1 to t
equals 2 and s equals 1 to s equals 2.
But then I need to use my change of
variables formula to figure out what I
need here.
And so first, to do that we have to do
what the, the quiz question was last time.
So I came up with the, the change x equals
the square root of s over t.
And y equals the square root of s times t.
And then, I calculated the partial
derivatives for the change of variables.
So I got, 1 over 2 times the square root
of st.
Square root of t divided by 2 times the
square root of st.
Square root of s.
Oh, so, minus the square root of s divided
by 2t to the
3 halves, but I wrote that as t times the
square root of t.
And then, square root of s divided by 2
times the square root of t, so.
For me, I, I put this here just because I
think it looks a little
prettier, but in terms of doing the
calculation,
I find this, this formula far more useful.
So these are actually the things I would
plug
into, that I would plug into the Jacobian
formula.
And these, you know, if I write my
transformations like this, then I can just
use the power rule to figure out what's
going on to take the partial derivatives.
And so the Jacobian for this particular
change of variables just becomes this,
and if you cancel everything out so you
can see it's kind of constructed.
So stuff cancels out nicely, so the square
root of t will
cancel out this square root of t, square
root of s cancels out.
This, square root of s.
And so in both cases, we just get 1 over 2
times the square root of t.
Sorry, 1 over 2 times the square root of t
squared.
So I get 1 over 4t times 1 over 4t, and
that's one over 2t.
Okay, at least one person got the right
answer on the quiz.
So now I can plug this into my change of
variables formula.
So, this was the original integral over
the funny-shaped domain d.
And now I've already worked out what the
new domain, omega, is.
It's just the square 1,2 to 1,2.
I have my function is x and my change of
variables was
x is equal to the square root of s divided
by t.
So this is, oops see if I can.
The square root here is just x.
Then, the absolute value of my Jacobian
is 1 over 2 times t.
And since I defined x and y to be greater
than 0, that
was part of the definition of my domain,
then, the Jacobian, so t.
Is this function of x and y, but it's
going to be positive
only when x and y, or it's positive when x
and y are positive.
So the absolute values, they're kind of
invisibly here, but not necessary.
And then I can change this into an
integral, ds dt.
And so now I just have to integrate.
This function, instead of just x.
But at least the, the limits are quite a
lot easier this time.
So instead of having these complicated
limits for for
the first integral, I now just have 1 and
2.
And so again, it's just sort of two single
variable problems one after the other.
And again, I like to write it in this form
here, so I can see
clearly how the power rule or the
anti-power rule are working.
And so the rest of it's just sort of an
exercise
in keeping track of signs and not screwing
up too much.
And, once we get to the end, I end up with
the same value, so last time
I had negative 6 plus 5 root 2 over 3.
the only thing that changed here is
somehow my negative 6 being ended
up second but we get the same answer so
that's a pretty good affirmation.