The last lesson in this set is
Marginal Density of a Bivariate Normal
Distribution.
So this was actually one of the integrals
that
motivated me to have this class in the
first
place because I gave this in Introductory
Statistics class
to people who haven't done Calculus for
quite some time.
And pretty much everybody fell flat on
their face.
So hopefully if we go through this one
time, I want to just point out some of
the tricks that pop up quite often when
we're integrating probability distribution
function, probability density functions.
And this a reasonably complicated and
useful example.
So if you thought the Black-Scholes
formula was difficult
[LAUGH]
this, this one is it's got the same number
of
variables but they have Greek names or at
least five of them have Greek names.
And so I think that makes people think
it's more complicated.
For the model I want to use, we can
simplify it a bit.
So it, what I would want to use this for,
its
a, for two random variables but
rather than being independent, they're
correlated.
And so this last argument that I have here
is a correlation coefficient.
When it's positive, it just means if first
random variable so if,
if x were large and I could observe that
before observing y
then I would expect y to be large as well.
If it were zero, then knowing the value of
x wouldn't tell me anything about the
value of y.
And if it were negative, then if I knew I
had a large
value of x, that would lead me to expect a
small value of y.
If I want to use this in a financial
application, the, the mu, these are sort
of expected values.
So there would be expected return.
And I, if I were using this for a
single asset, I would sort of say that the
expected
return in this period is probably going to
be
the same as this expected return in the
next period.
And then these sigma x and sigma y are
thought of as the, the risk of owning that
asset.
So the sigma x would be the risk in the
first
period, sigma y would be the risk in the
second period.
If the periods are next to each other and
reasonably short, then
you can also get away with just assuming
that that's the same.
So I'm going to rewrite this with
sigma x equals sigma y just equals sigma
and mu x equals mu y just equals mu.
And that'll at least make this fraction in
the right-hand side drop down one level.
Because I'll be able to take this, this
sigma x squared will be
the same as this product, sigma x sigma y,
and the same as this.
So I'll be able to write that just down
here.
And
then, the thing that I'm trying to compute
is called a marginal density.
So this is the density, you know, in
theory I have these two variables that are
somehow
behaving together, but if I don't, if I'm
in
a position where I can't see the other
variable.
So suppose I don't pay attention to what
happened on
the, during the first period and I just
wonder what's
going to happen in the second period,
that's the marginal density.
So, if I don't care about x and I just say
what, what's the best you can tell
me about y given that I'm choosing to
ignore
x, you end up with this thing called
marginal density.
And you get that just by integrating one
of the variables out.
So if I take a functions of x and y and I
integrate it from negative infinity to
infinity with respect to x, I'm going to
be left with this partial integral.
It's going to be a function of y and
that's going
to be called in probability and
statistics, the marginal density of y.
For our, for, you know, for this course,
I'm just doing one partial integral.
So let's see.
So that was my, my example was, oops, x
and y were returns on an asset in
consecutive periods.
And then the simplification I'm going to
make is that
the expected return on the asset is the
same in
each period and the risk that I'm taking
on by
investing on that asset during that period
is the same.
So I only have one mu and one sigma.
And so, I can almost force this onto one
slide.
So the, oh, oops, if I've done it the
other way around.
Yes.
So on the first slide, I said I was
going to get the marginal density with
respect to y.
Here, I'm doing the same thing with
respect to x but it's
exactly the same operation since it's
symmetric with respect to x and y.
So what I want to do is integrate this big
ugly bivariate
density function from minus infinity to
infinity with respect to y.
And one of the nice things to that,
I said this was the normal probability
density function.
It has this nice property that most of the
time when you
do things to it, the answer is a normal
probability density function.
So, a good first step and this happens
quite often, you can
usually make a pretty good guess as to
what the answer should be.
or you can at least guess, you know, what
it
should be if it's going to be easy to do.
you might try that and find out it doesn't
work
and then it's not going to be easy to do.
but in this particular case, I'm just
going to
guess that the marginal density is just a
univariate.
so this is the, the same, you know, phi
function.
It's just been scaled by a factor sigma
and shifted by a factor mu, but this
is a normal probability density function.
And so here, since I'm, oops, since I'm
integrating with respect to y, everything
in this
marginal density with respect to x is
going
to be constant with respect to this
integration.
So what I'm going to do is factor all of
that stuff out
of here, move it outs, oops, move it
outside of my integral sign.
Because if, if it's constant with respect
to y, it can cross the integral sign.
And then look at what's left, and hope
that
that's something I can figure out how to
integrate.
So, the idea is that I will end up with
this marginal density.
My guess at what the marginal density
function should be, times everything
that's left.
So, this C here is, this, this thing here
with
the 1 over square root of 2 pi sigma
factored out.
I just couldn't fit everything into the
slide if I did it.
And then, I have all of
this stuff left over.
And so I need to somehow show that this
integral from minus infinity to infinity,
this big ugly mess, dy is equal to 1.
And so this is, this is what this value of
C is equal to.
So it's if you multiply this by C, you
just
get the scaling factor from the, from the
bivariate density function.
>> Can we go back over this real quick
[INAUDIBLE]?
>> Yep.
>> I'm sorry, so you're taking your
guess for
[INAUDIBLE]
would be and multiply it by what we have
up above?
Is that what's going on?
>> So, what I've done, I've taken this
term here or this factor
here and I've split it up into this and
this.
Alright, so if I multiply those together,
I get this thing back.
And then, this is what I want to appear
outside.
Oh, and again, this should be an x.
It should be the same as this, just with
the opposite sign.
and so if I have a negative 1 here and a
positive 1 here, that would be e to the 0.
So it's basically what I've just done, is
multiplied this
thing by 1, but used a, a clever choice of
1.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay.
So now what I want to do is look at the
part that's in the
square brackets, so if I go back,
I'm looking at this, this square brackets
here.
I just, I want to simplify that.
So, this is the bit in the square
brackets.
If I wanted to do this subtraction, then
I've got 2 sigma squared in the
denominator here and 2 sigma squared times
1 minus rho squared in the denominator
here.
So I need to multiply those first term by
1 minus rho squared over 1 minus rho
squared.
So if I do that, then I can put everything
over a common denominator.
And I have 1 minus rho squared times x
minus mu squared.
And then, what I had originally.
And if you look at this carefully, I have
1 times x minus mu squared
minus x minus mu squared.
So this 1 is going to disappear.
This whole term is going to disappear and
what will be
left is negative rho squared times x minus
mu squared.
So let's hope that that's what I've done
in the next step.
Yep.
So I have negative rho squared times the
quantity x minus mu squared.
I have everything else still staying the
same here.
And let's see, what have I done?
So now I multiplied the numerator by
negative 1 and then I'm
going to cancel that out by multiplying
the whole fraction also by negative 1.
So that made my first term positive,
second term negative, third term positive.
And if you stare at this for a while, it
should start to look familiar.
So if
you think back to the Completing the
Square Lecture, you'll actually realize
that this
is already in the, the right form, it
could be written as something squared.
And that something is just going to be rho
x
sorry, rho x times the quantity x minus mu
minus y minus mu squared or
sorry, minus y minus mu.
Hopefully I'll get it right when I hit the
Next key.
So I have rho times x minus mu.
When I square that, I'm going to get this.
Then I have minus y minus mu.
And then the cross terms are going to be
rho x minus
mu y minus mu with a negative sign in
front of it.
I'm going to get two of those from the
outer and from the inner,
and so that's where this middle term is
coming from or going, I guess.
Okay.
And then I'm going to write this.
So it's exactly the same thing, I've
just sort of rearranged where I'm putting
parenthesis.
So I have y
minus something and that something is mu
plus rho times x minus mu.
So all I've done here, I had a, a rho
times
x, sorry, a rho times x minus mu and a
minus y.
so I did something that's a bit a bit
clever here.
Since this is squared, I can multiply the
inside by negative 1.
So I can actually write this as y minus
mu, minus rho times x minus mu.
And when I square that, the negative 1
will go away.
So it'll be negative 1 squared times the
product here.
So that lets
me put this term in front.
And this term, second.
So I end up with this y, oops, minus this
mu.
So this mu here becomes this mu here.
Then, I have minus rho times x minus mu
but since I'm writing it in these
parenthesis here, that minus has to be a
plus because that minus is going over
here.
So, I end up with mu
plus rho times x minus mu.
So, that's mostly just an exercise in
bookkeeping for science.
And then in the denominator, I'm going to
write sigma squared times 1 minus rho
squared.
As sigma times the square root of 1 minus
rho, I'll put that all in parentheses and
square that.
And now if you look closely at what this
is, this is a variable minus a constant
squared
over 2 times another constant squared.
And now I'm going to plug this back into
my square brackets here.
So this is what we had at the end of, you
know, two slides ago.
This was the thing where I said, I want to
show that this integral is equal to 1.
And
I want to look just at the integrand so
that's the C times the thing in the square
brackets.
So on the previous slide I found another
expression for what's in the square
brackets here.
And that's, I've plugged in here.
And then in my C constant, I'm going to do
the same thing I did I'm going to write
the sigma times the square root of 1 minus
rho squared in parenthesis.
And now this constant here is equal to
this constant here.
And if you think back to what did
the standard norm or what did the normal
density
function look like, in the original one
this was called sigma.
I just had a 2 sigma squared over in the
exponential part of the function.
And I had a 1 over square root of 2pi
times sigma.
So this is just a new value for a sigma.
And then the numerator of the exponential
part, I have y minus mu squared and so
now, I just had y minus something but it's
I'm integrating with respect to y.
And this doesn't have any ys in it, so
that's effectively a constant.
So this is actually a normal probability
density function,
just with a different mean and a different
standard deviation.
So this, this term down here is the
And this, this term here is the mean.
And so, if I let m
equal this guy here, which is that.
And I let
s equal sigma times the square root of one
minus rho squared, which is that.
And when I plug those in, I end up with 1
over the square root of
2 pi times s e to the minus y minus m
squared
over 2s squared.
And this is exactly the normal
density with mean m and then standard
deviation s.
And so if I integrate this, so I'm
integrating
this with respect to y from minus infinity
to infinity.
I know it's a density function so this is,
this is
sort of the big trick because I don't
actually have to do
the integral if I can show that it's a
density function
because I know every density function is
going to integrate to 1.
So
the integral of this normal density over
the entire real
line, so from minus infinity to infinity
is equal to 1.
And so now if I go back to, so this was
my, my big ugly formula.
I've just been simplifying and simplifying
the integral.
And now I have it oops, looks like the dy
disappeared off the end of the slide.
but the integral of this density
over the entire real line is equal to 1.
So, I get that my
marginal density was equal to 1 over the
square root of 2 pi sigma.
This is just the thing that I guessed and
factored out at the beginning.
oops, so, it looks like I switched the xs
and ys again, so this should be an x.
so x minus mu squared divided by 2 sigma
squared.
So I get that the marginal density of x is
also a a normal distribution.