Okay, and then onto the last section which
is continuity and asymptotes.
So most of the time when we have a
function F of X, if I take the limit
of that function as X goes to A then
that's going to be equal to F of A.
And, and in fact you know, sometimes it's
hard to imagine why that would not be
true.
I'll show you one, one picture in a
second.
But if you think about the, the quiz
question you just did, that is actually
well defined.
or sorry, there's a very good choice of a
number
to choose for that when x is equal to one.
But the function's not defined at one.
And so this is kind of the indea of
continuity.
If this blue curve is my function f of x
then you can think of it as a function's
continuous.
If I could draw the curve associated with
that function without lifting my pencil
off the piece of paper.
And so if I, if I have a point A on the
X-axis and input A, and if I just move
along the curve until I get to A,
then the value of that point should be
equal to f(a).
And so that's actually the concept of
continuity.
That's the definition of continuity.
So we say a function f is continuous at a
point a if the limit as x goes to a of my
function f of x is equal to f of a.
And then we can be a little bit, a little
bit more precise about this.
So we say a function is right continuous
if as I look at points that are greater
than a and kind of moved down towards a,
the limit of f of x is equal to f of a.
And then we have the same idea.
The function is left continuous at A.
If, if I look at points,
less than A and move towards A the limit
as f of x goes up to A is equal to f of a.
And so clearly if a function is continuous
it's going to be both right continuous and
left continuous.
And then we'll also say a function is
continuous
on an interval, so I named my interval c,
d.
So that's just the lower limit c, up to an
upper limit,
d if it is continuous at every point to a,
in that interval.
And so this Is kind of an idea of what a
discontinuity would look like.
So if there's a jump in the function for
one reason or another.
So this is pretty much the same thing I
had on the last slide.
It's just at this point a, I decided to
add a little bit to f of x.
So that explains this jump here.
And then the open circle means that I
follow this curve up to every point that's
less than A, but not A itself and then
this solid circle
means that I start at A and for every
point greater than A.
So, if the solid circle were down here and
the open circle would have to be
up here because the function can only be
defined To be one value at any given
input.
And that's just going to affect the, the
definition of whether it's left or right
continuous at that point.
So here is f of x continuous at a.
And I would say no, because if I look at
the limit as I go.
Towards A over here if.
I was bouncing back and forth.
You know sometimes I'm going to be quite a
bit
less than the function value, no matter
how thin I make
my interval, am always going to be able
to, and if I choose an epsilon
that makes a Range around this solid dot.
Say halfway in between the open circle and
the filled in circle.
I'm never going to be able to get any
points on this side, into that range.
So it's
definitely the limit as I approach a from
the left hand side,
it's going to be less than the value of
the function there.
So it's not continuous.
Is it right continuous?
So if I forget about this lower curve and
only look at
the stuff on the, the right hand curve,
you know, as I
move down since I've defined my function
to be the value of
the top curve at A it is going to be right
continuous.
But the reason that it's not continuous is
that it's not left continuous.
So as I approach this point a from the
left, the limit is
this open circle but the value of the
function is the filled in circle.
So that's the sort of the way we want to
give a rigorous definition to this idea of
Of continuity.
And so then again in a first-year calculus
text book, you're going to
be able to find lots of theorems about
when is a function continuous.
And so I'm just going to list off a lot of
these very quickly.
So, let f and g be continuous functions.
So they're continuous at a point a.
And again, c is just going to be a real
value constant.
So the sum of two continuous functions is
continuous.
The difference of two continuous function
is continuous.
If I multiply a continuous function by a
real
value, that's also going to give me a
continuous function.
If I take the product of two
continuous functions, that's going to be a
continuous function.
And as long as the denominator is not
equal to zero at the point A,
then the ratio of two continuous functions
is also going to be continuous.
And again, this is, this is a point wise
definition so this is only continuous as a
point A,
so all of these have to hold on an entire
interval for these functions to be
continuous on that interval.
Any polynomial, so, 1 useful interval is
R, that's all of the real
numbers, so everything greater than
negative
infinite and everything less than positive
infinite.
Any polynomial is continuous on the real
numbers.
And then the following functions are
continuous on their domains,
so the domain is just where the function
is defined.
So sometimes you have to be a little bit
careful, like if you
have the logarhythm, that's not going to
be defined for a negative number.
So like I said, a polynomial is continuous
on the entire real line.
So it's its domain is a entire set of real
numbers.
So it's continuous on its domain.
Trigonometric functions, so this is sines,
cosines, tangents, things like that.
You have to be a little bit careful
because sometimes
you end up Dividign by 0 for instance
without tangent.
But if you're not dividign by 0 it's going
to be continuous.
Rational functions so that was things like
f over g.
Inverse trigonometric functions, so this
is, you know if I say the sine of an angle
is a certain vaule.
I can do something called the arc sine of
that value.
Is going to give me that angle up to some
sort of multiplicity.
And so it's going to be continuous on the
right domain, and range.
The square root or cubed root, something
like that.
Exponential functions, and logarithmic
function.
So you can see from this set of sort
of seven things, there's probably not very
much that you
would normally be able to write down
that's not
going to be continuous at least on some,
on some domain.
And then also if you have a function of a
function so if g is a continuous function
and sorry if g is continuous at a, And
there's going to be a value g of a.
If f is continuous at that value g of
a, then whoops, f, so this, this means
composed with.
And the, probably the easier way to think
about it is just
f of g of x.
[INAUDIBLE]
.
That's also going to be a continuous at
the point A.
And so just a, a quick example.
where is the following continuous?
So it's log of x plus, arc tangent of x
divided by x squared minus 1.
So, this is a bit confusing sometimes.
Because if I put a 2 there, generally I
mean tangent squared.
If I put a negative 1 there, I mean 1 over
tangent, I mean arc-tangent, usually.
So, I would say, best to avoid this
notation.
Use arc tangent.
And if you need that to be a power just
write it as 1 over tangent squared or
something like that.
So this second bullet point is just
a little diversion to explain this, this
tangent.
Which I think basically was invented
because it fit nicely on calculator keys.
So, I'll first got a look at the numerator
here.
So I have log(x).
That's going to be continuous on its
domain, 'cause log is
a logarithmic function and its domain is
x>0 and arctan(x)
is going to be continuous For any X in the
real numbers.
So, the numerator is going to be
continuous for
any X in the interval from zero to
infinity.
Now I'm going to look at the denominator
Oops.
So x squared minus 1.
Well this is a polynomial.
We said polynomials were going to be
continuous on
all of the real numbers so this is
continuous everywhere.
And so f of x is then going to be
continuous.
Everywhere except where the bottom is
equal to zero.
So that was my one condition for a
rational function to be continuous, So X
squared minus one is going to be equal to
zero only when X is equal to one.
One or negative one, except that we're
really only considering Zero
to infinity because of the numerator.
So, the only point where I'm going to have
a problem is the x equal to 1.
And so that tells me that f of x is
going to be continuous on the intervals
0,1 and 1 infinity.
And by using the parentheses here I mean
zero one.
So every number that's greater than zero
and
less than one, but not zero or one itself.
If
I want to include the endpoints in my
interval, then I use square brackets.
And so basically, it's continuous on this
interval,
except when x is exactly equal to one.
And then just one last thing that I want
to stick somewhere in the course
and this is where I think it fits best is
the idea of a horizontal asymptote.
And so basically what I'm plotting here Is
this rational function X squared minus one
divided by
X squared plus one and I want to know what
happens to that as X becomes large.
And if you think about it,
you know, when, when X is small sort of
minus one
divided by one is going to be the dominant
part of this
but when X is big, like if X were 1,000
It's
going to be a million minus one divided by
a million plus one.
So it's going to be pretty close to one.
And so the definition of this red line.
So if I have, if I look at the limit as x
goes to infinity of f of x.
If that approach is some finite value,
then I'm going to say that this
function, f of x, has a horizontal
asymptote at that, at that value.
And the way I've, the way I've written
this, or
the way I've designed this example, you
get the same value
if I go Do plus infinity or minus
infinity, that doesn't necessarily have to
be the case.
So this L here doesn't necessarily need to
be the same as this L here.
And so this line is called the horizontal
asymptote,
if the limit as X goes to infinity is
equal to L Or if the limit, as x goes to
minus infinity, is equal to a different L.