Topic two is Vector Length and Planes.
So I'll start out with length.
And the length of a vector, w, is just
going to be defined.
so length of w, I'll use this notation to
mean length.
So it's just these two vertical bars, sort
of like a double absolute value, and it'll
just
be the dot product of the vector with
itself, and I'm going to take the square
root.
And so if you think about the reason for
the square root, if w or something
that was actually measured in units.
Then when I did this dot product, I'm
going to have W times W.
So whatever unit that would be, would be
squared.
And so if I want to talk about the length
of W, if W was measured
in feet, I want this length to come back
in feet, not in squared feet.
So the square root will get rid of that.
And In the plane, you can think about this
as just the standard
Euclidean distance between the origin and
the point described by W.
So for example, if W was a vector of four
components, then
the length of W is just the dot product of
W with itself.
That's just going to be the sum of the
squared components.
And then I'm going to take the square
root.
And the length of a vector is going to be
positive, except for the zero vector.
So remember the zero vector was a special
vector where every component was equal to
0.
And the length of 0 will be exactly equal
to
0 and any non 0 vector has to have
positive length.
And then there's a special vector that
useful
in a lot of situations that's called, unit
vector.
And this is just a vector whose length is
equal to 1.
And so if the dot product of two vectors
is equal
to one, then I don't have to take the
square root.
So I can just describe that as u dot u is
equal to one.
And usually that the reason the unit
vector is going to be useful is it,
is it captures the direction of a
vector without capturing the length of
that vector.
So if I have any non-zero vector, I can
find a unit vector.
So here I imagined w as a non-zero vector.
W with a little tilde above
it is going to be a vector that points in
the same direction but has unit length,
and I can turn any vector into that type
of unit vector, just by dividing it by its
length.
So W is a vector here, the length of W is
a scalar, so I'm just
using my property that one over the length
of W times W, that's also a vector.
Then this idea of length can be
generalized using something called a norm.
And so a norm is a function, I'm going to
use
the same notation here, that assigns a
length to a vector.
Here, I've put lengths in italics, because
the font that I use for these
slides doesn't really make italics stand
out that much I also put it in quotes.
So it's some quantity
that you can interpret like a length.
But it's not necessarily going to be the
euclidian
length of the, of the point from the
origin.
So a norm, to be a norm, this function has
to satisfy the following three conditions.
So,
a norm has to be, has to assign this
length quantity.
That's greater than or equal to zero.
And, it can be zero only for the zero
vector.
So, for a non zero vector, it has to
assign a positive length.
The norm of a sum of two vectors has to be
less than or equal to the norms of each of
those vectors.
And then if I scale a vector by a real
number
A, so remember if I have a scalar A and I
multiply that by a vector that gives me a
new vector
that just has A times the length of the
original vector.
And that is actually a condition that the
norm is going to enforce.
So A times X, the norm of that vector has
to be equal to the absolute value of A,
times the same norm, of X.
And
then important class of norms, are called
the, the p norms And the definition.
So, if I just use this notation.
So, and X or any vector with the two bars
on either side.
I'm ging to mean the, the standard vector
norm.
Which is just the uclidian distance
between the origin and the point.
If I put a subscript here,
that's how I'm going to communicate that I
want this norm to be some different
function.
So if I put a subscript p, what I'm going
to
mean is this expression here, so x i,
these are the components of my vector x.
I take the absolute value of those to the
p power and I sum them up.
And then I pick the pith root of that.
So one over p is the same thing as taking
the pith root.
And the standard vector norm Is just going
to be the 2-norm, in this notation.
So if I put a 2 here, I would be
squaring each component, so I wouldn't
need the absolute values anymore.
So that would be the sum of the squared
components, to the
one-half power, which would be the same
thing as the square root.
So, putting p equals 2 just gives me back
the, the regular norm.
Using
P different value can sometimes be useful
for solving different problems.
You can also define something called the
infinity norm,
where if you take the limit of this as P
goes to infinity, what it ends of giving
you
is just the maximum of the Elements of the
vector.
And, then there's also something called
the 1 norm.
Which is just going to be the sum of
the absolute values of the elements of the
vector.
And, this is, so, in statistics, this is
sometimes called the Manhattan distance.
So, if you imagine, so, Manhattan.
Is a city that's got a grid for its
streets.
it can be any city I suppose that has a
nice square grid for its streets.
And so if you wanted to describe how to
get from one address to another address
you'd have
to think of going sort of so many avenues
east and west and so many streets north
and south.
Where, you know, the euclidean distance
would be if I
just wanted to walk straight at where I
want to go.
you know, in New York city, the buildings
are all very tall,
so generally you can't walk the straight
direction where you want to go.
Okay.
And
we can also talk about the angle Between
two vectors.
So the dot product has a nice property,
that when two vectors are perpendicular.
So for instance if I thought of the vector
(1,0)
that would just be a vector pointing in
the X direction.
I could think of the vector 0,1, which
should be a vector pointing in the Y
direction.
If I took their product I would get 1
times 0 plus 0 times 1.
So, that's 0 plus 0 which is 0.
So, if I have 2 vectors.
So, this property
holds in general.
So, if I have 2 vectors that are
perpendicular,
when I take the dot product I get 0.
And then another little bit of knowledge
is if I define a vector V.
To be cosign phi, sign phi or some angle
phi.
Then this is always going to be a unit
vector.
And so I can see that just by computing
the length of V.
So I have cosine times cosine plus sine
times sine, and cosine squared plus sine
squared
is equal to 1, and when I take the square
root of that, I just get 1.
So the length of this vector V is equal to
1.
[SOUND]
So
I couldn't make all of this pop-up in
sequence like I normally like to.
So I had to just put it all on the slide
at the same time.
So if I define a vector U to be the vector
(1,4), so that's this black vector.
Pointing up here.
Then if I
find a unit vector pointing in the same
direction, so I can get that just by
dividing u by its length.
[COUGH]
Then the components of that unit vector
are
going to be the cosine of beta, sin beta.
So this angle here is beta.
And then I can do the same thing with w.
So here I'm just going to turn w into a
unit vector.
And then the components of that unit
vector are just going to be.
Cosine alpha,
sin alpha, so this blue angle here is
alpha.
And then if I look at the angle between
those two vectors, so the
angle between w and u, the cosine of that
angle, so here's I've defined that
to be this red angle, theta, the cosine of
that angle, is equal to
the dot product Of these two unit vectors,
the u tilde and the w tilde.
And then another nice property that I will
refer to later on, is called the Schwarz
inequality.
So it tells me that the dot product of
these two vectors u and
w, so these are the actual u and w, not
the unit vector any more.
This has to be less than or equal to the
length of u times the length of w.
And so remember when I, when I don't put
any subscript on
this norm operator, I mean the actual
Euclidean length of the vector.
OK, so now onto the second piece which was
planes.
So, so far, all of my examples have been
in two dimensions and that's mostly just
for convenience.
If it's two dimensional, I can draw a
picture of it,
and it also doesn't take up too much space
on the slide.
But everything, so dot products, lengths,
angle between two vectors All of
that's going to work in higher dimensions
too, using the same formula.
So a plane is a, so, when I was talking
about a plane, so
I had the XY plane and I had things that
lived in that plane.
They were lines and points.
Now, if I'm talking about three
dimensions, I could have a line
or a point or a plane that lives in my
three dimensional space.
So, a plane is just going to be a
2 dimensional sheet that lives in a 3
dimensional space.
So a simple example would, if I had, you
know x,
y and then z vertical.
I could think of x, y as defining a plane.
But there's no reason it needs to be flat,
you know, I could tilt
my plane like that or that, I could shift
my plane up and down.
So there can be a whole lot of planes
living in three dimensions.
And the way I'm going to describe a plane
in three dimensions, I'm going to pick a
vector n.
So this vector n is called a normal
vector, and I'm going to define my plane
to be all of the vectors that are
perpendicular to this normal vector n.
So, often normal means the same thing as
perpendicular in linear algebra.
And so if I have a vector, v, just
representing a point in my plane, p.
So, p is my plane.
And it has a normal vector, n, so there's
a, a plane,
and then there's a vector perpendicular to
that plane that's called n.
And if I took any vector in that plane and
I took the
dot product with the normal vector, then
by definition I should get zero.
Because if the vector is normal because
it's perpendicular to all the vectors in
the
plane, then my condition for a dot
product being zero was the vectors were
perpendicular.
And if I also allow 0 to be in the plane,
so this plane contains the origin,
so we'll generalize on that in a moment,
but
right now it's a plane going through the
origin.
Then I would have n dot 0 equal to 0.
And then if I had a plane now passing
through (x0, y0, z0), so this is just some
point
in space and I have a plane perpendicular
to this
vector n and it has to go through this
point.
Then, this is the equation you end up
with.
So, this is n dot v minus that point.
And, I can just write that out.
So, that's the first component of n
times x minus x,0.
Second component of n times y minus y,0.
And third component of n times z minus
z,0.
And that has to equal zero.
And so then what I'm going to do is just
move all of the- so the x,0,
y,0 and z,0 parts of this to the other
side of the equal sign.
And, when I add those up, so, nothing is
changing here.
The x0, y0, z0, that's a fixed, there are
three fixed numbers.
The normal vector has to stay the same,
so, n dot x0 y0
z0, that's just going to be a sum constant
which I called d.
And, so I end up with this equation.
So, some coefficient times x plus some
coefficient times
y plus some coefficient times z is equal
to d.
So, that's going to be the equation of a
plane with normal vector n.
And then, different values of d.
So if, if the planes are perpendicular to
the same vector, they're going to be
parallel.
So different values of d just shift the
planes
up and down, but they're never going to
intersect.
So the distance between those planes will
stay the same.
Oh wait, sorry.
Not the distance between the.
The distance between the planes is what's
changing.
Sort of the, the slope of the planes is
what's staying the same.
And then if I choose d equal to 0, that
gives me the plane through the origin.