The next thing we can do then is to group
the tasks we have just defined into
simple task networks.
And such a task network is really just an
acyclic directed graph.
And this graph consists of some nodes,
denoted by the set U and some edges given
by the set E.
And the nodes in a task network are
simply a set of tasks, t1 through tn,
where each of the elements in the set, t1
through tn, is a task.
So, it's a syntactic expression of the
form given a task symbol and some
arguments not just a task symbol.
And then, we have the edges in the task
network which simply define a partial
ordering of those tasks in the set U.
And then, what follows, I will use the
same notation we've seen previously so
that I can say that a task ti comes
before a task tj by using this symbol.
And that's it.
That's the task network consisiting of a
set of tasks, and a set of edges that
form a acyclic directed graph.
Note that the graph has to be acyclic.
And task networks, like tasks, can be
ground or primative, or both.
And a task network is considered to be
ground if all the tasks in it are ground.
Not just one, but all of them.
And it's considered primitive if all the
tasks in our network are primitive.
And it's ground and primitive if both the
properties hold for all the tasks in the
network.
But if only one task in the network is
unground, then we consider the whole
network unground.
And if only one task in the network is
non-primitive, then we will say that the
whole network is non-primitive.
Apart from being ground and or primitive.
a task network can also be totally
ordered or partially ordered.
To define the ordering of a task network,
we say that tu comes before tv in the
network w consisting of nodes U and edges
E if there is a path from tu to tv. Then,
we can say that our simple task network,
w, is totally ordered if the set of edges
in this network defines a total order on
our nodes.
And a total order here means that every
node is ordered with respect to every
other node by this network.
So, there are no two nodes in this
network that are not ordered with respect
to each other.
And if this is the case, then we can take
our network w and simply represent it as
a sequence of tasks written like this.
Here, just like we've written the
sequence of actions earlier.
This is a sequence of tasks starting with
tn and ending in t1,
which are all totally ordered with
respect to each other.
So, this gives us a third property that a
task network might have.
A task network can be totally ordered,
ground, and primitive.
And if we are given such a network
described by the sequence t1 through tn,
then we can define the plan that
accomplishes this task network by this
function pi of w, and is simply defined
as the sequence of actions a1 through an.
So, it's the same length in the sequence,
where each ai is the same as the ti.
So, the name is same as the name of the
task. In other words, each action
accomplishes the task that is at the same
position in the sequence of task in the
task network.
And to make sure you understood all this
correctly, here are a few examples from
our dock worker robot domain as an STN
domain.
The first we have given here is a set of
tasks, and the first task is t1 described
by taking with crane application
container, one from container two in pile
one.
This task is primitive.
It is primitive because we have an
operator that has the same name, namely
take.
And this task is ground because all the
arguments that are given to this task are
all objects and not variables.
Similarly, we have a task t2 which
consists of the same task symbol, take,
and it takes, with the crane at the same
location, container 2 from container 3 in
pile 1.
And again, this task is primitive because
we still have an operator with the same
name, take.
And it is ground because all the
arguments are constants and not
variables.
And then, we are given a third task here,
t3, which is move stack p1, q.
And this task, of course, is
non-primitive.
It is non-primitive because move stack is
not the name of an operator we've defined
in the dock worker robot domain, and is
un-ground, because q here is a variable.
We're not specifying the stack to which
we're trying to move our containers.
So, given these three tasks, we can now
form task networks.
And the first network we have is w1, and
it consists of all three tasks defined
above, t1, 2, and 3.
And just two ordering constraints, namely
t1 before t2, and t1 before t3.
So, this task network is partially
ordered because t2 and t3 are not ordered
with respect to each other.
It is non-primitive because it does
contain at least one non-primitive task,
in this case t3.
And it is unground because it also
contains one unground task, again this is
t3.
And then, we have a second example of a
task network, w2. This consists only of
the first two tasks, t1 and t2, and it
has only one ordering constraint, t1
before t2.
This network is totally ordered and we
can write it as a sequence t1, t2,
because all the tasks are ordered with
respect to each other.
And then, we can say that this network is
ground because, again, all the tasks in
it are ground, t1 and t2, these are the
two tasks here, were ground and
primitive.
And again, since these are the only tasks
we have here, this whole network is
ground and primitive.
So, this is a totally ordered, ground
primitive task network.
And that means we can immediately derive
the plan that accomplishes this task
network.
And this is pi of w2, as defined earlier.
Simply consisting of the two actions that
have the same name, the syntactic
expression describing this action, as the
two tasks in the task network.
So now, we know what tasks are and we
know how to form networks out of these
tasks.
And for some of these networks, we even
know how to form plans that accomplish
these task networks.