What we've seen so far is the complete
input that must be given to a planner.
Now we will turn to the output of the
planner which is, of course, a plan.
And a plan is a sequence of actions, A1
through AK.
We're using the pi symbol here to denote
the plan and the sequence consists first
of the action A1 then of the action A2
and so on until we reach the action AK.
And K must be greater or equal to zero so
the plan can be empty and contain no
actions.
The length of a plan then, is simply the
number of actions it contains.
So it is K, where K is zero or more
actions.
Given this definition of plans, there's a
number of things we can do with those
plans.
For example, we can concatenate plans.
That means, if we're given a plan that
consists of actions A1 through AK, and
another plan consisting of A prime one
through A prime J, then we can define the
concatenation of those two plans, as
simply the sequence of actions
consisting, first, all those actions from
the first plan.
And then, all those actions from the
second plan.
We can also extend our state transition
function as follows.
We can define a state transition function
for a state and a plan.
By defining that it is the state from
which we start, if our plan was empty.
So if there were no actions in the plan,
we simply remain in the same state.
But if there were actions in the plan.
So k was greater than zero.
Then what we do is we first execute the
first action.
That gives us a new state.
And then what we do.
We apply the state transition function,
recursively, to the remainder of our
plan.
For this to be well defined, of course
our action, A1, the first action in our
plan, must be applicable in the state in
which we're trying to apply the plan.
In any other case the state transition
function applied to the state and the
plan is undefined.
So the most important thing to remember
here is we define plans simply as
sequences of actions.
Of course there are more complex types of
plans but this is what we're looking at
here now.
The output of a planner is a plan.
But of course, not every plan is a
solution to a planning problem.
And here is how we can define what
constitutes a solution.
We are given a planning problem
consisting of a state transition system
or a set of operators.
An initial state, and a goal description
then we can say that a plan pi, is a
solution for a planning problem.
For this planning problem that we are
given here.
If the state transition function applied
to the initial state of the planning
problem.
And the plan that we're trying to execute
in that problem gives us a new state.
And that state satisfies the goal.
So, a plan is a solution, if the
execution of the plan leads us to a state
in which the goal is satisfied.
Since there may be many plans that are
solutions for planning problems, we want
to distinguish those.
And we can do that by defining some
properties of the solution plans.
So we can say that the solution is
redundant if there's a proper subsequence
of this plan, that is also a solution for
P.
So if we can take our plan pi, remove
some of the actions, and still have a
solution plan, then we call the original
plan redundant.
And we can say that the plan pi is
minimal if no other solution for our
planning problems contains fewer actions.
So it is minimal if it has the minimal
number of actions.
Now all the definitions you've seen so
far apply to classical planning.
But in fact, there are variations of what
is exactly classical planning.
Most of what we've seen so far is the
strips representation.
Here, I want to give you a quick overview
of what other flavors of classical
representations exist.
The simplest representation is the
propositional representation.
In the propositional representation, a
world state is described by a set of
propositions.
So, a proposition is a simple symbol.
It does not contain any internal
structure.
In the strips representation, in the
state, we have first order atoms,
ground atoms, to be more specific.
And these relate objects to each other.
In the propositional representation,
there are only propositions, symbols.
Actions in the propositional
representation consist of preconditions,
post-conditions to be added and to be
removed.
The first thing to note here is there are
only actions, there are no operators
because we don't have parameters and
that's because we have symbols that have
no objects they relate to each other.
So there's no variables which means
everything is ground, everything is in
action.
Then we have preconditioned propositions
which means we don't have positive and
negative propositions in the
preconditions.
Only positive propositions exist in this
simple representation.
And then we have negative and positive
effects, as before these are symbols not
ground atoms.
And I've also mentioned they are often
called the add list and the delete list
to be removed.
The strips representation then is simply
the same, but instead of propositions
we're dealing with first auto-literals,
in most cases.
Specifically this means the preconditions
of an operator can be positive or
negative.
The final variant is the state variable
representation where a state.
Consists of a set of state variables.
A state variable is simply a variable
that must have a value.
It's usually described by a function.
So, for example, we could have a function
that describes the location of the robot.
RLook that takes a robot as an argument,
and tells us where that robot is at
location L.
The advantage of this representation is,
that it represents the functional
property of this.
The robot can only be at one location at
any one time.
So in the strips presentation, at least,
in theory.
You can have several assertions of where
the robot might be.
In the state variable representation.
And, the functional property, namely that
the robot can only be at one location at
a time is exploited.
Actions in this representation are simply
undescribed by sets of preconditions that
look like expressions like this and
assignment of new values to these state
variables like this one.
So what you need to remember here is that
there are different flavors of the
classical representation, there's not
just the stripser presentation we've
looked at.
There's also these other two.
But, and this is the important point,
these representations can be translated
into each other so essentially they're
all equivalent in terms of
expressiveness.
There's nothing that you can say in one
of these three representations that you
can't say in the other.