As you may have guessed, we will be using
search to solve STM planning problems.
The search nodes in the search space that
we'll be searching will be task networks.
and the methods we have just described
will be used as refinement operations in
our new search space.
Methods give us the safe transitions we
need to move from one task network to
another, and the way this is done is that
we use methods to decompose tasks and
that's what I'll be talking about next.
Here is an example how decomposition
works in the Dock Worker Robots domain.
And to do the decomposition I've already
introduced the decomposition function
delta that takes a task, a method
instance, and substitution sigma.
We can visualize the process of
decomposition by means of a decomposition
tree which is what you see here.
The decomposition tree has as it's root
the task t.
So this is the task t, that we're trying
to decompose and that is the root of our
decomposition tree.
In this case, the task was to move the
stack from p1 to some other pile q.
Then, we have a method instance that
we're using to decompose the task with.
And the method instance here is recursive
move, p1, p2,
c1, c2.
And the final component the substitution
sigma tells us how we have to replace the
variables so that's what we find here, we
have to replace the variable q with the
value p2.
Then the children that we have off the
node that represents the task that we are
trying to decompose are exactly those sub
tasks that we find in the method.
So here it is the first sub task
move-topmost and here the second one to
move the stack.
The only other thing worth noting is this
arrow here, that underlines the
substitution and the method, and that
simply gives us the order in which we
have to execute the sub-task.
And if we look at this tree we can
immediately see what the result is by
looking at the leaf nodes.
So, this is the result of this
decomposition here, namely to move the
top most container from pile p1 to p2 and
then move the remaining stack from pile
p1 to p2.
As you can see there's quite a lot of
redundant information in this tree.
For example, you can derive the
substitution you're looking at from the
values used in the task and the method,
or in the sub tasks.
That is why when you see this tree later
in another example, I will leave out some
of that information to save a little
space and be able to draw bigger trees.
Now that we understand how to decompose a
single task in isolation, we will look at
how to decompose tasks that are in a task
network.
So we start with a task network, w,
consisting of nodes and edges where the
nodes are tasks and the edges are
ordering constraints.
And we want to decompose one of the
tasks, t, that is in this network.
And this must be a task that has no
predecessors in w.
So, if this network is totally ordered,
then it will be the first task in the
list.
If it's a partial-order network, there
may several tasks that have no
predecessor.
Then we want to decompose this task using
a method and this method of course has to
be relevant for the task under some
substitution sigma, and this method
itself will have a network consisting of
notes and edges.
Then we can define the decomposition of
t, the task t in the network w by method
m under our substitution sigma as
follows.
The first thing we have to do is we
replace our task t by the instantiated
network task that come from our method.
So from our original network w consisting
of the tasks in u we remove the task t
and in its place we put all those tasks
that are in and instantiate those with
the substitution sigma.
That is how we modify the tasks in the
network and then we also have to modify
the edges in the network.
And the edges we have to replace are
exactly those edges in e that involve t,
because t is no longer available as an
endpoint to an edge.
We have to replace them by edges to
appropriate nodes.
In our new set of nodes that we've just
introduced sigma of
To illustrate this, let us look at a
simple network that consists of two
tasks, task nodes, that I illustrate
here, and just one edge that orders
these.
Let this be our network w.
Then the only task that has no
predecessors here is this task here, and
that's the one we can decompose now.
And suppose we have a method that is also
very simple and decomposes our task into
another very simple network just like the
one above consisting of nodes 1 and 2,
let's say.
Then, the first thing our decomposition
function does is replace the task t,
so we have to remove it from the network.
And we insert the subtasks defined by the
method.
And these are, of course the tasks 1 and
2 from our method.
And then we have to replace all the edges
that were connected to t which is this
edge here and we can replace this with
edges to all the newly introduced nodes,
so we have to have an edge here and an
edge here.
But because we already have this edge,
there's no need to have the second edge
so we can actually omit that if we
wanted.
And in this example, the resulting
network would be the sequence consisting
of the node 1, 2 and this final node
here, which I'll call 3.
And what we have done to get to this
network, is we have applied the
decomposition function, which is defined
here.
And the application consisted of two
steps.
We have replaced the node t that we're
decomposing by all the nodes in the
network of the method.
And we've replaced all the edges that are
connected to T by edges to the new node.
And this is how you decompose a task in a
task network.