Welcome to the course on AI planning.
Planning is one of the most important
aspects of intelligent behavior.
The ability to identify and select
appropriate activity, and to project
forward the consequences of executing
that activity, is fundamental to humans
and intelligent robots alike.
The planning course lasts five weeks.
In the first week of this course, we will
formally define the problem solved by
planning algorithms and talk about the
context in which planning is used.
After that in week two, we will describe
some basic AI techniques used for problem
solving in general, and planning problems
in particular.
This will leave you with a good
understanding of the STRIPS planning
system.
In week three, we will look at different,
a different approach to the same problem,
namely, plan space search.
In addition, we will cover hierarchical
planning, which addresses a similar
problem and has been used in many real
world applications.
Week four gets us closer to the
state-of-the-art in planning research,
introducing some of the techniques used
in the fastest planners available today.
Finally, in week five, we will talk more
about application areas in which they AI
planning has been used, and some more
advanced topics.
The course is going to make use of
lectures on video, supplementary material
on a wiki, and we'll give you some links
to some AI planners to try, along with
relevant online resources, and some
recommended quite short readings.
There'll be a number of quizzes and
online assessments to monitor your
progress.
We're going to encourage you to use the
course social platform, which includes
the discussion forums in the wiki.
There's going to be a course Twitter tag
and there's also a virtual world meeting
space for you to try.
Full details of all aspects of the social
platform are on the course website.
We hope you will enjoy the course and
will learn something useful.