>> Before we go into the details of the
graph plan system, I want to start with a
simple example that we will use throughout
the segment.
This example is again from the dock worker
robot domain, so you should be familiar
with that.
And it illustrates the propositional
representation, so it consists of a
propositional planning domain and a
propositional planning problem.
To put the propositional representation in
context, here's a quick reminder of
classical representations, and I've shown
you this slide before.
So far, we've seen planning domains and
planning problems represented in the
STRIPS representation.
The STRIPS representation is exactly like
the propositional representation we will
see next.
But, it uses first order literals instead
of propositions.
So, the atoms are relations that relate
objects to each other.
We have also seen a specific syntax that
we can use to write STRIPS representation
domains and planning problems, and that
was the PDDL language.
Now, in the propositional representation,
a world state is simply a set of
proposition symbols.
And as opposed to first-order literals,
symbols don't have an internal structure.
And then, the actions in the propositional
representation consists of precondition
propositions, propositions to be added and
to be removed.
So the propositions to be added are the
positive effects, and the propositions to
be removed are the negative effects.
The precondition propositions correspond
to the positive preconditions in the
STRIPS representation.
And this is another difference between the
STRIPS representation, as we've seen it so
far, and the propositional representation.
In the STRIPS representation, we had
positive and negative preconditions, and
now we only have positive preconditions.
As it turns out, this isn't much of a
restriction, as every STRIPS planning
domain, every STRIPS operator that has
negative preconditions can be translated
into an equivalent domain and operator
that has no negative preconditions.
So, any problem that can be represented in
one of these two representations can be
translated into the other without much
difficulty.
And just as a reminder, there was also a
third flavor of this type of
representation, the state-variable
representation.
But, I won't go into detail here as we're
not going to use it in this segment.
But as a reminder, this representation is
also essentially equivalent to the STRIPS
representation.
So, nothing can be said in one of these
three representations that can't be said
in the others.
And here is an example world state from
our simplified dock worker robot problem
that we will be using in this segment.
In this state, we have only two locations.
Location 1 and location 2.
And they are connected by a path as you
can see in this image.
The two robots are called r and q, or
robot r and robot q, and are at the two
locations initially, r at location 1 and q
at location 2.
Both robots are currently unloaded, but
there are also two containers in this
state, and the two containers are
container a and container b, at the two
locations as shown here.
What's new here is that robots can load
and unload the containers autonomously.
So each robot has its own personal crane
attached to the robot that is carries
around with it.
Also, we will now think of locations as
being big enough for multiple robots.
Otherwise, there wouldn't be much we could
do in this state because both locations
are already occupied.
That really simplifies the problem a lot.
And the problem is then give by a set of
actions which I will describe shortly.
An initial state, which is shown here, and
a goal description which simply consists
of a state in which the two containers are
swapped.
So, in our goal state, we want container a
at location 2 and container b at location
1.
And here are the operators in the STRIPS
notation as we can use them for state
transitions in this simplified domain.
The first operator we have defined here is
the move operator which moves robot r from
location l to location l prime.
And since there can be multiple robots at
the same location, the preconditions and
the effects of the move action are
actually a lot simpler than what we've
seen previously.
Similarly, we have simpler load and unload
operations that take fewer parameters and
have fewer preconditions and effects
because the crane is now attached to the
robot.
That also means we don't need a take and
put action for the cranes.
One nice side effect of the simplified
problem is that none of the operators have
negative preconditions.
As I've just mentioned, that is one of the
features that we need for the
propositional representation.
Another interesting observation is to do
with the number of possible actions that
are instances of each operator.
So, looking at the move action first, we
have two possible robots, and we have two
possible locations that we can use for l.
And two possible locations that we can use
for l prime.
So, in theory, that means there should be
8 possible instances of this move
operator.
But when we look at the preconditions of
this operator, we have one precondition in
here that is static.
That is, this relation never changes from
any world state to another.
So, when we translate our operators into
actions, we can exploit that.
We now know that for this operator, there
are two possible robots.
And for this pair, ll prime, there are two
ways we can satisfy the adjacent relation,
as defined in our problem.
That means we have to multiply this by 2.
Giving us 4 actions that are possible in
this problem.
Now, let's have a look at the propositions
symbols we will use in our example to
represent world states and actions.
And since we'll have to handle quite a few
of these symbols in our actions, they are
actually very concise.
For example, we have the symbol r1 that we
use to denote that the robot with the name
r is at the location 1, r1 and r2.
Meaning that the robot with the name r is
at location 2.
The strips representation for these two
symbols will look something like this, r1
is at robot r location 1, and r2 is at
robot r location 2.
Similarly, we have equivalent symbols for
the other robot for robot q.
This symbol means that robot q is at
location 1, and this symbol means that
robot q is at location q.
And we also need symbols to express that
the robot is not loaded with the
container, and we use the symbol ur,
meaning that robot r is unloaded and uq to
indicate that robot q is unloaded.
So, that means that we have 6 symbols to
talk about the two robots.
But, we need more symbols to talk about
the containers.
And here, we have the symbol a1, for
example, meaning that container a is at
location 1.
Or more specifically, it means that this
container is at the unique pile that is at
that location.
So, it's not on a robot that is at
location 1, but really in that pile at
location 1.
Similarly, we have a symbol representing
that container a is at location 2 , in a
pile at location 2.
Or we have a symbol that says that
container a is on robot r.
Or the final location for the container it
can be on robot q.
This is container a on loaded onto the
robot q.
And we also need equivalent symbols for
our second container, container b.
And we have those here.
B1 means container b is in the pile at
location 1, b2, container b is in the pile
at location 2, br, container b is loaded
onto robot r.
And finally, bq, container b is loaded
onto robot q.
So that means we have altogether 8 more
symbols to describe the state of the two
containers.
And, of course, these symbols are already
sufficient to describe our initial state
which is given here.
In our initial state, our robot r is at
location 1, whereas our robot q is at the
other location, location 2.
The container a is in the pilot location
1, and container b is in the other pilot
location 2.
And both robots are unloaded.
These are all the propositions that are
true in the initial state, and all the
propositions not mentioned here are false.
And here are all the symbols we will use
to represent actions in this domain.
Let's start with the available move
actions.
And again, the symbols I'm using for
actions are quite concise.
So, this symbol here Mr12 represents the
action of moving robot r from location 1
to location 2.
The first thing that you note here is that
the first letter representing the action
is a capital letter.
I have used symbols with lower case
letters for state propositions.
And I will use symbols starting with an
upper case letter for action propositions.
And the first letter indicates which
action this is.
M for move.
Then, there are the parameters represented
by single letters here.
Namely r, we're moving robot r, and we're
moving it from location 1 to location 2.
Then similarly, we have Mr21 indicating
that we're moving robot r from location 2
to location 1, representing this action,
this instance of an operator.
Similar actions for robot q are Mq12.
Meaning, we're moving robot q from
location 1 to location 2.
And here, we have Mq21, moving robot q in
the other direction from location 2 to
location 1.
So, these are the four possible move
actions that exist in this problem
instance.
Similarly, we have actions representing
loading of containers, and these all start
with the capital letter L, like Lar1,
meaning we're loading container a onto
robot r at location 1.
And here is what that was as an operator.
Then, we have Lar2.
Meaning we're loading container a onto
robot r at location 2, and so on.
We have symbols for loading container a
onto the different robots at the different
locations.
And symbols for loading container b onto
the different robots at the different
locations.
And finally, we have the unload actions.
The unload actions start with the capital
letter U like Uar1 here, which means we're
unloading container a from robot r at
location 1.
And of course, the other unload actions
follow all the same pattern.
We have the letter U, followed by the
container we're unloading, the robot from
which we're unloading it, and the number
Indicates which location this is happening
at.
So, what we have here is 4 plus 8 plus 8.
All together 20 diffeent action symbols
representing 20 different types of
actions.
And we had 14 different proposition
symbols that we use in states.
So, all together we have 34 different
symbols we need to deal with.
And that concludes my simplified DWR
problem in the propositional
representation.