The fact that the 8 puzzle, the search
space usually fits into memory means we
can do some interesting analysis on this.
So here's the example we've seen earlier.
This is the same initial state we've seen
before.
What we have for this initial state is
that we can move in all 4 directions and
so we have 4 successors for this state
and they are shown here as the 4
successors of this node.
Note that all the arrows here are
bi-directional because, in this search
problem, as in many others, actions are
reversible, which means I can always go
back and forth between 1 state and 1 of
its successors.
So there's already a little optimization
potential for our search algorithm.
We can avoid reversible actions.
So, looking at the successes we have 3
possible actions here.
But of course, 1 of them would us get
back to the initial state.
So, in fact, there's only 2 successes
that we would generate here.
For this, again, we have 3 possible
actions here.
3 possible actions.
And there, 3 possible actions.
Which means, for each of those.
Successors we generate 2 more successors
as shown here.
So we look at 1 example here where we
have moved the empty tile up and this
gives us those 2 successors and in this
case there are 2 actions here and 2
actions there which means for each of
those as only 1.
Possible, real successor, but again note,
it's a by directional arrow, so, we can
go back and forth between these states.
And so on I can follow this path, and
generate more successors.
You can see there, I've ignored some,
that I didn't generate, or didn't look at
in detail, and so on.
Here is where I'm simply running out of
slide, otherwise I would have gone a
little further.
And then you would see what I'm
effectively doing here, is the moves I'm
following are simply shifting the empty
tile in this circle.
And, what this means is eventually, this
path will lead up here again.
We're back at our initial space.
So, this shows that as a graph, and it's
a graph that contains quite some long
loops.
And as I said before we can actually
create the whole search space and then
analyze how deep the different solutions
are.
And this is what this graph shows us.
We have here the depth of the different
solution nodes, so what we did is we
started a generation from the solution
node and generated all the different
nodes that are availible in the search
space and these are the depth at which
they are from the solutions.
And here we've the number of different
states that are at that depth.
Altogether there's about 180,000
different states in the search space.
And we can see that most of the states
are actually at around depth, what is
this, 24.
So, as I have said before the number of
states we generate in both tree and graph
search grows exponentially.
So what we can expect is that this will
initially more or less follow the states
base here that we generate the No's as
they are available.
But then, then for tree search this will
continue to grow exponentially so this
goes up here somewhere, and out of the
slide.
But then we see for the worst case here,
at depth 31, there's really only two
different states.
And if we wanted to use tree search to
search for those states, we would have to
generate all those states up here where,
in fact, there are only 2.
So what this would lead us to expect is
that tree search is reasonably efficient
up to about this depth here and then
becomes incredibly inefficient and we
should use graph search for these worst
case scenarios.
But then graph search also has some
additional costs.
We need to maintain that hash table, as
we've seen.
And comparing states in the hash table,
well depending on the complexity of these
states, this can take up quite some time
too.
So there's a basic trade off here.
Another problem is related to
permutations of solutions.
By that I mean, if we are given one
solution part from the initaial state to
a goal node, if we can swap some of the
states and some of the actions on that
path to obtain a different solution path,
then this is a permutations of that
solution, and this creates problems for
that star.
Often permutations are allowed if we have
independent actions in our domain.
So if for all states, if we first apply
one action and then another, we get one
state and that is the same state as
applying the actions in the reverse
order, then we say these 2 actions are
independent.
We could, in principle, execute those 2
actions in parallel, but isnce we are
only looking at action sequences so far,
we have to choose an order.
And since the order doesn't matter, we
have a permutation in our solution here.
The state that is the result of applying
these two actions, in which ever order we
choose them is the same.
Now why is this a problem for a star? And
here is the worst case scenario.
This is unrealistic but it is the worst
case.
Suppose we are given a the search problem
where we have an intiatial state and we
found a path to our goal state and
they're many intermediate notes here.
And our optimal path has a lenth of n,
and the worst case is that All these n
actions are independent.
It is easy to show that if all the pairs
of actions are pair wise independent,
then we can basically permute those
actions into any order we like, and it
doesn't change the outcome of the plan.
Now remember what I said earlier about
contours, namely that a star, if the
optimal solution length is n in this
example, will need to generate all the
nodes within a smaller contour.
So, if the F value is n-1 then this is
the contour that a star will generate
with the FLU being equal to n-1.
What this means is that it will generate
all those permutations that have n-1
nodes.
So what this means is in this part
there's n-1 factorial, different
combinations of solutions.
And, we'll explore all these paths before
it moves on to the first solution.
Of course, then it will find n factorial
solutions for this problem which are a
lot of solutions.
And, you should now understand that there
is no way around this, of course.
So you can now go and experiment with
this by programming all this in your
language of choice.
Specifically, why don't you try to
generate this graph here that tells us
how many different states exactly there
are at the different depths.
So for example, how many states would you
find here at depth 27? That is a
question.