>> As I have told you before, the graph
plan planner performs two types of
operations.
The first is forward planning graph
expansion, which is what we've looked at
so far.
And the second is, a backward search
through the planning graph.
This backward search is what we're going
to look at next, although I probably don't
have to describe this to you.
I could just say that this is a depth
first graph search, where the search nodes
are subsets of nodes from the different
layers.
But, for those of you that find that a
little superficial, here comes the detail.
And here is an overview of the search
procedure followed by graph plan.
We start by searching backwards from the
last proposition layer in our planning
graph.
Of course, this layer Pk, must contain all
the goal propositions, and none of these
goal propositions must be mutex.
Otherwise, the planning graph cannot
contain a solution plan.
So, this is where we start the search and
the remaining three steps describe how we
proceed with the search from any
proposition layer.
So, we assume that g are the current set
of goal propositions that we're trying to
achieve in a given proposition layer Pj.
Initially, this is the last layer.
But, during the course of the algorithm,
this will move backwards through the
graph.
And what we do to achieve these
propositions in layer Pj is to look for a
set of actions, pi j, that are a subset of
the actions in layer Aj.
So that's the layer before Pj.
And, of course, the actions that we're
looking for must together achieve all the
conditions in g, and they must not be
mutex.
Then, we can simply take the preconditions
of all these actions as our new subgoal,
the new propositions that we try to
achieve in proposition layer Pj minus 1.
And, of course, the search ends when we've
reached the layer P0.
And here is an example of how this works
in the planning graph we've seen before.
We start with our original goal consisting
of two goal propositions in the last
proposition layer which is P3 in this
graph, and this layer does indeed contain
the two goal propositions and they are not
mutex here.
Then, we have to chose a set of non-mutex
actions in our action layer A3 that
together achieve all the goals in
proposition layer P3.
And the positive effect links tell us what
options we have here.
And in this case, it's quite simple.
We choose these two actions here.
Then, we can follow the preconditioned
links to identify the subgoals in our
proposition layer P2.
And these are those four subgoals as you
can see here.
So far, this corresponds to one iteration
in our search algorithm.
And now, we can continue as before, we use
the positive effect links to identify
actions in the next action layer which is
A2.
And we see here each of these propositions
can be achieved by one action.
But, remember this graph does not show the
no-op operations that should be in this
layer.
I just left them out to save some space.
So technically, there are two more ways of
achieving these two propositions here.
Namely using the no-op operations.
Taking them straight from the preceding
layer.
And that's what we will do here.
So, from the actions shown here, we select
those two and we also take the two no-op
operations to achieve our goal
propositions in layer P2.
Then, we can use the precondition links to
identify the next subgoal in layer P1.
So, these are the preconditions of all the
actions we have chosen, including the
no-op operations here for subgoals.
And that concludes the second iteration
through our search.
So now, we proceed as before.
We use the positive effect links to
identify the actions in action layer A1,
and we can also use some no-op operations
as shown here.
But in addition to the no-op operations,
we also need two of the actions listed
here, namely those two.
And again, we use the precondition links
to identify those propositions in layer P0
that we need to be true.
And, in fact, as you can see here, all six
of the propositions in layer P0 are
required for this problem.
So that means we have found a solution
plan in our planning graph.
And it is a layer plan consisting of those
two actions in action layer 1, those two
actions in action layer 2, and those two
actions in action layer 3.
That's the plan we have come up with, the
plan we have found through backwards
search in our planning graph.