We have now seen what Tasks and Task
Networks are and how we can use methods
to decompose these tasks into sub tasks
in a network.
That means we have the basics for our new
search space, task networks as search
nodes at methods with decomposition as
state transitions in this new search
space.
That means we can now define domains,
problems and solutions to planning
problems.
Let's start with STN planning domains.
These are the reusable components that we
can use to define many problems.
And an STN planning domain is simply a
pair consisting of a set of STRIPS
planning operators.
That's the set O, that's it here.
And it has also in addition a set of
methods STN methods.
That's the set M.
So, you can see, it's an extension of the
STRIPS planning we've seen before because
the operators still make up the domain.
but, in addition to operators, we now
have a set of methods.
That's really all there is to STN
planning domains.
Now, one special case are total-order STN
planning domain and we say that a domain,
D, is a total-order STN planning domain
if every method In its message said is
totally ordered.
And later when we look at STN planning
algorithms we will see that totally
ordered networks are slightly easier to
deal with.
So first we will have this as an
algorithm and secondly we'll introduce an
algorithm that solves partial order STN
planning problems.
Now that we have defined STN planning
domains we can turn to STN planning
problems.
And an STN planning problem is a 4-tuple
consisting of Si, Wi, O and M.
And I'll explain these four components.
The first component, Si, is the initial
state of the world from which we are
planning.
So, this is a set of ground atoms.
And that means, it's just like for a
Strips planning problem, which also had
an initial state consisting of a set of
ground atoms.
What is different here is that we don't
have a goal component as part of our
planning problem.
Instead, we are given an initial task
network.
And that is what Wi is.
So the problem, then, consists of
refining this initial task network into a
plan.
And you will see that this initial task
network often consists of just a single
task in which case this forms the route
of our decomposition tree.
The remaining two components, O and M
simply form an STN planning domain that
we also give as part of our planning
problem.
So you can see an STN planning problem is
not very different from a strips planning
problem.
We still have an initial state and we
still have a domain.
Of course, the domain is now a domain
consisting of operators and methods.
What's really different is that we don't
have a goal, but an initial task network.
And as for planning domains, we have a
slightly simpler version here namely, a
total-order STN planning problem.
A total-order planning problem is one
where both the initial network and the
domain are totally ordered.
So, in the domain, all the methods need
to be totally ordered and in the task
network, that we're initially given, all
the tasks must be totally ordered.
If this is the case, then our planning
problem is totally ordered.
Ordered.
STN domains and problems were quite
straightforward, and should be easy to
understand.
STN solutions are a little more complex.
And the reason for this is simply that,
the definition is the blueprint for the
algorithm that will follow.
So understanding this definition will
help you understand the algorithm.
Algorithm.
What we need to define here is the
following: we need to define for a given
planning problem consistent of initial
state, initial task network, operators
and methods.
When does a task pi consisting of actions
a1 through an constitute a solution for
this STN planning problem? And this is
the case, if one of the following 3
conditions holds.
And the first condition is quite trivial
here.
Namely, if our initial network, Wi, is
empty.
So there were no tasks in the network.
And our plan is also empty.
Then, this plan constitutes a solution
for this network in the planning problem.
So that's quite obvious.
If there's nothing to do, doing nothing
is a solution for the problem.
the next collision is a little more
complex.
So suppose there is a primitive task t in
our network and that task has no
predecessors in the network so it's one
of the first components in that network.
Also suppose that a1 the first action in
our plan is equal to t. So this action
accomplishes this first task in our
network and suppose it is applicable in
Si the initial state.
Then we can say our plan, consisting of a
1 through a n, is a solution to our
planning problem, including the network
Wi, if the following conditions hold.
If the modified plan, pi dash, consisting
of the actions a2 through an.
So that's all the actions apart from the
first one, is a solution for a modified
Planning problem and this modified
planning problem simply starts at a
different initial state and then the
states that we get after applying the
action a1 in our previous initial state.
So we take the successor of our initial
state given our action a1 given our new
initial state in our new Planning
problem.
And we remove the task t from our task
network and of course we also remove all
the edges connected to t.
The operators and methods remain the
same.
So, if our slightly shorter plan is a
solution for our modified planning
problem then we know that the longer plan
is also a solution to our original
planning problem.
And the third alternative in our
definition follows a similar pattern.
Now we assume there is a non-primitive
task t in our network.
Previously it was primitive task, now
we're looking for a non-primitive task
that has no predecessors in the network.
Take one of the first tasks, this time
it's non-primitive.
Now, suppose we have a method, M, that is
relevant for this task.
That is, there is a substitution, sigma,
such that sigma(t) is the task of the
method.
And suppose this applicable in our
initial state.
Then our plan pi is a solution for our
original planning problem if it is also a
solution for a modified planning problem.
And this modified planning problem
consists of the same initial state.
But then, we have to decompose the task
network, Wi, which contains the task t as
one of it's first task, using method m
and substitution sigma.
And this gives us a new task network that
we take as part of this modified problem.
And again, the operators and methods
remain the same.
So, if our plan pi is a solution to this
modified problem, then our plan pi is
also a solution to our original problem.
What we have here are 3 alternative
cases, namely the task network is empty
which means there is no first task in the
network or the task network has tasks
that are first in the network and they
can be either primitive or non-primitive.
One of these three cases must always
hold.
So one of these three branches in the
definition is always applicable.
And as I said before, the algorithm that
we will see for solving STN planning
problems will closely follow this
definition.