In this next segment you will learn about
a completely different approach to the
planning problem.
We will still use search to solve
planning problems, but we will consider a
completely different search space.
In this new search space we will be
looking at, the search states will be
partial plans.
Partial plans simply consist of part of
what we finally have in the solution
plan.
The components of the solution plan will
be our partial plans.
So let's have a look at what these
partial plans, the search states in our
new problem will look like,.
Just as a reminder, let's look at
state-space search.
What we did in state-space search is we
searched through a graph of nodes
representing world states.
So the nodes were world states in our
search.
What this means is that if we were doing
graph-search, the graph we were
generating while we're doing search looks
exactly like the graph of the state
transition system.
This is not the case for plan-space
search, which is what we'll be looking at
here.
Here, we are searching through a graph of
partial plans as I've already mentioned.
In this graph, the nodes are partially
specified plans,
so they're not complete plans that we can
execute yet.
And then we have arcs in our search space
and these are plan refinement operations.
They tell us how we can move between
partially specified plans usually by
refining them and adding more content to
these plans.
And finally we have a new concept of
solution to planning problems namely
partial-order plans in which the actions
are not in a total order as we've seen
previously.
So remember, previously we have seen
plans that consist of actions that are
only in sequence after one another,
but now we will also be looking at plans
where actions can be in parallel, so they
are partially ordered.
If our goal was somewhere over here and
we hadn't gotten there yet, this could
actually be a partial plan that we
encounter as a search node on our way to
the goal state.
So what is a partial plan? I'll now try
to answer this question informally before
I give you the formal definition.
In the introduction to this course, I
told you that the plan in general is a
set of actions organized into some
structure.
In the kind of planning we've looked at
so far, the structure was always a
sequence,
but this characterization of plans
already gives us the first idea of what
could be a partial plan.
If a complete plan is a set of actions,
then a partial plan could simply be a
subset of those actions that are part of
the complete plan,
so not all the actions are in our plan.
Also if in, our complete plan, the
actions are organized into some
structure, then we could have a subset of
the structure for our partial plan.
In a sequence of actions, all actions are
ordered with respect to each other.
So again, we could drop some of the
ordering constraints and have this as a
partial set, a partial plan that does not
contain all of the ordering constraints
of the original plan.
Also, in the planning algorithms we've
looked at so far, we always had a reason
for introducing actions into a plan, that
is the rationale of introducing that
action to the plan.
In forward search we have considered
those actions that were applicable and
then in backward search we have
considered those actions that are
relevant.
An action being relevant or applicable is
the rationale for considering that action
in a plan.
If we had recorded that rationale as part
of the plan, then we could drop it again
here and have a partial rationale as part
of a partial plan.
And finally, as part of the planning
process, we have used operators and
turned them into actions.
That means we've introduced variable
bindings.
We've assigned values to the parameters
of the operators to turn them into
actions.
Now, we can use a subset of these
variable bindings to create a partial
plan.
So this tells us there are four different
ways of making a plan partial, namely by
including only a subset of the actions, a
subset of the temporal constraints, a
subset of the rationale, or a subset of
the variable bindings.
Now, here is the formal definition of
what constitutes a partial plan, and a
partial plan is defined here as a four
tuple consisting of four components.
It consists of actions, it consists of
ordering constraints, variable bindings,
and causal links representing the
rationale why actions are in the plan.
So let's start with the first component,
that's the set A of actions in the plan.
In fact, these are partially instantiated
planning operators,
so we take planning operators.
We may bind some of the variables with
values and those are our partial actions
that we consider part of our plan.
We have a set of these actions, not a
sequence,
so they are not necessarily ordered with
respect to each other as part of this
set.
The ordering relations are maintained
explicitly in this ordering relation,
that is the second component of a partial
plan.
And the ordering relation consists of
pairs of this form, ai before aj, simply
saying that the action ai, which must be
a member of our set A comes before the
action aj in our plan that we're building
up here.
The third component of a variable
bindings for the actions in our set A and
these variable bindings tell us what
values the variables can take.
Variable binding constraints can be more
general than just assigning a specific
value to a variable.
In fact, we will allow three different
forms here,
namely x=y saying that two variable must
have the same value or x unequals y,
meaning that the two variables must have
a different value,
or we can specify a domain for variable
saying this variable must have a value
from a given set of values.
,, the fourth component are the causal
links that are part of this plan and they
are of the syntactic form here.
They connect actions ai and action aj
through this proposition p.
And here's what this all means.
So ai and aj must be actions in our
current partial plan.
Also, the action ai, the first component
must come before the second component,
so we must have an ordering relation in
our ordering constraints of this type ai
before aj.
Then, the proposition p must be an effect
of ai, so it is produced by ai and is a
precondition of aj, which mean aj is
consuming this proposition.
That is why ai is called the producer in
this causal link and aj the consumer of
this proposition.
The proposition p is the protected
proposition as we are not trying to
interfere with this proposition before aj
can consume it. And finally, since these
expressions all contain variables we've
got to make sure that the binding
constraints for variables that we are
using in ai, in aj and also appearing in
p are consistent and are also appearing
in our binding constraints the set B.
So, in short, remember this, a partial
plan is a four tuple consisting of
actions, ordering constraints, variable
bindings and causal links where a causal
link connects a producer to a consumer
via a protected proposition p.
So that's what a partial plan looks like
and the search nodes in our search space
will be partial plans.