Now with a formal definition of a STRIPS
planning domain, we can now define a
STRIPS planning problem.
A STRIPS planning problem is a triple
consisting of three components,
and these are given here.
This is, of course, the state transition
system that we're looking at.
This is the initial state and that is the
goal.
So, what are these formally?
The first is a STRIPS planning domain
that is defined over some first order
language we've seen earlier.
And again, we have the state space here,
the action space and the state transition
function as we've seen in the previous
slide.
Then there are two more things we need
for a planning problem.
The first is an initial state which is
simply one of the states in our states
base.
Finally, the goal of a planning problem
is defined as a set of ground literals.
And once we are given a goal described in
this way, we can define the set of
possible goal states, as all those states
in s that satisfy the goal.
And satisfaction was something we defined
earlier,
you may remember the symbol.
We said that s satisfies g if all the
positive literals in g are true in s and
none of the negative literals in g are
holding in s.
So that is the definition of a planning
problem.
An interesting observation is that goals
are defined as exactly the same things
that are the preconditions of operators
namely sets of literals or for actions
sets of ground literals.
That is not a coincidence.
And here's a very simple example of a
STRIPS planning problem, a DWR example
from the dock worker robot domain.
The planning domain is the one we've
defined earlier consisting of the five
operators described in PDDL.
Then I need to pick an initial state
which is what I've done here, so this is
our initial state and I've described that
in this expression here as a set of
ground atoms.
So each of those are relations that
relate different objects in the domain to
each other.
It's a very simple example as you can
see.
And then I have to pick a goal, which is
a set of ground literals.
In this case, I want the robot to be
loaded with a container, so it is not
unloaded, and I want the robot to be at
location too.
These are my two goal conditions, and in
this simple example, there is only this
one state, that is a goal state.
And here is a definition of a planning
problem in the PDDL syntax.
Note that this is a different problem so
it is not the problem we have seen in the
previous slide.
In PDDL we of course must define the
initial state, and the goal.
Just like we need for any planning
problem.
But there are a few other things that we
need to define.
The first thing is, we can give the
planning problem a name, so we can refer
to it.
That's what we do here, it's a DWRPB1
problem.
Then we can say which domain we're using.
And we're saying that by referring to the
domain name as shown here.
Then we can explicitly define what
objects we're using in this domain.
This is actually optional and requires
the typing extension.
So we say that there's one robot which is
a type robot.
then we have two locations, two cranes
and four piles here and all together we
have six containers and the palate.
The palate is of course also defined in
the domain, but that doesn't matter here.
So this declares what things exist in our
states.
Then the initial state contains the
ground atoms that relate these objects to
each other.
So that's what we got here.
We start off with a static relations.
These are the things that describe the
topology, and won't change from state to
state.
So there's the adjacency between the two
locations.
There is where the different piles are.
Piles one, P1 and Q1 are at location one.
P2, Q2 at location two.
And where the different cranes are.
One crane at each location.
Then we have.
The dynamic relation's listed next.
And they tell us what is in the first
pile.
Namely, container A, B, and C.
Here's the order of the containers on the
pallet.
Container C is at the top.
The same for the second pile.
This is also at location one, containing
three containers, stacked on top of each
other.
And container F at the top.
The piles at the other location are both
empty as you can see here because the top
of the pile is the pallet.
Finally we learn where the robot is and
that's unloaded and also that the two
cranes are currently not holding
anything.
That was the initial state, and now comes
the goal.
The goal is described as a conjunction.
So all of these things must be true.
And it's simply saying, in which pile the
different containers must be.
Ca must be in P2.
Cc in P2, and so on.
And the other four containers must be in
the pile, Q2.
So it doesn't specify the order in which
the containers must be in those piles,
just in which piles they must be.
Note that there are no negative goals in
this example but of course it is possible
to define negative goals in general.
And if you find this a little hard to
read again here's the URL where you can
find the complete description of this
problem so you can download it and read
it in quiet and peace later.