So now that you know how the A* algorithm
works, I want to go a bit in to the
theory, and give you some properties of
the algorithm.
These all rely on the fact that the
heuristic use is admissible.
And we will talk about that first.
A heuristic is called admissible if it
never overestimates the distance from a
node to the nearest goal node.
So what this means is that the value of
the function h(n) must always be less or
equal than the actual distance to the
nearest goal node.
The equality is actually quite important.
For example, the heuristic value of a
goal node is equal to zero and therefore,
it's equal to the actual distance to the
goal node.
So any heuristic must have that property.
In other words, there's usually at least
one node for which the equality holds
namely, the goal node.
Unfortunately, this is often the only
node for which this holds.
Otherwise, we would have a perfect
heuristic, and that is too good to be
true.
Admissible heuristics usually think the
nearest goal node is closer than it
actually is.
They tend to underestimate the distance
to the goal.
An example of an admissible heuristics is
one we have seen for the touring Romania
problem, namely the straight line
distance.
The shortest distance between two points
on a map is usually the straight line.
Hence the straight line distance
heuristic must underestimate the actual
distance along a road.
Thus, it is an admissible heuristic.
For A* search, here's what that means.
We set that the evaluation function f(n)
represents the cost over the shortest
path through node n to a goal node.
So if the uristic never overestimates the
distance from n to the nearest goal node,
then the evaluation function used by A*
never overestimates the true cost of a
lu, solution through the node n.
This brings me to the most important
property of A* namely that it is optimal.
We can prove the following theory.
A* using tree search is optimal if the
heuristic h is admissible.
Just as a reminder, optimal here means
that the algorithm is guaranteed to find
the shortest path from the initial state
to a goal node.
And this theorem tells us that if our
heuristic is admissible, then A* will
return with an optimal path.
That is of course a very useful property
for a search algorithm to have.
By the way a similar theorem can be shown
for A* using graph search but I won't go
into this here now.
Another property of A* is that it is
complete which means that if there is a
solution, A* can find the solution.
This can be shown using something called
contours.
And since this is quite an interesting
concept, I want to introduce this here.
So contours are sets of states that can
be reached within a certain cost.
This is a bit like a topographic map that
you've all seen, I hope.
In a topographic map, you see lines
indicating points of equal altitude.
Here the contour is a line indicating
nodes of equal F value, and all the nodes
within the contour belong to the set.
A prerequisite for being able to draw
contours is that the f values along a
path are non-decreasing.
So what this means is that as we move
away from the initial state the f values
are usually increasing.
Now the way A* works fundamentally is
that it starts from the initial state and
then adds nodes according to these
contours.
It always starts with a smaller set and
then increases the F value as it goes
along.
But it will always explore nodes with
lower F values before it moves to a
higher plateau, so to speak.
If our heuristic function always had the
value zero,
what A* would do is essentially draw
circles around the initial state.
If the heuristic always had the value
zero, this would, of course, be
uninformed search.
And, in fact, this algorithm has a name.
It's called uniform cost search, or
Dijkstra's Algorithm.
But with the heuristic that provides some
information what happens is that the
contours become ellipses that are drawn
towards a goal state, so they try to get
closer to a goal state.
And the more accurate our heuristic is
the more these ellipses stretch towards a
goal.
A completeness of A* simply follows from
this, because as it explores more and
more nodes the contours are growing and
growing.
And eventually this must include a goal
node.
This is true, because each contour can
only contain a finite number of states.
And once these are all explored, A* will
go to the next higher altitude for bigger
contour.
And here is what this looks like visually
for our touring in Romania example.
We start off in Irat.
And the F value there was 366, so that's
the smallest control from which we start
that contains A node at all.
Then, A* will continue to grow this
contour.
Initially, as a small set, but then we
have a slightly bigger set, that for
example, has the value 400.
And as you can see this node here is
almost on the edge.
And if you go back to the tree you will
see it's F value is above 400, so it must
be outside the set.
And so on.
So, A* continues to grow this contour
until it includes the Bucharest node.
In this example, you can see nicely how
the ellipsis it draws stretch toward the
goal node.
But you can also see it the other way
around.
What this means is that A* must explore
all those nodes that are within a contour
that has a value just less than the cost
of the optimal path.
A* needs to include all those nodes that
are within this contour that almost leads
to the goal node.
And often, that is still quite a large
number.
So in this example, you see that most of
the contours contain different nodes.
But think about the eight puzzle for a
second, and what that looks like there.
In the eight puzzle the maximum goal
distance you have is 31 steps.
Yet, you have just over 180,000 nodes.
So there must be many nodes that have the
same F value.
Here is another property of A* namely A*
is optimally efficient.
What this means is, that no other,
optimal algorithm is guaranteed to expand
fewer nodes than A*.
This is of course true for a given
specific heuristic function.
What this gives us is that, any other
algorithm that guarantees us an optimal
solution must expand at least as many
nodes as A* for a given heuristic
function.
Of course, there can still be a more
efficient way of finding a solution to a
given problem namely if we have a
different, more efficient heuristic.
But for a fixed juristic, A* is optimally
efficient.
Notice that efficiency here is counted in
the number of nodes that are expanded,
but of course that's not the only thing
that makes an algorithm efficient.
For example, computing the juristic
function has a computational cost but it
does not count towards the number of
nodes that we expand.
So A* is only optimally efficient with
respect to number of nodes it expands.
To be more specific, it's not only the
number of nodes that any other algorithm
must expand.
It is exactly those nodes.
Suppose there is another algorithm that
is optimal, which means it returns an
optimal path.
But it does not expand one of the nodes
that is expanded by A*.
What does this mean?
A* expands all those nodes with an F
value that is less than C* where C* is
the value of the optimal power.
So, if another algorithm did not expand
one of these nodes.
That means, in the search space of the
algorithm, there's an unexplored node
that has an F value of less than C*.
So that means the most promising path
through that node that the algorithm
ignores, looks better than the optimal
path.
So if we don't explore that path, we can
never find out that it actually turns out
to be something worse in the end.
So in the end, A* expands a minimal
number of nodes that still guarantee an
optimal solution.