So the last topic for today is Lagrange's
method plus Newton's method.
So I want to revisit.
Okay, I guess I'll remind everybody what
Lagrange's method was.
So, it was a method for solving
constrained optimization problems.
And the way we approached it, well we had
to make this function called a
Lagrangian that had the, the objective
function, as
well as these Lagrange multipliers times
the constraints.
And then, I know that the extreme values
of the constrained
optimization problem are going to occur at
critical points of the Langragian.
So what I need to be able to do is take
the gradient of the
Lagrangian, set that eqaul to zero, and
solve that.
So that's exactly, well, sometimes, like
in the case of the minimum
variance portfolio, that was easy, because
that was just solving a linear system.
When the system is non-linear it can be
more difficult, so the maximum expected
return portfolio.
This ends up, because the constraints now
have this
quadratic form in it, it ends up being
more difficult.
I have to solve a non-linear function to
find the maximum expected return.
So I'm going to revisit the example from
the slides for Lagrange method.
So I was trying to find the minimum or the
maximum of 4x2 minus 2x3.
Subject to these two constraints.
[COUGH]
And so what I did is I wrote
down the Lagrangian so that's just the
objective function.
This is the, the function that I want to
find the maximum value of.
And then I add lambda one times the
first constraint and lambda two times the
second constraint.
And I want to think of this as a function
of five variables now.
So there's three that come from the x, and
two that come from
the lambda.
So, it's a function of five variables.
So, when I take the gradient of this
function Gm, then I get
that's a row vector with five entries and
I want to find the inputs.
So, that's x1, x2, x3, lambda 1 and lambda
So that this gradient vector is equal to
the zero vector.
And so when I try to solve this in the, in
the Lagrange, Langrange
method slides, I ended up coming up with
these five partial derivatives.
I set them equal to zero.
And then it wasn't exactly easy to solve
but you could do it, and I think we found
that, well we got lambda 1 for free
because of this equation, and then you
found that lambda 2 was plus or minus 1,
and then
that was enough to determine the values of
x1, x2, and x3.
So in that case at least it was possible
to solve it exactly.
[COUGH]
And the nice thing about having done that
already
is we also know that it has two critical
points.
So it turned out the non-linear equa, the
non-linear equation that I
need to solve, so I already know just from
looking at this.
The value of lambda 1.
So, I'm going to not bother solving for
that one.
So, that means I am solving just F of x
comma lambda 2
this time and sort of the a function of
four variables with four outputs.
And just by looking.
So, I have to take the the partial
derivatives of each entry here.
So, that will be four partial derivatives.
So, that's what's going to give me my
gradient matrix.
So, this has a partial derivative with
respect to x1 this is
the only term with an x1 in it, so that's
2 lambda.
So I put a two lambda here.
There's no x2, no x3, so both of these get
zero.
And
I'm going to take the derivative of this
term
with respect to lambda two, I get 2x1.
So I just continue that process for each
Each of these
four functions that are making up my
vector valued function capital F.
And that gives me the the gradient matrix.
And so if I want to use Newton's method
for
this, I'm going to need some R functions
for evaluating this.
So Here, instead of writing out x as x1,
x2, x3, and lambda 2,
I've just decided to call all four of
those things one vector-valued argument x.
And so, all I'm going to do is make
this function F, it's just going to return
a vector of
length four that has the four pieces in it
from
the previous lines, if you if you want to
compare
on your own time it's basically, I've just
rewritten this vector valued function
in R, and then I did the same thing for
the gradient matrix here.
So, here I have tried to keep that at
least a little bit so so it will be
human readable, so you can see this is 2
lambda 2, 0, 0, and then 2x1.
So that
was the first row of the gradient I had on
the previous slide and
so if I'm going to enter the values like
this, remember R wants to create matrices.
By putting things into columns, so it
fills up the
first column first, then the second column
then the third column.
So if I want to put things in by row, so
that I can have it equal to
what I'm writing out here, I have to put
this optional argument at the end by row
equals true.
So this ma, this function matrix is going
to take this vector of 16 values, turn
that
into a four by four matrix by filling
in the rows rather than filling in the
columns.
And so this is going to be a function DF,
given the four inputs, x1,
x2, x3, and lambda 2 just creates the the
gradient matrix
so then I need a starting point.
So, again, I have no particularly good
idea what the starting point should be.
So I just chose a vector of ones.
So I need a vector of length 4.
So this command just repeats.
It repeats the first argument the
second argument number of times, so this
is going to make a vector of length 4.
Where each element
is a one.
Then this time am going to do 15 newton
iterations.
And again now the newton iteration the
code for this is actually pretty simple.
Once you have the function for the
gradient
and for evaluating the function, this is
all
the the newton stuff is ever going to look
like so I just taking x, I'm subtracting
my update to x And I'm storing that again
in x.
And then if I repeat that, my x is going
to follow my sequence of Newton steps.
Hopefully closer to the value x star that
I'm looking for.
So, code for Newton iteration's very
simple.
And, what I've done here, so these were
the solutions that we came up with.
In the Lagrange method slides.
So there was lambda 1, that was fixed,
equal to negative 2.
And then we found that lambda 2 could be
either negative 1 or positive 1.
And then the rest of the solution's, just
the
sign of them was determined by the sign of
lambda.
So I'd get negative
2,3, negative 7.
And 2 negative 3 7, so it's the first 3
are just
multiplied by negative 1 to get the first
3 of the other solution.
And what this big R matrix is showing so,
it's
showing the values for x1 x2 x3 and lambda
2.
So some side I got the lambda 1 for free.
I didn't bother putting that in here, but
I could have it, just what have made
things a bit more complicated.
What each row is showing is the value
after that many iterations.
So remember I said my starting point was
going to be the vector 1, 1, 1, 1.
So after zero iterations, my x0 is 1, 1,
1, 1.
After one
iteration
I end up at 6.25, 1.25, 11.25 and negative
3.25.
And so what we're seeing is, each time I
do
an iteration it's changing what the values
of these things are.
And for the first few steps, nothing very
extreme happens.
And then all of a sudden in step 3 I went
from 1.62 to negative 247,
you know I went from 5 to 81 from about
negative 2 to negative
500 and something but then after that they
get better Until finally
after, so this is the reason why I chose,
there's nothing magical about
me choosing 15 or anything about this
problem that suggested me choosing 15.
I just happened to get exact convergence
to, you know,
within the numbers that the computer's
capable of displaying after 15
steps and also I couldn't fit anymore
lines on this slide.
[COUGH]
So from a starting point of 1, 1, 1, 1, I
ended up getting
to within the sort of numerical precision
that the computer is capable of of doing,
the solution that we found theoretically.
So, the solution corresponding to lambda 2
equal to negative 1.
And so this is something we have to be
aware of as there are two solutions.
I know there are two solutions.
But, Newton's methods, if it converges,
it's only
ever going to converge to one of those.
I can't run it a little bit longer and
hope that it then tells me what another
solution is.
>> Were different in initial values
[INAUDIBLE]?
>> Yeah.
Well, that might be on the next slide
[LAUGH].
>>
[LAUGH]
>> first though, I guess, I just made
some plots of.
So this is.
I couldn't figure out how to, how to put
the vector length.
Symbol over here.
So I just use absolute value.
But what I mean here is xk minus x star.
So since I have this theoretical result, I
knew what the real answer was.
So I just mean the length of the vector,
so the, how
far away I am from the point that I'm
trying to estimate.
And you see at the beginning I with my
initial
guess of 1, 1, 1, 1 didn't do too bad.
And, then all of a sudden it bumps way up
to here, but then, it takes me pretty
quickly back down.
And, so after about 10, you know, I can't
see anything on this scale anymore.
So, I plotted this.
On the log scale.
So that's exactly the same plot except now
instead
of putting the, the actual scale I'm just
putting the
log of the number that was on the y axis.
And so again you see in the first few
steps nothing very exciting happened, then
it got much worse.
And then on the log scale it sort of has
this linear bit.
And then it really starts to drop off
after that and so somewhere around here is
one
this quadratic convergence that I was
talking about, that's
where that kicks in, and you can see for,
you know, for this step and this step.
You can think of the scale here is roughly
the number of significant digits.
So when I go, ops, when I go from this
step to this
step, I'm getting an increase of about
it's going to be about one significant
digit.
Here I'm going to get an increase of one
significant digit.
And then after the next step after that, I
get an increase of maybe two or three
significant digits.
And if I were to keep going, You know,
that's just getting better and better.
So, some observations about this.
So, from a given starting point, Newton's
method converges, you
know, if it converges, to a single value x
star.
So, in this case, there are actually two
values
that it could converge to, if it were
working.
And it, just because of this initial
condition that
I gave it, it converged to one of them.
And so, starting at the point 1, 1, 1, 1,
I got this answer.
So, here I've just dropped out the value
of lambda 1.
But I know there's two critical points.
And so I'm just going to kind of guess
that if
I start from all 1s and this ends up being
a negative 1, maybe if I multiply this
starting vector
by negative 1, that's just going to flip
everything around and
this will be a positive 1.
So let's try doing that.
So I just put a, a negative sign here.
And so that's going to make my initial
vector a
vector of minus 1s, instead of a vector of
1s.
The code for doing the Newton iterations
stays exactly the same.
And so this is the solution I'm hoping to
get.
Oh no, sorry.
That's the solution I actually get after
this, which is,
this solution divided by negative 1, which
is what I was expecting to get.
So yeah, if you try different solutions,
but the problem is
in general, we're not going to know the
number of critical points.
So it, in this case, I knew that I got one
of them.
And I knew what the other one was.
So that gave me some idea.
So for instance, using negative 1, that
might lead me to that other critical
point.
in general,
that's not going to be the case.
So usually what you
can do is you can get some additional
information about the problem.
So you can study the problem a bit more.
I, if you read the Lagrange chapter in
textbook, he talks about how to classify a
critical point as a minimum or a maximum,
so you might know that your solution has
or that
the problem you're trying to solve only
has two critical points.
So this is the case in a maximum expected
return portfolio.
You actually get two answers, a maximum
expected return and a minimum expected
return.
And so, if you can classify the point that
you found
as a maximum, then you know that you've
found what you want.
So sometimes, that allows you to use this
to,
to get an answer to the problem that you
want.
And if you can't do that, the very best
you
can do is just try to use multiple
starting points.
So Really, what you would do here is use
some sort of random number generator to
just choose problems.
you want to be a little bit smart about
it.
So, you want to choose things that are on
the same scale.
I guess another thing I should point out
here is the starting value that I chose.
And that might go a long way to explaining
why we get this huge jump here.
The starting point that I chose doesn't
actually satisfy the constraints
of the, of the, Lagrange method problem
that I'm trying to solve.
So, I think what sort of happened here is
it kind of meandered around, until
it managed to get into the space
of points, where the constraints were
actually satisfied.
And then that's when we go this much nicer
looking behavior.
It's a converging towards
towards the value that I wanted.
So unfortunately if you, if you don't know
anything else about your problem
that's a about the best you can do is just
try starting points randomly.
Hopefully they'll converge to more than
one solution.
And then you can look at the value at that
solution and decide
if you've got you know, at least a local
minimum or a local maximum.