In the next few slides, I will give you
an overview of the plan-space planning
algorithm, PSP.
This will be a generic version of the
algorithm and I'll follow this with some
implementation detail that will make
things more specific.
So, here's a quick recap of the search
problem as we've defined it so far.
We have given the statement of a planning
problem, consisting of a set of
operators, an initial state, and a goal
condition.
Then, we need to define a search problem
which consists of an initial state, and
our initial state was the empty plan,
which isn't quite empty.
It consists of the init action and the
goal action.
These were the two dummy actions we've
introduced to encode our initial state
and the goal condition into the plan.
And then, we have one ordering
constraint, namely that the init dummy
action must come before the goal dummy
action.
And we have no variable bindings and no
causal links initially.
The goal test, as we have just seen, is
simply to check whether a plan has flaws.
If it has no flaws, then our plan is a
solution state.
What I haven't mentioned so far is the
path cost function.
That's simply because the path cost
function is not very relevant here.
You can choose pretty much anything you
like.
For example, the length of the plan as
usual.
Note that this path cost function would
not be related to the cost of the plan
refinement operations,
but to the cost of the plan that we're
searching for.
And the final component of our search
problem is the successor function.
And here, we will consider all those
refinements of our current plan that
maintain the ordering and the binding
constraints in a consistent fashion.
So, our successor function will allow the
application of more than one plan
refinement operation at a time.
And here is an informal overview of the
basic operations that we need to perform
during our plan-space search.
The basic idea, the main principle behind
the algorithm is that we always refine
our partial plan while maintaining the
order and binding constraint, in a
consistent fashion, until the plan has no
more flaws.
In some sense, this is the main loop of
our algorithm.
Then, within this main loop, what we have
to do is first, find the flaws that are
currently in our plan.
So, these flaws can be either sub-goals
or threats.
We need to identify them, so that we can
remove them from the plan.
And we will deal with these flaws one at
a time.
So, the next step is to select one of
those flaws.
Once we've selected a flaw, we need to
find all those ways in which the flaw can
be removed from our plan and which it can
be resolved.
And again, we need to choose one of the
resolvers for the selected flaw.
And finally, we refine our plan according
to the chosen resolver.
So we've selected a flaw, we've chosen a
way to get rid of this flaw, and now we
apply this to our partial plan.
This is the step that corresponds to a
state transition in our search space.
And, of course, while we are refining our
plan with our chosen resolver, we've got
to make sure that we maintain our
ordering and binding constraints so these
two are connected.
And we need to make sure that our
constraints are consistent.
If our constraints are no longer
consistent after we've applied a
resolver, then this node is a dead-end in
our search space.
And here is what I've just told you in
pseudo code.
We define the function PSP that takes a
partial plan as input.
The procedure then refines this plan into
a solution plan.
Note that there is no planning problem
given as input.
That is because, initially the plan that
is given to this procedure is the empty
plan which encodes the planning problem
as it has the dummy steps in it and goal
having the initial state and the goal.
Then, the first thing we do is we compute
all the flaws that are currently in the
plan, and there are two types of flaws of
course, namely the openGoals, the
preconditions that are currently
unsatisfied, and the threats that exist
within the current plan.
And if the set of flaws is empty that
means we have reached a solution plan
because as you told you before, no flaws
means a solution.
But if there were flaws left in the plan,
then we can now choose a flaw which is
the flaw we want to remove from the plan
next.
And once we have selected one of the
flaws, we can compute all possible
resolvers for this flaw in the current
plan.
If the set of resolvers is empty, that
means there is no way to remove this flaw
from the plan, and that means we can
return failure because this partial plan
can never be refined into a solution
plan.
But if there were resolvers in the set,
then we have to choose one to remove the
flaw from our plan.
The next step then is to generate a new
plan, which consists of applying the
resolver to our current plan.
This is the step that generates a new
search node in our search space.
And this time, I haven't defined the
search procedure as an iterative
procedure but as a recursive procedure
where the recursive call comes here.
So, we've generated a new node and we've
simply applied the PSP procedure to that
new node.
Now, there are a few things to say about
this algorithm.
Firstly, it contains a number of
functions that I still have to define.
For example, how to compute the open
goals in a plan,
or how to find the threats that exist in
a given plan.
Also, I need to be able to compute the
resolvers that are available for a given
flaw in the plan,
and I need to define how I can apply
these resolvers to a current plan.
These are implementation details that I
will look at, in the next section.
But before I get here, there are two more
functions that look quite trivial but are
actually different.
As you can see, I've chosen different
names for this.
Firstly, we need to select a flaw. And
secondly, we need choose a resolver.
And there's a good reason why I've chosen
two different words for these two
different functions.
The two functions, chooseOne and
selectOne, represent choice points in our
algorithm.
Let me first describe the choice point
where we select a resolver.
So, we have a function called
Resolvers.chooseOne that selects one of
the resolvers for the chosen flaw.
This is a non-deterministic choice point.
So, the way the algorithm is described,
is as a non-deterministic algorithm which
means we need to turn this into a
deterministic algorithm for the
implementation. And this choice point is
one that we need to backtrack over.
That means, it's a non-deterministic
choice point.
We need to come back here if we fail in
one branch and try a different branch in
our search.
The other choice point where we select
one of the flaws, that we try to resolve
next, is a deterministic selection.
That means, we don't need to backtrack
over this choice.
That means, we can choose one of the
available options and then don't need to
explore the other options at this point.
And the reason for this is very simple.
If a plan contains multiple flaws, we
need to resolve all these flaws before it
becomes a solution plan. But the order in
which we do this is not important.
Since flaws really dont interfere with
each other, we can deal with one flaw
after an other and whichever flaw we
choose first does not prevent another
flaw from being resolved.
So, the order in which we choose the
flaws is not important, at least not for
completeness.
Our algorithm will still work in
whichever order we choose the flaws.
But, of course, the order is very
important for the efficiency of our
planning algorithm. For example, consider
a plan that has one flaw for which we
have no resolver and several flaws for
which we have resolvers.
If we first choose those flaws that we
can resolve and then deal with the flaw
that has no resolvers lost, we create a
search tree that has no solution node, of
course. Whereas, if we first choose the
one that has no resolvers, we immediately
terminate our search.
So, important.
Flaw selection is a deterministic
selection and we don't need to backtrack
over the selection in our implementation.
Selecting a resolver is a
non-deterministic choice and we need to
implement this as a backtrack point.