This, last section, so the last for
today is the R Environment for Statistical
Computing.
So this isn't going to be so much of how
to do stuff.
It's basically I just want you to try
doing some of these things with a computer
ones because that's really the only way
that this is going to be practical.
so what is R?
This is sort of the programming language
that's been adapted by the CFNRM
department.
So R is a language and environment for
statistical computing and graphics.
Luckily, statistical computing ends up
being very, very similar to
scientific computing, so, that's mostly
just solving things with matrices.
So
R offers, and this is not an exhaustive
list data handling and storage, a
suite of operators for calculations on a
raise and in particular matrices.
So this is the bullet point that we will
be making the most use of.
It's also, a complete programming
language.
So, there are some questions you can solve
just by, or some problems
you're going to be able to solve just by
using, Matrices and
vectors, but if you need to do something
more general or if
you want to verify that you've gotten the
correct solution, you can
actually write something just like it was
C or any other programming language.
And also a good thing for us is that it's
free
software, so if you just click on this
link, so it's www.r-project.org.
you can download a copy on the University
network.
It should take you about a minute between
clicking
this link and having it installed on your
computer.
And so when you load up R it's going to
look something like this.
So this is a picture for Windows on a
Macintosh
or on Linux, it's going to look a bit
different.
But, the important thing is there will
always be
this one window in the front called the R
console.
And, this little prompt here, I call it a
Carrot.
I don't know if that symbol actually has a
name.
It's just, sort of, R's way of telling you
it's
ready to do something, and you need to
type a command in.
So, you type in a command, and you
press Return, and it's going to do
something for you.
And, I guess I should apologize for those
of you taking 461.
This'll seem a bit redundant.
[COUGH]
So, you can think of R as a calculator.
And so the commands are going to look like
what,
in my slides, the commands are going to
look like this.
So this is the little carrot that you're
going to see in the R command window.
And then, this, oops.
This is the input that you're going to
type in.
And then when you hit Enter, oops.
This isn't actually running R, so I have
to hit Down Arrow.
the output will look like this.
This is just sort of placeholder to tell
you that
this is the first element of a vector, so
the
answer is not the thing in the square
brackets, the
answer is the thing that comes after the
square brackets.
And so when you do this in R, it's just
going to look like this.
You see the prompt.
You type in 1 plus 1.
You hit Return, and it types out 2.
So, hopefully, that's pretty clear.
That's the answer I expected anyways.
One sort of useful thing to know right
from the very beginning is
if you need help with a function, you can
use a function called help.
So I type the name of a function, open
parenthesis.
The thing inside the parenthesis is called
the Argument.
And the Argument to the help function is
just
the name of a function that I want help
with.
So in this case there's a function called
little c, and
I want to see the help file for this
little c.
Then there's also this gate sign or pound
symbol or number symbol.
It's just got a lot of names.
and this is what you use in R to comment
your code.
So, this is one line that I could type
into the R command prompt.
The R is going to see this symbol and
it's just going to ignore everything that
comes after it.
So, I could say, I can leave myself
messages
and you won't do this so often in the
console.
But, if you're making a script file that
you're going to cut and paste in the
console,
you might want to leave yourself messages
for
what each line of that script is doing.
And so here my message is saying that
question mark c is going to do
the same thing as just saying help and
then giving it the argument c.
So I can do help c and that'll give me the
help page for
the c function, or I can do question mark
c and that'll give me the same thing.
So the first thing we're going to want to
be able to do is make vectors.
So, this little c function that I was
talking about,
this takes values and puts them together
into a vector.
So this is going to put the values 34, 12,
65, 24 and 15 into a vector in this order.
And so the output of that just looks looks
like this.
So again, I get this 1 in square brackets.
All that's telling
me is that this 34, the thing right next
to it, is the first element of this
vector.
I can also use this colon to get sequences
of, of values,
that differ by 1.
So, generally, the only way this makes
sense is if I say an integer value colon
another integer value.
So if I do negative 3 colon 7, that's just
going to be, give me
negative 3, negative 2, negative 1, and so
on up to 7.
If you want a little bit more control,
there's a function
called seq which stands for sequence, and
so I can give it
multiple arguments to find out what all
the possible arguments are
you have to look at the help file for the
function seq.
So here what I'm telling it I want it to
start at 0 I want
it to go to 1 and I want it to take steps
of size 0.05.
So when I run this, it prints something
like this out.
So the first one is 0.
Then in steps of 0.05, it goes up to the
number 1.
And so now you can see, it's a little bit
more clear what this one is here for.
So, it's telling me that 0.00 is the first
element of this vector.
You know, then I have, two,
three, four, five, six, seven, eight,
nine, and
then 0.45 is the 10th element of this
vector.
So, its just the little aid so you can
kind of figure out about where you
are in a vector when it has to
be split across multiple multiple lines in
the output.
>> You
[UNKNOWN],
assuming a row vector, or?
>> So, a vector doesn't really have row
or column by itself.
It's only when you start to talk about
matrices
that it has a, a row and column format.
And so, R actually, I think, most of the
time, I, If I have a vector, and I need
to put it into something with two indices,
so I
need to put it into a equation with a
matrix.
I think of every vector as a column
vector, and if I want
it to be a row, I put a little t next to
it.
And I'll talk about that in, in, next
time.
here are actually, well, I'll get to an
example
that'll hopefully be a little bit more
clear about that.
So then another useful thing you can do in
R is you
can save the result from one computation
to use in another one.
So, here I'm going to make
a vector that has elements 24, 30, 41, 16,
and 8.
And then I'm going to store that in a
variable called x.
And so when I do this now there's no
output.
Because instead of taking that output and
printing it on the screen
R is just going to put that output into
the variable x instead.
So if I want to see what x is, I can now
just
type x at the command line and hit Enter,
and now this prints
out what's stored in this variable x, so
it's the vector that I
created in the first command here, so 24,
30, 41, 16, and 8.
And, once I've created a vector, then I
can manipulate it.
So, this is my, my vector that I created
on the previous slide.
And I called x.
And I use square brackets to get at the
individual elements of x.
So here x[3] is going to refer to the
third element of x.
So if I run this on the command line, I
just end up getting a 41.
Everything in R is treated as a vector,
so, this 3, even though you think it looks
like a scalar, you know, internally R is
treating that as a vector of length 1.
So I can also subset on vectors, and
that's going to probably have the
predictable result.
So if I give a vector of indices, this is
going to refer to the first, second, and
fourth elements of the vector X, so that's
going to be 24, 30, and 16.
And so when I do that on the command line
I get 24, 30, 16.
So I can get a subset of the elements out
by putting,
giving a vector argument to this, to these
square brackets.
And then I can also use this subsetting
for assignment.
So suppose I have my vector x and I
want to
replace the first, second and fourth
elements with negative 1.
Well, this was a, a subset that took those
elements out.
So, it somehow refers to those places in
the vector.
I can use my assignment operator, this
little
arrow symbol.
To put a negative 1 into those places in
x.
So if I, if I have x currently as holding
this, when I run this command it's
going to replace those entries.
So the first second and fourth entries
with a negative 1.
And so now when I look at my value x
I end up with negative, negative, negative
1, negative 1, 41,
negative 1 8.
So the, the first, second and fourth
entries have been replaced by a negative
1.
[COUGH]
I can do Vector Arithmetic.
So, remember when I talked about adding
two vectors, they were added element vise.
So, I just sort of made up a new vector x.
My vector y is just integer values from 1
to 8, so x has length 8.
So I can use x plus y to add those
together.
And so this just ends up being 1 plus 6 is
7,
2 plus 12 is 14, 3 plus 4 is 7, and so on.
And, plus, minus, multiply, and divide are
all implemented this way in R.
So it just happened element wise.
And the vectors have to be equal length.
And a lot of other functions in R also
work that way.
So for instance the logarithm.
It says log, log is log with base e not
base 10 so R, R treats this as a natural
logarithm.
and that's just going to return, so this
first element is the natural logarithm of
six.
Second element of the logarithm of 12 and
so on.
And then I can also scale and shift a
vector.
So if I have a vector of length one, or
I'm going to think of it as a scalar,
and I use a star, so multiplication, this
is
going to be interpreted as 2 times each
element of x.
And then when I subtract a vector of
length
1, that's going to be the same as
subtracting a scalar.
So I think of this as 2 times each element
of x, and then each of those
elements minus 3, so if I run this command
I'm going to get 9, and that's just
2 times 6 minus 3.
21 is 2 times 12 minus 3, and so on.
And now that's, that's sort of my brief
introduction of vectors.
And then I can create matrices using a, a
function called matrix.
So I'll first start by making a vector x
that just has numbers 1 through 16 in it.
And then I'm going to use the matrix
function to
turn that vector x into a 4 by 4 matrix.
So the first number here is the number of
rows, the second number is the number of
columns.
Oops,
[COUGH]
and that's just going to give me a matrix
that looks like this.
So it's 4 by 4 and it's put the vector
into the column.
So, let's put the first four elements in
the first column, the second four
elements in the second column, third four
in third and fourth four in fourth.
If want to instead go by row, you can give
the matrix function this optional
by row equals TRUE argument.
And now instead of filling this in column
by column,
it's going to fill it in row by row, so I
get one, two, three, four in the first
row, five,
six, seven, eight in the second row, and
so on.
So, for manipulating matrices, suppose I
have a 3 by 3 matrix,
so I'm kind of combining more and more
commands into one line here.
So here, I'm creating a vector that has
numbers 1 through 9 in it, and
then I'm using the matrix function to turn
that into a 3 by 3 matrix.
So, I get 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.
To get out the individual elements, I can
use square
brackets now.
.
But, because I have a matrix it's got a
number of rows and
a number of columns I have to use two
arguments with my square brackets.
And so if I say A 2, 3 that's going to be
second row,
third column, and so I get an 8, and
that's what I see here.
[COUGH]
You can also select multiple rows and
multiple columns by giving vector
arguments here.
So this will take the first two rows of A
and the second two columns of A.
And so we end up with, so remember the
first row oops.
First 2 row, or first column was 1, 2, 3,
but
I haven't selected that so that, oops,
that dropped off over here.
Then the second column was 4, 5, 6 and the
third column was 7, 8, 9.
But I've only asked for the first two rows
here so I get 4, 5 and 7, 8.
And then I can also leave an argument
empty to mean I want everything.
So instead of being forced you know, if I
wanted all 3 columns here, instead of
being forced
to write 1 colon 3.
I can just write comma and leave that
space blank and R is
going to interpret that as select the
first two rows and all of the columns.
So I end up with the first two rows of my
matrix A.
Then I can also use the t function to take
the transpose of a matrix.
This is something I'll actually, I'll talk
about on Wednesday.
But if such, this is just I made the
transpose of a
matrix is just a matrix whose rows are the
columns of the argument.
So the rows of A transpose are just going
to be the columns of A.
And so that takes the first column of a,
which was 1,
2, 3, and makes that the first row of a
transpose and so on.
So I have to start this section out with a
warning.
So R always considers a single star to be
component-wise multiplication.
So suppose x and y are vectors of n
components.
So here, I chose n equals 4.
And I say x is 4, 3, 2, 1, and y is 1, 2,
3, 4.
And, you might think, because x and y are
vectors, that if
I multiplied them together, what I'd be
getting is the dot product.
But actually, what I get is just the
element wise product.
So this is 4 times 1, 2 times 3, 3 times
2,
and 4, 1 times 4.
So I think I might have screwed that up,
but you get the idea, I hope.
[COUGH]
Yeah.
[LAUGH]
so for the dot product you have to use
this symbol here.
So, it's percent star percent.
And that means to do multiplication using
sort
of the multiplication rule appropriate for
the type.
And so since x is a vector and y is
a vector, this will be interpreted as x
dot y.
And so if I do that, I end up getting
twenty.
And the dot product will actually
have just been the sum of these elements
here.
So if you look at that, 4 and 6 and 6 and
4 are both 10 and 10 and 10 are 20.
And you can do a little sanity check to
use the sum function to
sum those up for you, and that also is
going to give me 20.
So now we can think about Matrix-Vector
and Matrix-Matrix Multiplication,
so I've sort of theoretically have a, a
vector of n components.
And let's let A be an n by n matrix, and B
an n by p matrix,
and so I'm choosing a different letter
here because
I want it to actually be a different
number.
So the operation x percent star percent A,
this is going to treat
X as a row vector, so this is sort of your
question, Bill.
so it recognizes that if I want to
pre-multiply by A because of my
multiplication rules,
whatever is over here has to have the same
number of columns as A has rows.
So if this is a vector, if x is a
vector, it's going to make that into
something with several columns.
And then if that has the right size,
it will then go ahead and do this
multiplication.
And then, if I put x on the right side,
now x has to
be a column vector, so R is going to treat
this as a column vector.
And it is possible, with the matrix
function, if you
tell it to create a matrix with one row or
one column, you can force x to be a row
vector or a column vector.
And in that case, if x were forced to be a
row, sorry, forced
to be a column vector, so it's actually a
matrix with just one column.
Then, when I do this, it's not going to
work.
The operation A percent star percent B,
that's
just going to give me the matrix product
AB.
And that'll work because the number of
columns of
A is equal to the number of rows of B.
On the other hand, if I try to do B times
A, so B matrix product A.
That's going to give an error, because the
dimensions of A and B, of B and A are not
conformable for multiplication, so I can't
do B times A, because p is not equal to n.
And then one last thing.
So recall, I had this system, so this is
the system from the first quiz.
And we found that the answer was, sorry
not the first quiz, it's from the first
set of slides today, we found the
answer was minus 1, 2, 2, and I had solved
that by elimination.
And so we can also do this in R just using
the solve function.
So this is actually a very common problem
that you want to be able
to solve, so there's a function built in
that's going to do this for you.
So I can first make my coefficient matrix
A, and I did it here just by typing it in.
Then I make a vector b that just has 2, 8,
10 in it.
And then I just call the solve function,
the syntax is the coefficient matrix and
then the right-hand side
vector, and that just prints out the
answer, minus 1, 2, 2.