Hello, and welcome to the AI Game Dev
labs.
My name is Alex Champandard.
And today we're going to talk about
planning in games and in particular more
of the lessons we've learned applying
planning into games over the past few
years.
And the opportunities that lie ahead in
using more advanced AI techniques.
And then some of the games that we've
actually applied planning to.
So, if you're anything like me, you're
super excited about the idea of applying
modern AI techniques into games.
And plannings is when it's particularly
interesting.
we've been doing this for about eight to
ten years now.
So, we've got quite a lot of experience
from applying planning in games.
I'm going to talk about some of those
games.
So, here's a, a non exhaustive list of
games that use planning or techniques
related to planning.
And I'm going to dig into them.
So, I've been lucky enough to, to work on
a couple of games that use planning.
And I've also interviewed developers
that, built planning into many other
games.
So, I thought it would be interesting to
dig into some of the insights that
they've shared.
And some of the lessons we've learned as,
as the games industry when it comes to
applying planning into those types of
situations.
So first let's look at games that use
planners.
And they can be split roughly off into
two categories, STRIPS style planning,
and HTN style planning.
And, STRIPS, you can think of it as a
very non-hierarchical searching through
actions that generate new states.
And then figuring out how to get from one
state to another via a set of actions.
HTN is more hierarchical, and it tries to
search through actions that break down
recursively using tastic composition.
And so, with STRIPS based approach, you
need to, to have a good idea of the
problem.
And to have an efficient implementation
as well, because it requires a start to
search through all the different options.
And the first game that really nailed
that down was Fear.
And that's based on the work of Jeff
Orkin at Monolith, who applied STRIPS
based planner into, into Fear.
And he did a lot of work to make this run
fast enough and combined with the
particular type of game that this was
with action oriented game.
Where you only really needed short action
sequences for the characters in the game.
And this, this turned out to be feasible
in 2005.
And this particular game spawned a whole
bunch of sequels and expansion packs.
And derivatives of this kind of
technology were used in, in all of those
games.
And you can actually find original
implementation in the STK of the original
Fear, so you can download that and find
the planner.
It's actually there and you can read the
whole code for it, so I highly encourage
you to do that.
You may need a copy of the original game,
but it's worth it.
So, that particular implementation was
well documented by Jeff Orkin and it
spawned a bunch of other games that were
inspired by.
And two of those were internal to
Monolith, Condemned and Condemned 2,
which I also believe used similar or the
same code base, STRIPS base also.
Then there's a couple other titles
including the Stalker games that were
also using planning and Stalker uses
hierarchies of STRIPS planners to drive
character behavior.
So, where as the behavior is potentially
complexive of the agents in Stalker or
the Stalkers as they're called.
they breakdown this complex, long term
behavior into a hierarchy of STRIPS style
planners.
Just Cause is also a similar kind of
open-world environment, that also uses a
STRIPS style planner.
And the civilians as well as the enemies
use that planner for for dealing with
unexpected situations and the emergent
behaviors that you get out of the
planner.
more planning helps deal with those
particular types of situations.
So, there's game shipped in 2007, 2008,
2010, War for Fall of Cybertron, the
Transformers game, also used STRIPS style
planner.
Which required lots of specific
optimizations and graph-based
optimization of STRIPS planners.
And Deus Ex, the most recent addition of
that franchise, in 2011, apparently used
a planner as well.
So these are, this is a list of games, a
non-exhaustive list of games that uses
STRIPS.
And, there are some other games that use
STRIPS, but these are the primary ones
that try to, to capture all the the key
franchises, the triple a games that use
planners.
There are a few independent games that
also use planners, and strip style as
well.
But the other major category is
hierarchical task network.
I'm going to talk about those now.
And those are inspired by particulary the
work of Gorilla Games on Kill Zone 2 and
I was lucky enough to work on the
multiplayer box for Kill Zone 2.
And initially when Gorilla did research
into hierarchical test networks, they
studied STRIPS that was available based
on the insights from Jeff Orkin.
And they thought that they needed a bit
more designer control over their
behaviors.
So, they built a more hierarchical
planner which helps the designers
essentially craft a specific tree of
behaviors, that can also be searched by a
planner.
And so, it seemed to them to combine the
best benefits of designer control with
planning.
And it turned out to be extremely
successful.
And the bots in the game are when was
reviewed by the, the journalists that
that reviewed Kill Zone initially.
And they often were surprised that the
bots were actually bots and they were not
online, so they were often fooled by the,
by the AI in the game.
So, obviously Kill Zone's AI was extended
and reused in Kill Zone 3, and
Transformers War for Cybertron borrowed
that approach as well.
And also implemented a hierarchical task
network style of AI.
so, initially, all these implementations
were derived from SHOP, that stands for
simple hierarchical orbit planner.
It has lots of advantages.
It's a simple algorithm, but adds some
purpose.
And the advantages that it has are
effectively because of design.
And it allows designers to express nice
hierarchies, ordered hierarchies.
They're plans that you can understand
exactly how those will get chosen in the
game.
So, you have full control over specific
type of behavior which makes them
particularly well suited for creating
character alley.
Kill Zone too, uses subset of SHOP.
It does not track exactly the, the side
effects of each action as they're applied
to the current world state as it searches
forwards through the set of action rules.
It searches forwards in time.
Whereas Transformers does that.
So, it tracks the side effects of each
action.
Kill Zone 2 on the other hand uses the
prepositional logic of SHOP that
Transformers doesn't.
So, or, we found different games that use
different subsets of the SHOP algorithm
and those proven to be useful in
different practices.
But we haven't fully seen a full
implementation of SHOP applied to games
yet.
But we've found hierarchical planners to
be extremely useful, generally speaking.
So there, those are the, the games use
HTN's officially and are well documented.
And there are a couple other games that
use hierarchical test networks
unofficially which I have discovered
based on my personal research.
And gossip and so I'm guessing here I
believe Max Payne 3 uses hierarchical
test network.
Planner, based on the work of Peter
Gornak, as well as Demon Souls and Dark
Souls as well.
Max Payne, I think uses some HTN concepts
within it's squads.
So, that was a presentation at GDC 2009,
but it's not it's not official.
[SOUND] And when the Total War series,
when Empire came out, there were some
rumors that it also used a planner.
And we invited Creative Assembly to a
gaming conference to give a presentation
about the AI.
And it turns out it's more of a
hierarchical approach and not a strict
style implementation.
And and it also turns out, it's a little
bit more reactive.
It doesn't fully search everything a, a
ahead like a, a fully featured HTN
planner.
but this is important to emphasize.
it draws the line between planners and
the more reactive techniques that are
used in industry like behavior trees.
And it's hard to often find the, the, the
gap between the two, or where do you draw
the line between a planner and not a
planner?
And there are certain things that are
called reactive planners, in academia.
And, the game developers have embraced
these types of technique.
And, these techniques, you search, but
not searching ahead and I'm going to talk
about those now.
And so, a behavior tree, for instance,
will look exactly like an HTN, except it
does not search ahead in time, it stops
at the current action and says, this is
likely to work out, I'm going to try it
out.
So, behavior trees have been extremely
popular in games and in particular since
Halo 2.
there was a presentation gave that Damian
Gessler gave at GDC about the behavior
trees in Halo 2.
And there were a couple of other titles
at the time, but also gravitated around
similar ideas, and Swap Four was one of
them, and Facade was another.
And this is inspired from, from a lot of
work done in robotics or the virtual
agents community.
And things have kind of crystallized
since then, and there have literally been
hundreds of title based on behavior trees
and many, many different games.
But I'm going to talk about,
specifically, some titles that have
relations to, to planning or the, the, to
somehow bridge the gap between the two.
And Metro 2033 was a stealth-action game
that and the developers had some
experiences of playing, planning from the
Stalker games.
And they initially used a planner but
then they switched to using more
behavior-tree style AI not very
hierarchical, a quite flat tree.
And, and that turned out to be better for
them to get more control over the
behaviors and and the game has a lot of
similar functionality than, than the Fear
franchise, for instance.
And it, it plays a lot in the same way.
So, it shows that similar behaviors can
be implemented with different techniques.
And that some of the strips the original
strips planning techniques didn't
necessarily create different behavior.
It just demanded developers to create
that behavior in a different way.
another studio that's worth mentioning is
Avalanche Studios, who built the strips
planner in Just Cause II.
now at the latest gaming [UNKNOWN]
conference we had the panel discussion
about this and Avalanche has actually got
it's own internal behavior tree
implementation now as well.
So it had a planner available, but it
decided to use behavior trees for certain
projects despite having the planning
technology available.
For many reasons that we've talked about
including designer control.
And it seems well it may seem obvious but
it's become obvious to the game developer
industry now that certain techniques are
better suited to different types of
games.
And in the more action combat oriented
games, you can get away with such
reactive techniques like behavior trees.
So, we've talked about a lot of
stealth-based games, and a lot of more
interesting, open-world games like Just
Cause 2.
And planners, more justifiable in large,
complex, open-world type games.
And in the the more linear scripted type
games, obviously, you need less of a
planner in such a closed-off environment
where there are fewer choices available
to the AI.
so behavior trees remains a very, very
popular option in industry, another set
of techniques that are used in games are
utilities systems.
And utility systems tend to be used in
very specific systems of games, like
weapon selection or selecting enemies or
in the action combat games.
That are very used for these particular
decisions.
You can think of a utility system as a,
kind of like a spreadsheet.
Of all these different options that I
have, which one should I pick, which
target should I pick, which weapon should
I pick, which smart object should I
interact with?
and what's interesting about utility
systems is that there is there is a gap
between or there's a bridge between them
and planning systems.
And Demigod is one of those titles that
bridges the gap between a utility system
and, and planners.
so Demigod is a multi-player online
battle arena, a MOBA for short.
And it has many challenges for the AI in
particular.
And it uses planning style algorithms.
As we'll combine with utility.
So, instead of searching for a specific
goal based on Boolean criteria, where
each action has strict dependencies that
need to be satisfied.
Demigod uses search, at that two depth
three of a set of actions.
And it tries to calculate a score for
what it's done,
And so it then, figures out if a specific
combination of actions have a higher
score or a lower score.
Not necessarily looking to satisfy a
Boolean goal, but using search to
maximize a specific utility.
So, the application here is significantly
different, but it's still using search to
automatically find sequences of actions
that are sensible for the AI.
So that's why, it's got many aspects of
planning but it's also got many aspects
of utility as well.
and I think that's a very promising area
that is very under explored, and
certainly very suited to these
multi-player online battle arenas.
And I presume we'll be seeing more of
those types of AIs being built, as mobile
games become more, more popular.
Another style or another type of game
that I'd like to talk about is the the
multi-player box implemented in, for
example, section 8 prejudice, or section
8.
Now, this is worth mentioning, because
Timegate had experience working on the
expansion packs for the original Fear.
And they built the AI, or they work with
the planner and the AI and the planner in
the STRIPS style.
But for their own game, Section 8
prejudice they chose to build a utility
system for the bots instead.
So, this is another action combat game
where the bots have to make fast
decisions, and they found that utility
worked perfectly well for this particular
purpose.
And they did not need to implement the
planning system.
despite having the experience with that
and this emphasizes again the, the fast
pace action games.
And not necessarily the best type of
games to implement planning in.
over planning does have its advantages as
well.
Which we'll talk about shortly.
And the third game, that I'd like to talk
about that's utility-based is the, the
Sims, and the Sims 3 in particular.
Now, earlier in the franchise, the Sims
1, the Sims 2, were almost entirely based
on utility.
but the Sims 3 took that a bit further,
and the characters were more purposeful.
They could interact with each other, and
within a neighborhood, and there was not
just a single single household that was
simulated at a time.
And to make this work, to pull this off,
with sufficient performance, Richard
Evans had to build conceptually a
hierarchical planner into the system
To partly isolate the utility system into
sub-decisions, so that the whole thing
was not utility-based, but it was more
like driven by the planner.
And then using utility at the base.
So, in a sense, utility was relegated or,
or, isolated a little more and more
responsibility was proportionately given
to the hierarchical planner to really
pull this off.
And the Sims 3 is a very interesting case
study, and looking forward, I hope to see
more games with purposeful characters,
like those in the Sims 3.
And it certainly shows that there's a lot
of potential in combining hierarchical
planners with other techniques, like
utility to get really great behaviors.
So, what have we learned from all this,
and we've basically been applying
planners in games since since Fear,
that's the first documented use of
planning in games.
And it's been almost eight years since
then.
So, in that time, we've, we've learned
quite a lot about planning in video games
certainly not as much as in robotics,
they've been doing it for, for decades.
But we still have, a lot of insights.
So, one thing we've found as far as games
are concerned, technology is really
rarely the problem.
Now, initially to get the STRIPS style
planner, interfere, Jeff Orkin had to do
a lot of work to, to get that running
fast enough.
And he has a paper on the subject,
entitled, how to plan in real-time and
keep your job.
So, it certainly was a performance
problem initially, a lot of developers
have benefited from his insight since
then.
And kind of optimization work is becoming
less important now that we have more
processing power to throw at the problem.
And so, it's fair to say that these
technical issues are secondary now to
design issues, and that's my second point
here.
That a lot of the questions that game
developers are raising about planning,
it's hard to combine automated planning
with designer control.
And that's a big open question about game
AI in general, how do you combine those
two things?
And it turns out that hierarchical
planning is our, currently our most
promising direction that we're heading
down.
Hierarchy allows you to edit specifically
what types of decisions you'd like to
constrain, and if you want to, very
constrained decisions, you'll be able to
very narrow tree It goes more deeply.
But if you want to give the, planning
more options, then you, will build a tree
that is much more broad.
And that that leverages search more, as
opposed to designers structuring of the
tree.
so these are big open questions.
How do we balance those two things?
But we've learned that hierarchies are a
very good way of doing that and that's
why simple algorithms that look simple
from a research point of view like SHOP.
Are very interesting from a game
developer's point of view, because
they're simple and they provide that
simple specification.
As a, as a kind of language for the
designers to use and to craft behaviors
that they can control.
The third big lesson that we've learned
is that when we're less sure about the
domain of how to build great AI, then
planning has many benefits.
And Jeff Orking mentioned that the
benefits of using planning on Fear, was
also during development, they could throw
together parts type behaviors.
And quickly get results without
necessarily understanding the impact of
the features that they were building.
They could get great-looking behaviors
quickly.
And, if you have larger, predictable open
worlds, I mean, maybe Stalker or Just
Cause.
Planning could also help if you don't
fully understand where things may end up
or how objects may interact.
So, planning is potentially a good way to
get around these problems and still
provide robust AI.
But conversely, in domains where we have
ever clear understanding of what the
problem is and what the scope of the
level is, or which objects may interact
with others.
Like tightly scripted action games,
developers building such types of games
have found themselves moving away from
planning techniques.
Because, well, they can do the same thing
without searching ahead and using more
reactive techniques instead.
the third important point and probably
one of the biggest lessons that we've
learned here is that, goal-based
architectures are very exciting from an
architectural point of view.
Regardless of whether we use planners or
not.
So, goal-based architecture is
conceptually separating what to do and
how to do it.
So, if you separate those two things, it
doesn't matter how you implement it.
You can implement that using a planner,
behavior tree, utility system, and you
still have a lot of benefits in your
architecture.
And it it turns out to be a very healthy
architectural separation.
So, you can have the designers work on
specifying what they want and have an
algorithm implement that in a different
way.
Search is just one way to implement that,
or planning is just one way to implement
that as well.
Another thing we've found is that
planning hasn't yet really made or broken
any particular game.
And like to see that, I'd like to see a
game where a planner is absolutely
necessary, but currently, we've found
that planners are just another technique
that can implement AI decision making for
characters.
And the most games could use behavior
tree utility systems relatively
interchangeably and you wouldn't really
notice much difference.
But what I would like to see, is a game
where planning is actually absolutely
required, you can not build up using a
reactive technique.
And there's been very little
investigation of that and that kind of
ties into my big opportunities for
planning and for, for these techniques in
general.
So, in the long term, I think the big
potential of planning is that we will
have more intelligent characters.
And planning is super talented and super
good at deliberation and logical
reasoning.
Figuring out how to achieve a goal based
on actions that are combined together.
And intelligence isn't the only thing
we're looking for in games.
We want the characters to be believable
and entertaining.
but intelligence helps a lot and will
help us make more believable characters
certainly.
Second big long-term promise that
planners can help us fulfill is the the
idea of a game master, or a game director
that can custom-craft or tailor an
experience for us.
So, if a designer has a plan for us, and
he cannot supervise every single game
instance in the world, then potentially
he could build a planner into that game
and
And have the planner help change, update
the story, give new quests based on
what's going on.
And really join in in the storytelling
to, to make each game experience fully
unique.
And this is something we are barely
scratching the surface of and there's a
lot of potential here.
In short-term, there's, three big things
that that I think are, are promising
avenues for planning.
The first is applying planning to other
domains and not just characters and
specifically not just enemies.
So, we've, we've done action combat games
and we've done them, too well.
Now, let's try some different types of
games, and Sims 3 is pointing in an
exciting new direction of how to
potentially use planning techniques in
different kinds of environments.
But we haven't really scratched the
surface of this either.
And, again, so not just exploring
different types of game applications, but
also different types of, games.
So, RPGs, or simulation games could also
benefit from planning.
And also, I think, in the short term, we
have a lot of potential in applying
planning techniques during the
development, as a tool.
So, if you think of a planner as a way to
compile and create a more reactive AI
that will run very efficiently, but we
can do all the computationally expensive
calculations.
Once the designers have finished
tweaking, tuning all their settings, we
should in theory know the domain fully,
that we can bake that and send that to
the customer as a reactive AI.
And that, that has everything it needs to
be able to make decisions effectively
without having to do run-time search.
Not all games will work with this but I
think there's a lot of potential in doing
that for many types of games,
surprisingly many.
So, if you'd like to find out more about
this, I've compiled a list of interviews
on all the games that we mentioned today.
All of those interviews are available on
line so, I encourage you to go and watch
them if you would like to get more
information about that.
So I've composed all those things
together.
Go to aigamedev.com/planning and you'll
be able to see that list of interviews.
And for any further references, I will
update this page and put them there as
well.
If you have any comments, of course you
can write to us on Twitter @aigamedev.
So, that was a, an overview of, of
planning in games, and I I hope you're as
excited about planning as I am.
I think we've barely just scratched the
surface, so I look forward to the, to the
next ten years of planning.
in games more so than than, almost any
other technique and it'll be exciting to
see what people come up with.
So, I hope you share that enthusiasm, and
until then, I will see you online at
AiGameDev.
Take care.
Bye.