You should now understand what tasks and
task networks are.
But I explained to you earlier that for
this approach to planning, we really need
3 new things.
Tasks, task networks and methods.
So that's what we will be looking at
next.
And while we look at methods, keep the
following in mind.
We again try to set up our planning
problem as a search problem and methods
describe ways in which we can transform
task networks.
They are plan refinements, and therefore
correspond to state transitions in our
search space.
I will start with the formal definition
of an STN method.
And the first thing we need to define
methods is a set of symbols that we can
use to denote these methods,
to name these methods uniquely.
These symbols will be disjoined from all
the others symbols we've used so unlike
task symbols which overlap with the
operators.
They will not intersect with the other
type of symbols.
Then an STN method is a 4-tuple which
means it consists of 4 things,
and these 4 things are the name, the
task, the preconditions, and the network,
and I'll explain those in entire now.
The first component is the name of the
method, and the name is a way to refer to
this method.
And again, we will use a syntactic
expression, which looks very similar to
the type of syntactic expression we've
seen for tasks and operators.
It's a symbol n, which must be one of our
unique method symbols,
followed by a set of parameters x1
through xk here, which are variable
symbols that occur in m.
And again these parameters describe the
objects that are manipulated by this
method.
The next component is the task of this
method and that is simply one of the
non-primitive tasks that we've described
earlier.
The task of a method describes what can
be accomplished with this method.
And, of course, it must be non-primitive,
as all primitive tasks can be
accomplished by an operator.
But if we have a task network that
contains a primitive task, that is, the
task of a method, then we can use this
method to accomplish the task in the
network.
The third component of a method are the
preconditions associated with that method
and again like for an operator this is
simply a set of literals that we need to
achieve before we can apply this method.
So when we apply a method these
preconditions need to be true.
They need to hold in the state where we
apply the method.
So they are very much like the
preconditions of an operator.
Note that there's no effect associated
with the method, so that distinguishes a
operator from a method quite
significantly.
And the reason for this is that in this
approach to planning we are trying to
accomplish tasks, rather then achieve
goals.
So we don't need the effects, we need the
task of the method to do planning.
The forth and final component associated
with a method is the network of the
method.
This is simply a task network consisting
simply of tasks and edges which are
ordering constaints.
And the tasks in the set U are called the
subtasks of this method and you can think
of this method as breaking down the task,
the second component of the method into
subtasks that make up the network of the
method.
So the task of the method describes what
we can accomplish, this is what we
accomplish and the sub tasks or the
network describe how we can accomplish
that task.
And there may be different methods for
the same task, but achieving the task in
different ways by having a different
network,
and usually also different preconditions.
Methods, like task networks, can be
totally ordered or partially ordered, and
that is simply a property of the network
associated with the method.
So, if this network is totally ordered,
then we say the method is totally
ordered.
If this network is partially ordered,
then we say the method is partially
ordered.
So, essentially, you can think of a
method as breaking down a task.
The task the method accomplishes into
subtasks represented by the network.
In the next few slides, I'll simply show
you some examples of STN methods, and
these are the same methods I've described
informally earlier for moving a stack of
containers to another pile respecting the
order.
And I'll start with the simplest method
from that example, namely moving the
topmost container, and that was simply a
take action followed by a put action.
And the first thing we have here is the
name of the method, which consists of a
method symbol, take and put here,
and the parameters of which there are
quite a few.
And these parameters are of course all
the objects that we need to perform the
two actions.
So I'll go through this.
C is the container that we're trying to
move, K is the krane with which we pick
it up and put it down.
This all happens at location L.
And then we have the pile in which the
container is originally.
And the pile to which it is being moved.
Then we have Xo and Xd.
These are two containers.
Xo is the container from which we are
taking the container that we're moving,
that's c.
And Xd is the destination container onto
which we're putting this container.
So these are all the objects involved in
the take and put method.
The task we accomplish with this method
is simply described here, and that's the
task as we described earlier.
So we've got a task symbol followed by
the parameters of the task.
And these are only the two piles from
which moving and to which we're moving.
And to be able to apply this method we
have a number of preconditions that need
to be satisfied.
And you should be familiar with this
notation from the way preconditions were
described for operators.
So the first precondition was that the
container that we're moving is on top of
the the origin pile, then it needs to be
on the container from which we're taking
it.
The pile needs to be at that location.
And a crane also needs to be at that
location.
Also the destination pile needs to be at
the location, and the container onto
which we're putting it, our container C,
must be the top of the destination pile.
And then finally we have the sub tasks of
the network associated with this method
simply consisting of the two primitive
tasks, take and put.
So we're taking with crane k at location
l, container c, from the origin
container, in the origin pile.
And then we need to put the container
with the same crane at the same location
the same container we just picked up onto
the destination container in the
destination pile.
These are the two sub-tasks of this
method, and as you can see I've described
them as a sequence, so they are totally
ordered which means this method is
totally ordered.
Next I will describe two methods for
accomplishing the task of moving the
whole stack.
Remember this moving the stack reverses
the order in the containers.
And the informal description said that
moving a stack can be accomplished by
repeatedly moving the topmost container
until the stack is empty.
And as you know, repetition can be
achieved through recursion, so I first
define a method, recursive-move, which
takes four parameters, namely the origin
pile, the destination pile, the container
we're trying to move, and the container
from which we're moving Moving it.
And the task that we accomplish with this
method is to move a stack from the origin
pile to the destination pile.
Remember, for the previous method, our
task was to move only the top most
container.
Here we move the whole stack.
And there are only two preconditions
associated with this method, namely that
the container, that we're trying to move,
must be at the top of the origin pile,
and it must be on top of the container, x
o, from which we're trying to take it.
Then we have 2 subtasks that we need to
accomplish, to accomplish the task of
moving the stack.
And the first subtask is that we need to
move the top most container.
And then, we have a recursive call, so to
speak.
Namely, we have the task that this method
achieves as a subtask.
So we need to move the remainder of the
stack from the origin pile to the
destination pile after we've moved the
top-most container from the origin pile
to the destination pile.
And again, the sub tasks here are totally
ordered so this is the total order
method.
But we have a 2nd method described here,
and that is the no move method.
And let me start with the task this time.
The task for this method is the same task
as before, so here have move stack from
P0 to PD.
and here we have move stack from PO to
PD.
These two methods Accomplish the same
task.
But the 2 methods have different names.
And they have different preconditions.
So, previously, we needed a container
that is on top of the origin pile.
And now, our only precondition is that
the pallet is the top of the origin pile.
Which is another way of saying that the
pile from which we are trying to move the
containers is empty.
And if the pile that we're trying to move
the stack of containers is empty than the
sub tasks are also empty.
That means there's nothing that needs to
be done to move zero containers from one
pile to another.
So the first method we've described here
implements the loop of moving the
containers repeatedly through recursion
and the second method makes sure the
recursion bottoms out.
The final example, then, is for moving a
stack via an intermediate pile, to make
sure that we maintain the original order.
So, the first move reverses the order.
And then the second moving of the stack
reverses it again.
It means we have the original order back.
And to accomplish this, we have a method
very cleverly named move stack twice.
Which takes 3 parameters.
The origin pile, the intermediate pile,
and the destination pile.
And the task that we accomplish with this
method is to move the stack in an ordered
fashion.
Move ordered stack from the origin pile
to the destination pile.
And this method is always applicable,
which we can see here.
It has no preconditions, so as long as we
can find values for the 3 parameters, we
can apply this method.
And the network associated with this
method, is again, totally ordered.
It has 2 subtasks.
And the first subtask is to move the
stack from the origin pile to the
intermediate pile.
And then, we move it from the
intermediate pile to the destination
pile.
So it's again, a totally ordered network.
Which means we have a totally ordered
method.
Which means all our methods were totally
ordered.