Now, before I explain to you how the
partial order version of this algorithm
works I want to discuss some of the
properties of this algorithm.
Let's first look at how the algorithm
chooses its actions as part of the plan
refinement for Primitive tasks.
The algorithm TFD only considers actions
that are applicable in the current state.
And that is very much like forward
search.
Forward search only looked at actions
that were applicable in the current
state.
And then, TFD also only considers actions
that are relevant.
In that sense, it's a bit like backward
search.
So it combines relevance and
applicability, from those two algorithms,
into the same algorithm.
That should help it focus its search
significantly.
Then, when we look at the plan
generation, how the algorithm assembles
its plan, what we see is that the actions
are added to the plan in the same order
in which they will be executed later,
when we try to execute the plan.
That means the current world state is
always know while we are planning.
So we're going forward through our state
space, adding more actions.
And we always know what the current wurld
state is like in which we need to apply
more actions add more actions to our
plan.
And again, this is a good thing because
that means we know where we are, and we
can apply good euristics to get to the
goal as quickly as possible.
Finally, the version of the algorithm
I've described to you is the Ground
version. So it does not follow exactly
the least commitment principle because it
uses actions where partially and
stantiated actions might be more
appropriate and reduce search.
And one way to deal with this problem is
lifting.
That means, we keep the variables in the
plan, and try to avoid unnecessary
commitments to the values of those
variables as long as possible.
This version of the algorithm is then
called Lifted-TFD.
And results in the same advantages that
would be seen for lifted backwards
search.
Namely, a reduced search space with a
lower branching.
factor.
OK and here is the psuedo code for the
ground TFD algorithm.
TFD, FD is still for forward
decomposition but P because it's partial
order.
The given network can be partial order
and the given methods can be partial
order.
The function, Ground-TFD, takes as input
a planning problem consisting of an
initial state, an initial task network, a
set of operators, and a set of methods.
So it is different from TFD because it
takes a task network as input, not just a
sequence of tasks.
But other than that, the structure of the
algorithm is very similar to what we've
seen before.
So we look at the first task in the
network, and again, the first case is
that there is no such task in the
network.
Then, if there is such a task, it can be
either primitive, this is the case here,
or it can be non primitive, which is the
final part of this algorithm.
So the first case is again the one where
the network is empty, so there is no
first task in the network.
And that means the empty plan is a
solution for this task network.
Then we get to the part where our first
task is either primitive or
non-primitive, but since this task
network is partial order, there may be
multiple tasks that are first in this
network.
First meaning it has no predecessors in
the network.
So what we have to do is choose one of
the set of all such tasks that have no
predecessors and make that the task that
we want to refine next.
So this task here is our chosen task, for
which we either want to find an action or
a method to deal with this task next in
our algorithm.
If our chosen task is primitive, then we
proceed pretty much as we've done in the
previous TFD version of the algorithm.
The first thing we have to do is compute
the set of all those actions that match
the task.
And are applicatble in our given state.
So this is the set of all actions that
fulfill these properties.
If this set is emtpy, than again we can
return failure, as this branch of the
search tree does not contain a solution
plan.
Otherwise, we can choose one of those
actions together with the substitution
that makes it the same as the task.
And we can apply the definition of a
solution here by inserting a recursive
call into our procedure.
So what we have to do is test whether a
modified version of the plan constitutes
a solution to a modified planning
problem.
And the way we modify the planning
problem is as before, we apply the action
in our current state and take that
successor as our new initial state.
Then, we give it a new network and that
new network consists of our original
network minus the task we are dealing
with here.
Actually, we're not only removing the
task here.
But also, all the edges connecting to
this task.
And then what we have to do is
instanciate the task network with the
substitution sigma.
So all the variables that we replaced to
match it to our action are now replaced
in this network.
The operators and methods are, of course,
the same as before.
They don't change.
And again, we assign the result of this
function call to our variable plan.
And if this plan, then, is failure.
That means we can return failure, because
there is no solution here.
Otherwise, we can pre-pend our action A
to this plan, and return that as a
solution plan for.
For our planning problem.
And finally, we get to the part, where
our chosen task, task, is non-primitive.
And in that case what we have to do is
again, compute the set of all methods
that are relevant for our insentient
task, and that are applicable in our
given state, s.
And if this set of methods is empty, then
again we can return failure otherwise you
have to choose one of those methods
together with the substitution, and we
apply the definition again by modifying
our problem and passing that into our
Ground-TFD procedure.
So in this case the state remains the
same, operators, methods remain the same
and all we have to modify is the network
and we do that by applying.
The decomposition function delta to our
network, where we decompose our task,
task, with the method, M, under the
substitution sigma.
And whatever this procedure returns will
be the result of our Ground-TFD
procedure.
So you can see the partial order version
of this algorithm is not much more
complicated than the total order version.
It still consists of the three branches
that are given by the definition of a
solution for a STN planning problem.