You have now seen the A* algorithm for
heuristic search and you should
understand how it works.
A* is a pretty good algorithm.
It always finds optimal solutions and it
is optimally efficient.
So you may wonder, why would we ever need
another search algorithm? Well, there are
a few more problems, and I will go into
those next.
Some of these problems are related to the
fact that we're usually searching a
graph, not a tree, so we will look at a
star as a graph search algorithm next.
And here is the pseudocode for the A*
tree and graph search algorithms.
The basic version of this algorithm is
the tree search algorithm, and there is
an extension that I've also included on
this slide which consists of three
additional lines of code, that performs
the graph search.
And the three additional lines of code
are, these.
Three lines here shown in gray.
But let's have a look at the tree search
algorithm first.
So we define a function A* tree search
that takes two parameters.
The first is our search problem, and the
second is the heuristic that we're using
This may or may not be an admissible
heuristic.
The first thing we do then, is initialize
our set of fringe nodes.
And we initialize the fringe, from our
initial state that was given in the
problem.
And what we do is, we put this initial
state.
Into a queue, into a priority queue that
sorts the node by their f value.
That means we always have quick access to
the node in that queue that has the
lowest f value and that is how we
initialize our fringe.
Then we go through the loop that does the
note expansion and generates the search
tree.
The first thing we do is we test whether
the fringe is empty.
That would mean that there would be no
more nodes to explore and that means we
can return failure because it means we
have generated the whole search tree and
haven't come across a solution node, so
there is no solution node.
So, we can return with failure.
[UNKNOWN].
But if there are nodes on the fringe,
then we have to select one of these
nodes, for expansion.
Note, that the select function here, does
not take a second argument, as it did
earlier, because our strategy here is
fixed.
We select the node with the lowest f
value.
Having said that I should point out that
this selection is not quite deterministic
as there may be many nodes with the same
f value that are currently on the fringe.
So our node is only 1 of the nodes with
the lowest f value.
And what we do next, is we perform our
goal test.
The goal test on the state contained in
that node.
And if this goal test succeeds, that
means we have found a solution, and then
we can simply return, the path, to this
node in the search tree.
If our chosen node is not a goal node,
then we have to add it's successors to
the fringe and I've shown this here as a
loop because we add each successor in
turn, and we use the function expand to
generate all the successors.
Of the selected node and our loop
variable successor here is the next
successor in that loop and then for the
tree search version of this algorithm, we
simply have to add that new successor to
the fringe.
So, we extend our current fringe with the
new successor and the place where we
queue this new successor in our priority
queue is of course the f value of that
node.
And for those of you who have been
wondering where we use the parameter h,
that is the second parameter of this
function, remember that f is defines as g
+ h, so that's where we use our heuristic
function, and that is all the pseudocode
we need for the tree search version of
this algorithm.
Algorithm.
But the graph search version isn't much
more complicated.
What we need to do in addition is first,
we need to initialize the set of all
nodes that we have seen so far.
And one way to do this is to initialize
this as a hash table.
of nodes.
And intially this will contain only the
inital state, that we can take from the
fringe or from the problem.
Then the algorithm proceeds as before,
going through the loop, trying to take a
node off the fringe if there is one.
Performing the goal test on that node.
If it's a goal node then we've found the
solution.
And if not we go to the loop where we
expand the current node and generate it's
successors, and that's where the
algorithm for graph search differs.
Namely for each successor that we're
generating we have to test whether this
is a node that we've already seen and if
we have already seen that node then we
don't need to add it to our fringe, if we
haven't seen the node then we continue as
before we add it to the fringe as our new
successor at its current f value and we
also have to add it to the set of all the
nodes we've seen before.
So that we don't explore this note again.
So this is a working version of the graph
search algorithm.
However, there is one problem with it.
If the given heuristic is admissable, the
graph search version, as shown here, no
longer guarantees an optimal solution.
And the reason for this occurs here.
Namely if we generate the successors of a
node, we may generate a new node that we
have seen before.
But the second time we generate the node,
we actually discover a shorter path than
the first time we generated it.
So what we really want to do here is keep
the node that has the shorter path and
doesn't matter whether we discovered that
first or later.
So what we could do is simply add a piece
of code here that tests whether our new
path is shorter than the old path.
But for many problems the heuristic that
we'll be using is not admissible, and
then A* doesn't guarantee as an optimal
path anyway.
So, we don't have to worry about this
shortcut question necessarily.
And here is the first problem with A* as
it stands, and that is it still uses
exponential space unless the euristics
are perfect.
In fact, in the worst case, the time and
space complexity of A*, are both an
O(b^l).
Where B is the branching factor, so
that's the number of successes we have
per node on average.
An L is the length of the path we're
looking for.
b^l is exponential, which means we have
exponential time and space complexity,
And in reality, we will see that this is
true most of the time the fringe grows
exponentially.
Now let's look at this.
What does this really mean? So
exponential time complexity.
That means when the problem grows by one
step, the size of the problem, the time
it takes to solve this problem, doubles.
Or in general, it grows by a factor of B.
This may or may not be acceptable,
depending on how much time you actually
have.
When it grows into the region of years
and centuries, this will no no, longer be
acceptable, of course.
But quite often we have another hour we
can give our.
But what about exponential space
comlexity? Well, what this means is that
a star will eventually exhaust the
computer's memory.
So first, it will eat up all the RAM,
then it'll eat up all the virtual memory.
And eventually, it'll just have no more
memory left.
And what happens then? Well A* simply
fails.
The algorithm terminates because it's out
of memory, and we don't even know whether
there is a solution or not.
As an example, the 8 puzzle will still
fit into memory, but the bigger version,
on the 4 by 4 grid, the 15 puzzle,
usually does not fit into memory.