The strips representation is based on the
idea that in a world state, we have
objects that are somehow related to each
other.
That means we need to define some
relations that we can use to relate the
objects to each other.
Relations are also known as predicates.
For a given world state, a relation
between several objects can either hold
or not hold.
That is, it is either true or false.
Here are the relation defined for the
dock worker robot domain in the PDDL
syntax.
The first predicate mentioned here is the
adjacent predicate.
Which defines when two locations are next
to each other.
So the way this works is that we name the
relation that we want to define.
And then we give the parameters to this
relation.
In this case, they are two locations.
They are denoted by variables here.
You can recognize a variable in this
syntax because it starts with a question
mark.
So this is not a specific location that
we've defined, but just a variable.
And this is followed by the minus symbol
with the type of those variables.
So what this is defining is that adjacent
is a relation that is defined over two
locations.
L1 and L2.
And again, there's a comment here that
explains this more readable.
Location L1 is adjacent to L2.
Then we have a relation attached, which
defines where a pile, P, is.
Namely at some location, L.
And the relation, belong, which defines
where the crane is also at some other
location.
Note that these variables, despite having
the same name, have no relation to each
other.
They're just used locally in this
definition of this predicate.
Together, these three relations define
the topology of the domain.
One thing that is special about these
relations is that they are static.
That is, once they are defined for a
specific state, they will never change
from state to state.
Locations are adjacent, they will always
be adjacent.
There's no action that can change that.
The other relations here are known as
dynamic or fluid relations, because they
can change from state to state.
For example, the at relation tells us
where a robot is currently, it tells us
at which location this robot is currently
located.
Then we have an occupied location, which
is a unary relation, it takes only one
argument, and tells us whether a given
location is occupied by a robot at that
location.
Then we have the loaded relation which
tells us whether there is a container
loaded onto a robot, or which container
is loaded onto a robot.
An unloaded is true if robot is not
loaded with a container.
Then we have a holding relation, which
tells us which container is held by a
crane.
And we have an empty relation, which is
true, if and only if the crane is not
holding a container.
You can see here that these relations are
not independent of each other.
For example, holding and empty are
closely related.
If the crane is empty, it cannot hold the
container.
And vice versa, if it is holding a
container, it cannot be empty.
The same goes for loaded and unloaded,
and at and unoccupied.
These two relations depend on each other.
Okay.
Remaining relations.
We have an IN relation, which tells us
where a container is, in which pile a
container is currently located.
Then we have a TOP relation, which tells
us which container is at the top of a
given pile.
And, finally, we have an ON relation,
which tells us which container's on which
other container.
The second container here can also be the
pallet, which is technically defined as a
type of container.
So these are the predicates used in the
dock worker robot domain, defined in the
PDDL syntax.
Now, here is a formal definition of what
a state in the strips representation
actually is.
So we start off with a first order
language, L.
And in this language, we have finitely
many predicate symbols.
These are the symbols we've just seen how
to define them in PDDL.
We also have finitely many constant
symbols.
These are the symbols representing the
individual objects in our domain.
And we have no function symbols.
And we haven't defined any function
symbols.
A state in a strips planning domain then
is a set of ground atoms over this
language L that we've just defined.
Let me go into this.
By an atom we mean a predicate with an
appropriate number of objects that we
have just defined in the previous slide.
An atom is considered ground when all its
arguments all the objects it relates are
real objects as opposed to variables so
there must not be variables in the atoms
we define here.
Then a state is simply a set of these
ground atoms over this language L.
Logically, we interpret this as a cun
junction that means each and everyone of
the atoms in a state holds in that state,
it must be true in that state.
So we can say that a ground atom p holds
in a state s, if and only if p is an
element of this set s.
So a state is a set of ground atoms.
And if p is an element of that set.
Then we say that p holds in that state.
And vice versa, if p is not an element of
that set.
We say that p does not hold in that
state.
We call that the closed world assumption.
And this is quite an important assumption
made by the strips representation, as we
define it here.
We can also define what it means for a
state to satisfy a set of ground
literals, G.
I need to explain this.
A literal is basically an atom that is
either a positive or a negative.
So it can be an atom or a negated atom.
G is our set of ground literals, and I've
used the letter G because eventually this
is how we will represent goals in our
planning problems.
And this is simply the symbol we use to
denote that S satisfies G.
And we consider this the case if every
positive literal in G is also in S.
So every positive literal in G holds in
S, and every negative literal in G does
not hold in S.
So it's not an element of S.
Let's illustrate this with an example.
Depicted here is a state in the Dock
Walker robot domain.
I hope you all intuitively understand
what's going on in this picture.
But for our planner we need to translate
this state into our formal representation
in the strips representation.
This means we need to define the set of
ground atoms that hold in this state.
We can do this by going through the
relations individually or in some other
order.
The first relation we defined earlier is
the adjacent relation and that tells us
which locations are reachable from which
other locations.
So we have two locations here, location
one and location two.
And they are connected by this path.
So what we have is that location one is
adjacent to location two, and vice versa.
And that's what we've got here.
We need to actually write down both ways
of this relation.
The symmetry of this relation is of
course not known to the planner
automatically.
Then we have two piles, p1 and p2.
And they are both at location one.
And that's what we express with these two
ground atoms here.
That p1 is at location one.
And p2 is also at location one.
And then we have one crane, denoted by
the symbol, crane one.
And again, we write down that the crane
one belongs to location one.
So this defines the topology of the
domain.
What we also have in this example is this
robot, R1.
And we can see here that the robot is at
location two, which is this relation
here.
And that means that location two is
occupied by this robot.
And we can also see that the robot is
unloaded, which means there's no
container on the robot.
Also the crane isn't holding a container,
so empty crane one must also hold in this
state.
Now, what remains to be described is the
two stacks of containers we see here.
The first stack consist of this container
C1 at the bottom, and C3 at the top.
And we have got here that these two
containers, C1 and C3 are both in the
pile P1.
Then we have C3 on top of C1, you can see
that here, and C1 is on top of the
pallet.
The top of the pile is the container C3
which defines this pile at location one
and that is pile one.
The second pile only contains one
container C2, and that container's in the
pile P2.
And it is immediately on the pallet and
also constitutes the top of this pile.
These are all the ground atoms that hold
in the state depicted here.
And what this means is, according to the
closed world assumption, that all the
atoms that are not mentioned in the state
do not hold.
They are not true.
For example the ground atom at our one
location one, does not hold, because at
the location one there is not the robot
R-1.
So this is false.
It is not part of our state, it is not in
that set, and the closed world assumption
means it is false.
So this is what a state looks like in the
strips representation.
It is subset of ground atoms.