Okay, so, moving on.
So now, I'll just go over a little bit of
this using a function of two variables.
Just hopefully, that'll help see something
concrete.
This is about as big as it can get while
it still makes sense on some slides.
So a, a function of two variables, we can
think of it as.
F of xy and then, oops, and then, then
the notation I, I introduced in the last
section.
I'll just say that's from r two.
So, xy would describe a point in the xy
plane.
And then f of xy is going to assign
one particular value to each point in the
xy plane.
And so, that,
that would be r.
So, you could think of it as z maybe
equals f of xy.
The partial derivatives of f are also
going to be functions of x and y.
And so this is how we would define them so
the partial of f with respect to x.
It's a function of x and y so that's why I
put this xy here.
And it's just going to be defined as the
limit.
So here when I'm taking the derivative
with respect to x, I'm just going
to add a bit to the x argument and then
subtract away the value at
my point, divide by h so that the distant
between the two points where
I have evaluated the function and then
take the limit as h goes to zero.
So that's exactly the same as the
definition of
the derivative, except that you just have
this extra y
hanging on here.
And then we do exactly the same thing for
y.
So this time I'm just adding the
perturbation to y.
And so that's going to give me the partial
derivative with respect to y.
And then the gradient of f of xy.
So I could write that as d.
So d here is an operator.
So the difference between an operator and
a function
is the output of a function is a number.
Here the output is going to be a vector of
two functions.
So the output is actually a function of x
and y.
And so instead of calling d a function,
I'm going to call it an operator.
So the output of an operator is a
function.
And then the Hessian is just going to be
made up of,
and yes, I actually did it right.
the four sort of mixed partials, although
the
ones on the diagonal are sort of hidden.
Are in disguise, because even though
they're a
mixed partial, they're the same thing
mixed with itself.
But they're also each going to be
functions of x and y.
And so now let's look at an example, so
suppose I define my function to be.
X square y cubed, and I just want to
compute both the gradient.
So df is going to be the gradient, and d
squared f is going to be hessian.
And then I want to evaluate em at the
point 1,2.
And so remember, well let's see if I.
So if I was going to try and find the
slope of a function just using
a function of one variable When I take
the derivative of my function, I get a
function.
So if I have a function of x, and I
take the derivative, I also have a
function of x.
So I'd have f prime of x.
And then, suppose I want to know what is
the slope of f of x when x is equal to 3?
I just evaluate the derivative at the
point x equals 3.
it's definitely
a mistake to evaluate the function at
three and
then take the derivative because you would
get zero.
And so for some reason everybody seems to
understand
that with a single a function of a single
variable, but then they go ahead and make
that
mistake very often when they start working
with multiple.
So, for instance When I ask, evaluate.
Ask you to evaluate it at the point 1,2.
They'll calculate the gradient correctly.
Evaluate that at the point 1,2.
And then try and take the derivative of
that again.
And the moral is, you have to take
all of the derivatives before you start
evaluating.
So.
Here I have just skipped, most of the
work, I think I just put the answers here.
So some of these are really easy to see.
So the partial derivative of x squared y
cubed with
respect to x is just going to be two 2xy
cubed.
It's also easy to see that the partial
derivative
with respect to y will be 3x squared y
squared.
It's just the power rule and treating.
The other variable, so in this case y,
in this case x, as a constant.
And then we have to compute the mixed
partials.
So here I have the partial of f with
respect to x squared
And so I all ready know what the, the
first partial is
with respect to x, so I can just plug that
in here.
And then I need to take its derivative one
more
time with respect to x, so I get 2y cubed.
The actual mixed partial, so here dy then
dx.
And again, I've already computed the
derivative of f.
Or the partial derivative of f with
respect to y.
So, I'm just going to recycle that result
rather than do it all over again.
And then, of this function, I'm going to
take the derivative with respect to x.
So, I get 6xy squared.
And then by the theorem I had.
So I hope nobody did both partial
derivatives for the quiz question,
because that was a well-behaved function,
so you could have just taken one and
then said, by the theorem, the other one
has to be equal to that.
So, I'm going to do that here.
So, this is a well-behaved function.
I can take derivatives of a polynomial
indefinitely.
At some point I hit a constant.
And then I take the derivative of that,
and I get zero.
But zero is still a valid function.
So I can continue to take the derivative
of that indefinitely.
And it just stays
zero, but it's still differentiable.
Oops.
And
then I just have to calculate the other
second order derivative.
This time, with respect to y.
And again, I'll just recycle the first
first
partial with respect to y that I've
already computed.
Take thats derivative.
And so, I get 6x squared y.
Oh, and I guess I, I put in sort of my
hidden light to gray color here.
That this is equal to the
other partial derivatove, other mixed
partial derivative.
[NOISE]
So now I'm just going to plug these into
the gradient.
So the definition of the gradient is just
a partial of the function
with respect to x and the partial the
function with respect to y.
So I can just plug in those two partial
of derivatives that I computed on the
previous slide.
And
then if I want to evaluate the gradient at
the point 1, 2 so here I have 2 times x
times y cubed so this is 2 times 1, so
that's just this one right here.
Times 2 cubed; so that's just this two
here.
And then 3 x squared, y squared.
So, 3 times 1 squared times 2 squared.
And easy enough, 16, 12.
And then, I"ll do exactly the same thing
for the gradient.
Sorry, for the Hessian.
So, first I'll just.
Plug in the formulas that I computed on
the previous slide, and remember
we get this symmetry of the off-diagonal
entries in the, in the Hessian.
And then when I want to evaluate the
Hessian of the point
1,2, I just plug in one for x and two for
y.
And so this gives me the actual value at,
of the Hessian.
But only specifically at the point 1, 2.
If I move away from 1, 2, then these
numbers here are going to change.
And so, I guess.
Where we're going to be using this when we
get to solving problems numerically.
we'll be computing the gradient and the
Hessian.
And then that's going to give our
algorithm some idea.
So based on what these numbers actually
are at a certain point.
We're going to try to move to another
point so we'll
move maybe from 1, 2 to 1, 1 and the way
we're
going to choose where we're going to move
is going to
be a function of these actual numbers that
appear in here.